<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">785E74A274E57E174383D9BC54C04DA9</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.124742</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Metal-organic atomic-layer deposition of titanium-silicon-nitride films</head><p>Jae-Sik Min, Hyung-Sang Park, and Sang-Won Kang a)</p><p>Department of Materials Science and Engineering, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Taejon, Korea ͑Received 11 May 1999; accepted for publication 19 July 1999͒ Titanium-silicon-nitride films were grown by metal-organic atomic-layer deposition at 180 °C. When silane was supplied separately in the sequence of a tetrakis͑dimethylamido͒ titanium pulse, silane pulse, and ammonia pulse, the Si content in the deposited films and the deposition thickness per cycle remained almost constant at 18 at. % and 0.22 nm/cycle, even though the silane partial pressure varied from 0.27 to 13.3 Pa. Especially, the Si content dependence is strikingly different from the conventional chemical-vapor deposition. The capacitance-voltage measurement revealed that the Ti-Si-N film prevents the diffusion of Cu up to 800 °C for 60 min.</p><p>Step coverage was approximately 100% even on the 0.3 m diam hole with slightly negative slope and 10:1 aspect ratio. © 1999 American Institute of Physics. ͓S0003-6951͑99͒01137-7͔</p><p>As the minimum feature size of semiconductor devices shrinks, the Cu diffusion barrier must be effective even when it is as thin as 10 nm because thick diffusion barriers leave little space for Cu, and thus, nullify the advantage of Cu metallization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In this respect, more effective Cu diffusion barrier materials with a thinner thickness are required. Amorphous refractory ternary metals such as ͑Ti, Ta, W͒-Si-N, W-B-N do not have fast diffusion paths such as a grain boundary present in polycrystalline materials and are promising candidates for these applications. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> These diffusion barriers need to be deposited with good step coverage, especially on the sidewall, as the aspect ratio of contact/via/ trench increases.</p><p>Metal-organic atomic-layer deposition ͑MOALD͒ achieves near-perfect step coverage and can control precisely the thickness and composition of grown films. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> We have already demonstrated that TiN film could be grown with excellent conformality by MOALD using tetrakis͑ethylmethyl-amido͒titanium and NH 3 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> However, MOALD of a ternary system may not be as easy to demonstrate as much as it is for a binary system and may not be understood straightforwardly in terms of chemical composition and growth kinetics. Therefore, in the present study, we have developed a MOALD technique for ternary Ti-Si-N films using a sequential supply of Ti͓N͑CH 3 ͒ 2 ͔ 4 ͓tetrakis͑dimethylamido͒ titanium: TDMAT͔, silane (SiH 4 ), and ammonia (NH 3 ), and evaluated the Cu diffusion barrier characteristics of a 10 nm Ti-Si-N film with high-frequency small-signal capacitance-voltage (C -V) measurements.</p><p>A MOALD apparatus was used to grow Ti-Si-N films, which is schematically similar to the one described previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> All the films were grown on SiO 2 ͑100 nm͒/Si wafers at the substrate temperature of 180 °C and with the reactor pressure maintained at 133 Pa. TDMAT was delivered from the bubbler ͑30 °C͒ to the reactor using Ar ͑70 sccm͒ as a carrier gas. Also, the flow rates of NH 3 and SiH 4 ͑forming gas with 10% SiH 4 /90% Ar͒ diluted in Ar were fixed at 70 sccm. The film thicknesses were measured by the surface profilometer. The composition of the grown film was analyzed using 9.0 MeV Cl 5ϩ elastic recoil detection time of flight ͑ERD-TOF͒, 2.43 MeV He 2ϩ Rutherford backscattering spectroscopy ͑RBS͒, and Auger electron spectroscopy ͑AES͒.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the dependence of the Si content in the Ti-Si-N film and the film deposition thickness per cycle on SiH 4 partial pressure. In this case, Ti-Si-N films were grown by a sequential supply of TDMAT for 5 s, SiH 4 for 10 s, and NH 3 for 10 s in a cyclic manner, and an Ar pulse for 20 s was inserted between each reactant gas pulse in order to isolate the reactant gases from each other. The partial pressure of SiH 4 was varied from 0.27 to 13. APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS VOLUME 75, NUMBER 11 13 SEPTEMBER 1999 1521 0003-6951/99/75(11)/1521/3/$15.00 © 1999 American Institute of Physics</p><p>increases logarithmically as the partial pressure of SiH 4 increases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> The difference between MOALD and MOCVD may originate from the fact that the Si content in the MOALD is controlled by the amount of SiH 4 that can be adsorbed on the surface during a SiH 4 pulse. As a preliminary experiment, it was observed that there was no reaction between SiH 4 and TDMAT, or SiH 4 and NH 3 at 180 °C. These results indicate that SiH 4 cannot react directly with TDMAT or NH 3 at this temperature. Thus, the amount of available adsorption sites for SiH 4 would be limited, since most of the available adsorption sites on the surface have been already occupied by TDMAT molecules, which were chemisorbed on the surface during the prior injection of the TDMAT pulse. Therefore, the Si content in the Ti-Si-N films will be controlled by the amount of SiH 4 adsorbed on the surface, not by the SiH 4 partial pressure.</p><p>On the other hand, the Ti-Si-N deposition thickness per cycle, 0.22 nm/cycle, is nearly half the value of TiN ͑0.44 nm/cycle, shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2͒</ref>. As mentioned above, SiH 4 cannot react directly with TDMAT or NH 3 at this MOALD temperature of 180 °C. Thus, SiH 4 can only take part in the Ti-Si-N formation during the reaction between TDMAT and NH 3 . Therefore, when the substrate covered with both TDMAT and SiH 4 is exposed to the NH 3 pulse, the reaction between TDMAT and NH 3 should at first occur on the surface. And then, the SiH 4 adsorbed on the surface could be involved into the Ti-Si-N formation. But, excess SiH 4 would still remain on the surface after the end of the NH 3 pulse and act as a blockade toward the adsorption of TDMAT during the following TDMAT pulse of the next cycle. Consequently, the total quantity of TDMAT and NH 3 that contributes to the film growth during one cycle would be decreased, and it would result in reduction of the Ti-Si-N deposition thickness per cycle.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>  FIG. 3. 1 kHz C -V measurements for MOS capacitors, Cu ͑100 nm͒/10 nm Ti-Si-N barrier layer ͑or without the barrier layer͒/SiO 2 ͑100 nm͒/N-type Si. ͑a͒ and ͑b͒ are the C -V profiles for the MOS capacitor without the barrier layer before and after thermal treatment at 600 °C for 60 min in H 2 ͑10%͒/Ar ͑90%͒, respectively. ͑c͒ is the C -V profiles for the MOS capacitor with a 10 nm Ti-Si-N barrier layer after thermal treatment at 800 °C for 60 min in H 2 ͑10%͒/Ar ͑90%͒. FIG. 4. Cross-sectional SEM micrograph of a 50 nm Ti-Si-N film grown by MOALD at 180 °C. Step coverage of the Ti-Si-N film is approximately 100% even on the 0.3 m diam hole with slightly negative slope and 10:1 aspect ratio.</p><p>nm͒/N-type Si, were fabricated to investigate the Cu diffusion barrier characteristics of the MOALD Ti-Si-N film. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref> shows the C -V profiles measured at the 1 kHz frequency of a small signal. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>, ͑a͒ and ͑b͒ are the C -V profiles for the MOS capacitor without the barrier layer before and after thermal treatment at 600 °C for 60 min in H 2 ͑10%͒/Ar ͑90%͒, respectively. ͑c͒ is the C -V profile for the MOS capacitor with a 10 nm Ti 0.32 Si 0.18 N 0.50 barrier layer after thermal treatment at 800 °C for 60 min in H 2 ͑10%͒/Ar ͑90%͒. In the case of ͑a͒, the C -V profile shows the typical high-frequency small-signal C -V characteristics. However, in the case of ͑b͒, the C -V profile shows low-frequency C -V characteristics in spite of the 1 kHz small-signal C -V measurement. This will come from the Cu atoms diffused into the N-type Si, because Cu atoms form deep donor levels and can act as the generation and recombination centers of electron-hole pairs. But, in the case of ͑c͒, the C -V profile shows no change by thermal treatment at 800 °C for 60 min, compared with the case of ͑a͒. It is revealed that the 10 nm Ti-Si-N film grown by MOALD performs the role of the Cu diffusion barrier up to 800 °C for the 60 min well.</p><p>The MOALD process has great potential for excellent step coverage on severe surface topography due to the com-plete surface reaction. Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the cross-sectional scanning electron microscope ͑SEM͒ image of the 50 nm Ti-Si-N film grown by the same method as in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. It clearly demonstrates the perfect step coverage of MOALD even on the 0.3 m diam hole with slightly negative slope and 10:1 aspect ratio.</p><p>A MOALD for Ti-Si-N was developed by alternate supply of TDMAT, SiH 4 , and NH 3 at 180 °C. The MOALD Ti-Si-N films showed excellent Cu diffusion barrier performance with 10 nm thickness up to 800 °C for 60 min. MOALD is a promising deposition method for Ti-Si-N with less than 10 nm thickness as a Cu diffusion barrier film.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. Dependence of the Si content in the Ti-Si-N films and deposition thickness per cycle on the SiH 4 partial pressure for the films grown on SiO 2 at the substrate temperature of 180 °C. Ti-Si-N films were grown by sequential supply of TDMAT for 5 s, SiH 4 for 10 s, and NH 3 for 10 s.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,330.49,519.78,214.56,185.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>FIG. 2. Dependence of the Si content in the Ti-Si-N films and deposition thickness per cycle on the SiH 4 /NH 3 ratio for the films grown on SiO 2 at the substrate temperature of 180 °C. SiH 4 and NH 3 were simultaneously supplied in the sequence of TDMAT for 5 s and SiH 4 /NH 3 for 10 s. On the contrary, when TDMAT and NH 3 were alternately supplied without SiH 4 , the saturated TiN deposition thickness per cycle was 0.44 nm/cycle.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,65.75,53.76,217.20,193.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Murarka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steigerwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gutmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MRS Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1993</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gutmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Cow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kaloyeros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lanford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Muraka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">262</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1995</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kolawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nicolet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">236</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1993</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sminth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nicolet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">262</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1995</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pessa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1986</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Appl. Phys., Part</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1998</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Custer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1997</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
