<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Deposition of Metal Tellurides and Selenides Using Alkylsilyl Compounds of Tellurium and Selenium</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Viljami</forename><surname>Pore</surname></persName>
							<email>viljami.pore@helsinki.fi</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UniVersity of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>FI-00014</postCode>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Timo</forename><surname>Hatanpa ¨a ¨</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UniVersity of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>FI-00014</postCode>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mikko</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UniVersity of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>FI-00014</postCode>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Markku</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UniVersity of Helsinki</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>FI-00014</postCode>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Deposition of Metal Tellurides and Selenides Using Alkylsilyl Compounds of Tellurium and Selenium</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">906D4D22B2E6C3D27A14145552321569</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1021/ja8090388</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received November 18, 2008</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Compounds with a general formula (R 3 Si) 2 Te and (R 3 Si) 2 Se react efficiently with various metal halides to produce telluride and selenide materials. By using this chemistry in atomic layer deposition (ALD), various metal selenide and telluride thin films including the phase change material germanium antimony telluride (GST) can be deposited in a highly controlled manner.</p><p>Metal selenide and telluride thin films have been gaining continuously increasing interest. Two well-known examples are CuInSe 2 solar cell absorber and Ge 2 Sb 2 Te 5 phase change material. Phase-change random-access memory (PCRAM) is a promising technology for future nonvolatile data storage. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> To be successful PCRAM must be scaled down to dimensions on the order of a few tens of nanometers or less, and the material has to be deposited conformally. <ref type="bibr">1b,c,2</ref> Therefore chemical deposition techniques, preferably ALD, are needed.</p><p>ALD is a unique modification of the chemical vapor deposition method for highly controlled deposition of thin films. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> Unique to ALD is that precursor vapors are brought onto the substrates alternately, one at a time, separated by purging periods with inert gas. The film grows via saturative surface reactions between the incoming precursor and the surface species left from the previous precursor. When all the reactions are saturative and no precursor decomposition takes place, the film growth is self-limiting providing a number of attractive features, such as easy and accurate film thickness control down to an atomic layer level, excellent large area uniformity, and unrivalled conformality on complex-shaped substrates.</p><p>The success of ALD depends strongly on appropriate precursor compounds. Reaching the self-limiting growth conditions places strict demands on the precursors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">4</ref> Besides volatile, they should be thermally stable against self-decomposition but at the same time also show high reactivity toward surface species formed by the other precursor. As decomposition cannot be exploited for the ligand elimination, the precursors must be chosen so that the ligands will be effectively eliminated by exchange reactions. Considering nonmetals, and the group 16 elements in particular, hydrides are often an ideal choice as they allow clean ligand elimination by protonation. However, hydrides of many nonmetals are highly toxic. In group 16 water of course is without this concern, and H 2 S can be used with appropriate precautions because its odor threshold limit is much lower than the harmful level. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">5</ref> By contrast, the hydrides of selenium and tellurium would require extensive safety systems and exhaust gas treatment. Alkyl compounds of selenium and tellurium have been quite widely used in CVD 6 but it appears that in ALD they cannot provide efficient exchange reactions with the common metal precursors. Therefore ALD of metal selenides and tellurides has been scarce, 7 and mostly limited to selenides and tellurides of zinc and cadmium because these are the rare cases where elements can be used as precursors for both constituents. <ref type="bibr">7a-e</ref> In addition, for GST, plasma enhanced ALD has been attempted but the outcome has been a combination of CVD and ALD growth at best. 8 Thus there is an obvious need to develop efficient ALD processes for metal selenides and tellurides. In this paper we show a breakthrough in metal selenide and telluride ALD by exploiting alkylsilyl compounds (R 3 Si) 2 Se and (R 3 Si) 2 Te as precursors.</p><p>Compared to alkyls and alkylamides of Se and Te, (R 3 Si) 2 Se and (R 3 Si) 2 Te offer a much more straightforward reaction route for the elimination of ligands of the metal precursors. In (R 3 Si) 2 Se and (R 3 Si) 2 Te silicon, a hard Lewis acid is bonded to the heavy group 16 elements which are soft Lewis bases, thus forming an unfavorable hard-soft Lewis acid-base pair. Upon exchange reaction with metal chlorides, for example, silicon becomes bonded to the harder base:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(R 3 Si) 2 Te(g) + MCl 2 (g) f MTe(s) + 2R 3 SiCl(g) (1)</formula><p>Further, if the metal of the metal chloride is soft Lewis acid, the other product of the exchange reaction will form a favorable soft-soft Lewis acid-base combination (M-Se or M-Te). Indeed, <ref type="bibr">Groshens et al. 9</ref> reported that (Me 3 Si) 2 Te together with Sb(NMe 2 ) 3 deposit stoichiometric Sb 2 Te 3 in CVD at very low temperatures and that the growth occurs, quite untypical for CVD, through stoichiometric exchange reactions between the two precursors. These observations are very promising in what comes to the reactivity requirements of ALD precursors. <ref type="bibr">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">4</ref> (Et 3 Si) 2 Se, (Et 3 Si) 2 Te, and ( t BuMe 2 Si) 2 Te were synthesized in good yields by reacting Na 2 Se 10a or Li 2 Te 10a with Et 3 SiCl or t BuMe 2 SiCl following literature methods. 10b Chlorosilanes larger than Me 3 SiCl were chosen to make less volatile tellurium/selenium compounds for safety reasons during the synthesis and use. (Et 3 Si) 2 Se and (Et 3 Si) 2 Te are liquids at room temperature while ( t BuMe 2 Si) 2 Te is a low melting solid (mp 44 °C). The compounds prepared were analyzed with 1 H NMR, 13 C NMR, MS, and TGA. Crystal structure of the only solid ( t BuMe 2 Si) 2 Te (CCDC 708333) was solved using single crystal X-ray diffraction. Molecular structure of the strictly monomeric compound is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. TGA (N 2 , normal pressure) revealed that all the compounds prepared evaporate completely. Thermal stability of the compounds was found to be remarkably high in ALD deposition tests conducted. The compounds prepared seem to be stable at least up to 400 °C. ALD film growth experiments were performed in a flow type F120 ALD reactor (ASM Microchemistry) operated at a pressure of about 10 mbar. First binary antimony and germanium telluride processes were examined with SbCl 3 and GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 as precursors.</p><p>Both synthesized Te precursors were shown to result in Sb 2 Te 3 film growth, but (Et 3 Si) 2 Te was chosen for further studies because of its easier handling (liquid). The saturative growth of Sb 2 Te 3 from SbCl 3 and (Et 3 Si) 2 Te on native silicon oxide is demonstrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. As characteristic to ALD, the growth rate clearly saturates to around 0.6 Å/cycle when both pulse lengths are increased. An exceptionally low deposition temperature of 60 °C was possible because SbCl 3 and (Et 3 Si) 2 Te show high reactivity and evaporate sufficiently from open vessels inside the reactor at 30 and 40 °C, respectively. The composition of the films was very close to Sb 2 Te 3 and no chlorine could be detected by EDX. The reaction thus appears to be very efficient at such a low temperature. When the deposition temperature was raised the growth rate started to decrease. With 1 s pulse times the growth rate dropped to 0.17 Å/cycle at 90 °C and further to only 0.02 Å/cycle at 140 °C. The films were crystalline showing the reflections of rhombohedral Sb 2 Te 3 (ICDD-PDF-015-0874) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</p><p>Next, GeTe films were grown using (Et 3 Si) 2 Te and a germanium dichloride dioxane complex GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 . The evaporation temperature for the Ge precursor was 70 °C which allowed the use of a low deposition temperature in this case also. A growth rate of 0.42 Å/cycle was obtained for the GeTe films at a deposition temperature of 90 °C. According to EDX the films were slightly Ge rich with a composition of 54% Ge and 46% Te. XRD indicated that the films were crystalline rhombohedral GeTe (ICDD-PDF-047-1079) with a noticeable fraction of amorphous phase (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</p><p>In addition to SbCl 3 and GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 , other antimony and germanium precursors that resulted in film growth with (Et 3 Si) 2 Te at a growth temperature of 140 °C were Sb(OEt) 3 and GeBr 2 . Film growth was not observed with Sb(NMe 2 ) 3 , Ge(N(SiMe 3 ) 2 ) 2 , Ge(O t - Bu) 2 , GeCl 4 , or GeBr 4 at the same temperature but a wider range of deposition temperatures should of course be covered before these compounds can be completely excluded.</p><p>The Sb 2 Te 3 and GeTe processes using SbCl 3 , GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 , and (Et 3 Si) 2 Te as precursors were combined in order to prepare the technologically important GST films. On the basis of the results obtained with the GeTe and Sb 2 Te 3 binary processes the lowest possible deposition temperature, that is, 90 °C, was chosen for the experiments. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a</ref> depicts the composition of GST films as a function of the GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 pulse length when GeTe and Sb 2 Te 3 cycles were applied in a 1:1 ratio. With increasing GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 pulse length the Ge content increases and then saturates with pulse lengths of 4 s and more. The growth rate in these films saturated to around 0.3 Å/cycle which is in line with the growth rates of the individual binary processes at 90 °C (0.17 Å/cycle for Sb 2 Te 3 and 0.42 Å/cycle for GeTe).</p><p>Based on the saturative behavior of all the precursors, it appears possible to prepare Ge x Sb y Te z films of various compositions by ALD in a controlled manner just by adjusting the GeTe and Sb 2 Te 3 cycling ratio. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4b</ref> shows the variation of film composition when different GeTe/(GeTe+Sb 2 Te 3 ) cycling ratios were used. The Ge/Sb ratio in the films increases linearly as the GeTe/ (GeTe+Sb 2 Te 3 ) cycling ratio is increased. To get equal amounts of Ge and Sb in the films, a GeTe/(GeTe+Sb 2 Te 3 ) cycling ratio of ∼0.35 is required.</p><p>A GST film with a composition of 23% Ge, 28% Sb, and 49% Te was subjected to high temperature XRD measurements where the sample is annealed under N 2 flow and measured with XRD in    situ at 15 °C intervals. The initially amorphous film started to crystallize at 130 °C showing reflections belonging to the metastable rock salt structure. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">11</ref> Further increase in temperature transformed the film gradually at around 250-300 °C to the stable hexagonal phase. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">11</ref> These observations are consistent with earlier studies on the crystallization of GST. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">12</ref> The cubic and hexagonal phases can be clearly distinguished in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5a</ref>.</p><p>Many of the potential PCRAM structures call for deposition of GST films conformally in deep trenches and pores. <ref type="bibr">1b,c,2</ref> To study the conformality of the GST ALD process, a GeTe/(GeTe+Sb 2 Te 3 ) cycling ratio of 0.33 was used to deposit a film on a high aspectratio trench pattern. The FESEM image in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5b</ref> shows that the film thickness (∼65 nm) is virtually the same in the different parts of the structure. It can be concluded that with this precursor combination GST films can be grown conformally on complex shaped substrates in a typical ALD fashion.</p><p>In addition to Sb 2 Te 3 , GeTe, and GST many other tellurides and selenides can be deposited by ALD using alkylsilanes of tellurium and selenium as precursors. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> shows all the materials and precursor combinations that have so far been demonstrated. These include ZnTe, Bi 2 Te 3 , ZnSe, Bi 2 Se 3 , In 2 Se 3 , and Cu x Se y . Higher deposition temperatures were required for these materials to ensure sufficient evaporation of the metal precursors. It is noteworthy that the deposition of ZnTe and ZnSe at as high temperature as 400 °C was possible. The applicable temperature range for (Et 3 Si) 2 Te and (Et 3 Si) 2 Se is thus wide and the deposition of various metal tellurides and selenides is possible. The growth rate is also very good in many cases. The dramatic decrease in the growth rate of Sb 2 Te 3 with increasing temperature (see above) thus seems to be related to the Sb precursor and not to the tellurium precursor. The range of materials in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> represents successful single growth experiments and the saturative ALD growth behavior of these processes is still to be verified. The general appearance of the films was however quite good with relatively little variations apparent across the substrate. All films were crystalline as verified by XRD. Metal chlorides seem to react very efficiently with (Et 3 Si) 2 Te and (Et 3 Si) 2 Se but also other precursors, such as carboxylates and alkoxides were shown to result in film growth. Growth experiments using copper(II) pivalate and (Et 3 Si) 2 Se seemed especially interesting because depending on the deposition temperature the stoichiometry could be controlled between CuSe and Cu 2 Se. This process combined with In 2 Se 3 could allow the ALD of CuInSe 2 , a wellknown solar cell absorber, and is currently under further study.</p><p>In summary, by using alkylsilyl compounds of tellurium and selenium as precursors the ALD of many tellurides and selenides is possible, and it seems that a whole new class of ALD processes has been found.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Molecular structure of ( t BuMe 2 Si) 2 Te (thermal ellipsoids at 50%). Te to Si distances are 2.5141(13) Å and Si-Te-Si angle is 101.51(6)°.</figDesc><graphic coords="1,341.23,179.80,172.07,94.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Growth rate as a function of (a) SbCl 3 and (b) (Et 3 Si) 2 Te pulse length for Sb 2 Te 3 films deposited at 60 °C. The other precursor pulse lengths were kept at 1.0 s and all the purge lengths at 2.0 s.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,94.27,172.92,138.01,116.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Gracing incidence X-ray diffractograms of a Sb 2 Te 3 film deposited at 60 °C and a GeTe film deposited at 90 °C.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Composition of GST films as a function of (a) GeCl 2 • C 4 H 8 O 2 pulse length and (b) GeTe/(GeTe+Sb 2 Te 3 ) cycling ratio. SbCl 3 and (Et 3 Si) 2 Te pulse lengths were always 1.0 s and purges were 2.0 s.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,328.20,186.16,198.00,211.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. (a) Gracing incidence X-ray diffractograms of as-deposited and N 2 -annealed GST films. (b) Cross-section FESEM image of a GST film deposited on a high aspect-ratio trench pattern. Scale bar ) 600 nm.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Published on Web 01/05/2009 10.1021/ja8090388 CCC: $40.75  2009 American Chemical Society</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Downloaded via TU EINDHOVEN on July 18, 2025 at 14:33:38 (UTC).See https://pubs.acs.org/sharingguidelines for options on how to legitimately share published articles.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgment. <rs type="institution">ASM Microchemistry Oy</rs> is acknowledged for the financial support and <rs type="person">Mr. Mikko Heikkila</rs> ¨for the in situ XRD studies.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Supporting Information Available: Description of the precursor synthesis, film characterization, crystallographic data file (CIF) of ( t BuMe 2 Si) 2 Te and complete ref 2b. This material is available free of charge via the Internet at <ref type="url" target="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JA8090388</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solid-State Electron</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ovshinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lacaita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Breitwisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rettner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Krebs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-L</forename><surname>Lung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. ReV. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968. 2006. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IBM J. Res. DeV</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Phase Change Memory; IEEE: Interconnect Technology Conference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Breitwisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-01-04">2008. 1-4 June 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="221" />
			<pubPlace>Burlingame, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NoVel Lithography-Independent Pore Phase Change Memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breitwisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE: Symposium on VLSI Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="101" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Thin Film Materials</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nalwa</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="159" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Angew. Chem., Int. Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5548" to="5554" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">409</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Amoore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hautala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sudha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R.-Y</forename><surname>Polyhedron ; B) Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-G</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Boscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Carmalt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Parkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Vap. Deposition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996. 2006. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Appl. Phys. Lett.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pessa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename><surname>Ma ¨kela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Suntola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Appl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Phys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lett ; Ahonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pessa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Suntola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Godlewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guziewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kopalko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lusakowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dynowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Godlewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Goldys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R J</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lumin ; Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sadowski ; Yoshikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tokita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N.-T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ueng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Suh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Karam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ehsani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bhat, I. B. Proc. SPIE-Int</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kyto ¨kivi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Koskinen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rautiainen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Skarp</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1981. 1980. 1991. 2003. 1997. 1995. 2000. 1994. 1993. 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. T. Electron Technol Phys. Status Solidi B J. Cryst. Growth J. Appl. Phys. Soc. Opt. Eng</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">D. Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3969</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Chem. Mater.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Low Temperature MOCVD growth of V/VI Materials Via a Me 3 SiNMe 2 Elimination Reaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Groshens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gedridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lowe-Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mater ; Groshens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gedridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scheri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994. 1996</date>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">430</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bhasin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Indian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chem ; Detty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Seider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Org. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1354</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1991, 30A, 632. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsunaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kubota</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">685</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Friedrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Weidenhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4130" to="4134" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
