<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Atomic layer deposition of GeSe films using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se with the discrete feeding method for the ovonic threshold switch</title>
				<funder ref="#_5jjbWte">
					<orgName type="full">Ministry of Science, ICT, and Future Planning of Korea</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-07-02">2 July 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Woohyun</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-7578-4813</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sijung</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chanyoung</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eui-Sang</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jeongwoo</forename><surname>Jeon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Young</forename><forename type="middle">Jae</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kyung</forename><forename type="middle">Seok</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Han</forename><forename type="middle">Joon</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yoon</forename><forename type="middle">Kyeung</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Cheol</forename><forename type="middle">Seong</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
							<email>cheolsh@snu.ac.kr</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-6254-9758</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Seong</forename><surname>Cheol</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-6254-9758</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">and Inter-University Semiconductor Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08826</postCode>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Atomic layer deposition of GeSe films using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se with the discrete feeding method for the ovonic threshold switch</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-07-02">2 July 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C03098EC7D90BC6DB9750D6AEC1FCBFC</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1088/1361-6528/aacda0</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 29 March 2018, revised 27 May 2018 Accepted for publication 19 June 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>atomic layer deposition</term>
					<term>discrete feeding method</term>
					<term>phase change material</term>
					<term>ovonic threshold switch</term>
					<term>germanium selenide</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The ovonic threshold switch (OTS) based on the voltage snapback of amorphous chalcogenides possesses several desirable characteristics: bidirectional switching, a controllable threshold voltage (V th ) and processability for three-dimensional stackable devices. Among the materials that can be used as OTS, GeSe has a strong glass-forming ability (∼350 °C crystallization temperature), with a simple binary composition. Described herein is a new method of depositing GeSe films through atomic layer deposition (ALD), using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se as Ge and Se precursors, respectively. The stoichiometric GeSe thin films were formed through a ligand exchange reaction between the two precursor molecules, without the adoption of an additional reaction gas, at low substrate temperatures ranging from 70 °C-150 °C. The pseudo-saturation behavior required a long time of Ge precursor injection to achieve the saturation growth rate. This was due to the adverse influence of the physisorbed precursor and byproduct molecules on the efficient chemical adsorption reaction between the precursors and reaction sites. To overcome the slow saturation and excessive use of the Ge precursor, the discrete feeding method (DFM), where HGeCl 3 is supplied multiple times consecutively with subdivided pulse times, was adopted. DFM led to the saturation of the GeSe growth rate at a much shorter total injection time of the Ge precursor, and improved the film density and oxidation resistance properties. The GeSe film grown via DFM exhibited a short OTS time of ∼40 ns, a ∼10 7 ON/OFF current ratio, and ∼10 4 selectivity. The OTS behavior was consistent with the modified Poole-Frenkel mechanism in the OFF state. In contrast, the similar GeSe film grown through the conventional ALD showed a low density and high vulnerability to oxidation, which prevented the OTS performance. The ALD method of GeSe films introduced here will contribute to the fabrication of a three-dimensionally integrated memory as a selector device for preventing sneak current.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Phase-change random access memory (PcRAM) is a strong candidate for the next-generation memory, with characteristics of non-volatility, fast operating speed, and low power consumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The three-dimensional-(3D)-stackable memory of the crossbar array has been proposed as a promising solution to overcome the existing limitations in the memory density of the PcRAM in a 2D planar integration structure. Despite the advances in 3D structural designs to scale down the memory, sneak current, which frustrates the accurate reading/writing of data in each cell, has remained a critical issue. Selector devices like the P-N junction diodes, metal-insulator-metal diodes, and ovonic threshold switch (OTS) have been devised to minimize these errors in operation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Among the options for the selector device, the OTS using amorphous chalcogenides has the preferable property of a bidirectional, controllable threshold voltage (V th ) and process compatibility with chalcogenide-based phase change materials. The material properties required in OTS, however, are different from those needed in PcRAM. For the memory element, both the appropriate crystallization speed and amorphous stability are among the essential requirements since the memory operation is based on the reversible change between the crystal and amorphous phases. The pseudo-binary system of GeTe-Sb 2 Te 3 has shown to possess the desirable properties. In the case of OTS, only the latter requirement on the amorphous stability is critical since the threshold switching is the characteristics of the amorphous phase, and no crystallization is involved for the material function as a selector.</p><p>Recent studies have shown that GeSe is one of the strongest candidates for OTS owing to its high amorphous stability (with a crystallization temperature [T cry ] as high as ∼350 °C), with a simple binary composition <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. The GeSe-based OTS device is often used as a selector component in a 1-selector-1-resistor (1S1R) structure for the stable operation of the crossbar arrays of random access memory. Previous studies successfully demonstrated a the 1S1R structure consisting of the stacking layers of the GeSe and resistive memory layer as a selector and memory element, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. Researchers also investigated the dependence of thermal stability and V th on the Ge concentration in Ge x Se (1-x) compounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Additionally, Sband N-doped Se-rich GeSe films have been proven to improve the performance of OTS <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Although the previous studies provided valuable information on the relation between the compositions and the OTS behavior, the adopted physical vapor deposition methods have limited applicability in the fabrication of 3D-stackable-matrix-integrated devices, due to their limited step coverage.</p><p>Atomic layer deposition (ALD), by comparison, possesses ideal properties, such as excellent conformality for the construction of complex, high-aspect-ratio structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The authors reported several ALD cases of GeTe 2 or GeTe films using Ge(IV) or Ge(II) precursors such as Ge(OEt) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> , Ge{N[Si(CH 3 ) 3 ] 2 } 2 , and HGeCl 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. In the case of the alkoxy-Ge precursor, non-ideal physisorption (lack of strong chemical adsorption) and the high oxidation state (+4) limit its use in the deposition of GeSe <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>. Recently, HGeCl 3 was reported to have shown a prominent ALD behavior in the deposition of GeTe as it acted as a Ge(II) source without requiring an additional gas for its reaction, and no incubation cycles were involved <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17]</ref>. Despite the achievement in the conformal and uniform morphologies of the GeTe 2 and GeTe films in previous studies, these unconventional precursors may cause complicated ALD growth behaviors due to the steric hindrance from the physisorbed molecules (i.e., precursors, byproducts). Various modified ALD methods have been suggested to be used to address this undesirable phenomenon. The discrete feeding method (DFM) has been shown to efficiently remove the physisorbed molecules in a HfO 2 deposition by subdividing the precursor pulse and purge times <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. It has also contributed to the improved film properties, such as a higher film density and a low impurity concentration, owing to the more fluent ALD reaction steps.</p><p>In this work, ALD of binary GeSe using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si)] 2 Se as the Ge and Se precursors, respectively, was studied. The 1:1 stoichiometry of GeSe was achieved by the ligand exchange reaction between the Se precursor and the GeCl 2 produced by the decomposition of HGeCl 3 . DFM was introduced for the Ge deposition steps, to overcome the extended Ge pulse and purge times for the saturation of the growth rate in the conventional ALD process. The method resulted in great improvements in the saturation behavior, surface morphology, and film density. The additional effects on the chemical and amorphous phase stability were also investigated. The GeSe film grown via DFM exhibited a short OTS time of ∼40 ns, a ∼10 7 ON/OFF current ratio, and ∼10 4 selectivity. The OTS behavior was consistent with the modified Poole-Frenkel (PF) mechanism, with the fitting parameters of 5.36×10 20 cm -3 charge trap density and 1.41×10 -7 cm inter-trap distance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experiment</head><p>The deposition of GeSe films was performed using a showerhead-type ALD tool with a 6 inch-wafer chamber (CN-1, atomic-premium). All the ALD lines where the precursor passed were maintained at 100 °C. The substrate temperature of the deposition stage was 70 °C, except for the experiments that were performed to determine the effect of the temperature. The Ge and Se precursors were HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se, respectively. Each of the precursors was placed in a separate stainless steel canister. The Ge precursor was maintained at 3 °C, and the Se precursor, at 30 °C. The vapor pressures of HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se were approximately 30 and 2 Torr at their respective canister temperatures. Due to the high vapor pressure of HGeCl 3 , the pulsed amount of the Ge precursor was regulated using a manually operated metering valve, and was diluted with 50 standard cubic centimeters per minute (sccm) Ar gas. It was delivered through the vapor draw method rather than through the bubble-type method. On the other hand, the Se precursor was carried into the chamber by being made to pass 50 sccm Ar gas using the bubble-type method. After each precursor injection sequence, the excess precursors and byproducts were purged out using 200 sccm Ar gas. The process recipes of the ALD sequence were designed to prevent a gas phase reaction between the precursors. The precursor sequence of the conventional ALD was determined as follows, through the ALD saturation experiments: Ge precursor pulse (7 s)-purge (15 s)-Se precursor pulse (2 s)-purge (15 s). To confirm the ALD-type saturation behavior, the process time of each step was varied while the other process time was kept constant. The recipe for ALD-DFM is Ge precursor pulse (1 s) -purge (5 s)-pulse (1 s)-purge (5 s) -pulse (1 s)-purge (5 s)-Se precursor (2 s)-purge (15 s). In this case, the 7 s long Ge precursor pulse time was shortened to 3 s but was divided into three 1 s's, and the 15 s long purge time was divided into three 5 s's while the Se precursor pulse and purge times remained unchanged. For comparison, the conventional ALD process with 3 s long Ge precursor pulses was also tested. The reaction mechanism between HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se was similar to that of the previously reported [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Te <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. The DFM, however, effectively removed the physisorbed molecules. Thermally oxidized 200 nm thick SiO 2 /Si and TiN/Ti/SiO 2 /Si were used as substrates, in which 50 and 5 nm thick TiN and Ti films, respectively, were deposited via reactive and direct-current (DC) sputtering.</p><p>The layer densities of the deposited films were measured via x-ray fluorescence spectroscopy (Thermo Scientific, Quant'X EDXRF), and the growth rate was the layer density value divided by the number of cycles. A resistivity-temperature experiment was performed using the real-time resistivity-temperature measurement system (homemade). Both the crystallinity and density of the films were measured with x-ray equipment (glancing angle incidence x-ray diffraction (GAXRD) and x-ray reflectivity (XRR), respectively), using an x-ray diffractometer (PANalytical, X'Pert PRO MPD). The impurity level of each film was confirmed via Auger electron spectroscopy (AES, ULVAC-PHI, PHI-700). Scanning electron microscopy (SEM, Hitachi, S-4800) and atomic force microscopy (AFM, JEOL, JSPM 5200) were used to observe the morphology of the film surface. X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS, UK VG, Sigma Probe) was used to confirm the chemical states of the elements in the films. The fast Fourier transform (FFT) image was analyzed via transmission electron microscopy (TEM, JEOL, JEM-2100F), using a specimen prepared with a focused ion beam (FEI, Helios 650).</p><p>The OTS devices were fabricated using hole pattern substrates and while proceeding with each 100 cycles sequence of the conventional ALD process, and with the DFM process (where the hole diameter and depth were 2 μm and 50 nm, respectively) formed in a SiO 2 layer. The hole was filled with W, which played the role of the bottom electrode. The schematic diagram of this OTS device will be shown later. A pulse generator (Agilent, 81110 A) and an oscilloscope (Tektronix, TDS 684 C) were used to observe the TS behavior of the films. The DC characteristics of the device were measured using a semiconductor parameter analyzer (Hewlett Packard, 4145B). Both experiments were conducted using a probe station (Cascade, REL-5500).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">ALD behavior of GeSe films</head><p>GeSe films were deposited by ALD sequence with and without DFM using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se. The conventional ALD process refers to the ALD without the DFM process, where Ge and Se pulse and purge were injected alternatively (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(a)</ref>). The ALD with DFM, by comparison, divides the total Ge pulse and purge times into several shorter times. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(b) describes the ALD-DFM sequence, where the Ge purge and pulse injection was subdivided into three consecutive pulses while keeping the total injection time the same as that in the conventional ALD process.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the growth behavior of the GeSe film deposited through the conventional ALD method using HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si)] 2 Se as Ge and Se precursors, respectively. As previously reported, HGeCl 3 is known to readily decompose into GeCl 2 and HCl at the relevant process temperatures. Under the adopted experiment conditions (canister temperature: 3 °C; ALD line temperature: 100 °C), the Ge precursor is pulsed into the chamber as coexisting three molecules (HGeCl 3 , GeCl 2 , HCl). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2(a)</ref> show two reaction mechanisms between the Ge and Se precursors during the deposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</p><p>The reactions follow mechanisms similar to the reactions between HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Te, as identified in the previous work on the ALD deposition of the GeTe film <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. According to the reaction mechanisms presented in figure 2(a), the deposition is expected to result in the stoichiometric GeSe film, which was indeed the case, as discussed below. The saturation growth rate (48.1±1.8 ng cm -2 cy -1 ) and the 1:1 stoichiometric GeSe composition were achieved for the Ge and Se precursors' pulse and purge times (Ge pulse: 7 s; Ge purge: 15 s; Se pulse: 2 s; Se purge: 15 s). The self-limiting growth behavior revealed that ligand exchange reaction occurred on the growing surface. Compared to the short injection time of the Se precursor for the saturation growth rate (2 s), however, the Ge precursor requires a 7 s injection time to achieve the saturation growth rate (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2(b)</ref>). This pseudo-saturation behavior is also reflected in the long Ge and Se purge times (∼15 s) for  saturation, as shown in figures 2(c) and (e). This is inconsistent with the previous report on the ALD of GeTe, where the growth rate is saturated with a 5 s purge time <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. A possible reason for this discrepancy will be discussed later.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows that DFM can improve the pseudo-saturation behavior. Here, a Ge precursor was injected through three 1 s consecutive pulses (total pulse time: 3 s) to compare its growth rate with the growth rate from the conventional ALD process. In DFM, the purge was also adjusted to three 5 s consecutive Ar pulses (total purge time: 15 s). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(a)</ref> shows that the growth rate reaches the saturation level with three 1 s Ge pulses (46.7 ng cm -2 cy -1 ). The rate is significantly larger than that from the conventional ALD process with a 3 s Ge pulse, and is comparable to the saturated value of the conventional ALD (7 s) within an error range. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(b</ref>) compares the growth rates of the GeSe film depending on the relative amount of Ge precursor injection with a given Ge pulse time (3 s). Due to the high vapor pressure of HGeCl 3 , the amount of the Ge precursor injection was adjusted by limiting the opening of a metering valve manually. The injection amount was reduced through the partial closure of the valve by changing the valve rotation number from the initial 3 to 2 and 1. It should be noted that the input amount control is only relative and not absolute because the information on the absolute amount depending on the valve rotation was not available. In all the cases, the DFM resulted in higher growth rates than with the conventional method, and showed a saturated growth rate with a reduced precursor amount (blue circle data in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(b)</ref>). Therefore, the DFM with the present conditions (three-time rotation of the manual valve and 1 s injection x 3) represents the fully saturated ALD growth despite its much shorter total Ge precursor pulse time. An even more important finding is that this faster saturation in DFM drastically enhanced the film quality and the OTS performance of the device compared with the similar film prepared through the conventional ALD process, as will be shown later. The conventional ALD method, however, showed a proportionally decreasing growth rate as the injection amount was reduced, consistent with the undersaturated condition of the 3 s Ge pulse time (red square data in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(b)</ref>).</p><p>The larger amount of precursor injection and the longer extended time required for its saturated growth in the conventional ALD process can be attributed to the screening of the reaction sites by the physisorbed molecules and reaction byproducts. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(c)</ref> shows the mechanism of the efficient removal of the physisorbed molecules through the DFM process. In the proposed mechanism, the same ligand exchange reaction occurs as the conventional ALD process in the DFM, but the discretized feeding of the precursor can efficiently remove the steric hindrance from the physical absorption of the precursor molecules or byproducts (i.e., HCl, (CH 3 ) 3 Si-Cl) during the intermittent purge steps. The results are consistent with those of the previous study on DFM for the ALD of HfO 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. In this ALD equipment, 1 s is the lower limit of the ALD valve opening with accurate flow control. Therefore, the further subdivision of the 1 s long pulse was not attempted. The data in figures 3(a) and (b) demonstrate, however, that the observed growth rate was the DFM-saturated growth rate.</p><p>The proposed mechanism of the efficient removal of the physisorbed molecules helps in the understanding of the difference in the ALD behaviors of GeTe and GeSe films with the conventional feeding method. In the previous report on GeTe, the growth rate saturated rapidly with only a 5 s purge time <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. The different bonding type can explain the different saturation behavior in the conventional ALD of Ge-Te and Ge-Se films. The deposited GeTe has a non-polar bonding nature due to the minimal difference in electronegativity between Ge and Te (0.09, in the Pauling electronegativity scale) while GeSe has a polar bonding nature due to the larger difference in electronegativity (0.54) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>. The polarity of the Ge-Se bonds induces a stronger dipole-dipole interaction between the film surface and the pulsed HGeCl 3 and other byproducts, possibly leading to the stronger (physical) adsorption of the molecules compared to the non-polar van der Waals forces <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. This stronger attraction can screen the reaction sites of the growing surface much more efficiently compared with the ALD in the GeTe case, and requires extended pulse and purge injection times to complete the reaction.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>(a) shows the layer densities of the GeSe films grown at a substrate temperature of 70 °C, as a function of the number of cycles, to determine the saturation growth rate and incubation cycles. Here, both the conventional ALD and ALD-DFM methods adopted saturated conditions for the precursor and purge injection times (conventional ALD: Ge precursor pulse (7 s)-purge (15 s)-Se precursor pulse (2 s) -purge (15 s); ALD-DFM: Ge precursor pulse (1 s)-purge (5 s)-pulse (1 s)-purge (5 s)-pulse (1 s)-purge (5 s)-Se precursor (2 s)-purge (15 s)). The graphs for the conventional ALD reveal that the film grows linearly with the cycle number, without significant incubation cycles. From the linear fitting, the 48.26 and 43.84 ng cm -2 cy -1 growth rates on the SiO 2 and TiN substrates, respectively, were confirmed. The growth rate of the film thickness can be calculated by dividing the growth rate in ng cm -2 cy -1 by the film density obtained from XRR measurement, and the converted rate of 1.12 Å cy -1 was obtained. The x value in Ge x Se (1-x) was also shown to be ∼0.5 regardless of the number of cycles. Overall, the results suggest a reasonable growth rate and a stoichiometry consistent with the reaction mechanism expected for normal ALD <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23]</ref>. The saturated growth rate from the DFM cannot be similarly estimated because only two data points are available (25 and 100 cycles). These data points (red diamond), however, precisely lie on the graphs from the conventional ALD process, suggesting a similar growth behavior.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>(b) shows the effect of the substrate temperature on the film growth in the conventional ALD process. The rates decreased from 46.5 to 3.2 ng cm -2 cy -1 on the SiO 2 as the temperature changed from 70 °C to 150 °C. The x value in Ge x Se (1-x) was shown to be ∼0.5 °C at 120 °C but to have a slight increased at 140 °C. The change in the Ge content was possibly due to the desorption of the volatile Se at a high temperature. The higher Ge content at a higher temperature suggests that the oxidation state of Ge remains close to +2 even under a high-temperature condition that could have led its oxidation to Ge(IV). The results confirm that even if the undissociated HGeCl 3 participated in the reaction, it did not directly affect the composition. After the ligand exchange reaction, H with the -1 oxidation state in the reaction site (HCl 2 -Ge-Se) is changed to the +1 oxidation state by a redox reaction with Ge(IV) and eliminated as HCl after binding with Cl <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. If the Ge precursors were already dissociated into GeCl 2 and HCl, only the +2 oxidation form of the Ge precursor (GeCl 2 ) reacted in the chamber to form GeSe films.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> compares the surface morphology of the GeSe film deposited through 100 cycles of the conventional ALD or ALD-DFM processes. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>(a) shows that the film deposited through the conventional method did not uniformly cover the substrate. The local variation in the amount of deposition indicates the existence of screened reactive sites during the deposition. The surface morphology was significantly improved by the DFM, as shown in the SEM and AFM images in figures 5(b) and (d), respectively. The root mean square roughness was determined to be 4.41 and 6.42 nm for the films grown through the conventional ALD process on SiO 2 and TiN substrates, respectively, and were changed into 0.350 and 0.514 nm for the films grown through the ALD-DFM process (figures 5(c) and (d)). This is a more-than-one-order-of-magnitude improvement in surface roughness, which already implies that the film quality can be quite different.</p><p>XRR and AES depth profiling were performed on GeSe films grown with the 100 cycles of the conventional ALD and ALD-DFM processes on SiO 2 substrates. Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6(a</ref>    show the XRR measurements and fittings with a Si/SiO 2 /GeSe sample structure. The densities and thicknesses of the films were 11.5 nm and 3.27 g cm -3 in the conventional ALD process, respectively, and 10.4 nm and 4.17 g cm -3 in the ALD-DFM process, respectively. The lower density of the film grown through the conventional ALD process may have been due to its susceptibility to oxidation under ambient conditions, which will be discussed subsequently in this paper. The density values were lower than that of the bulk crystalline GeSe but similar to the value of the amorphous GeSe deposited through the sputtering method <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>. The comparably larger deviation in the fitting of the XRR for the conventional ALD film originated from the roughness of the GeSe film.</p><p>The AES depth profiles in figures 6(c) and (d) confirm the stoichiometric composition of GeSe (1:1) for both films. A higher level of oxygen impurity is evident for the film grown through the conventional ALD process compared to the film grown via the ALD-DFM process. The results imply that the oxidation progressed less for the film grown through the ALD-DFM process than for the film grown through the conventional ALD process. The oxidation resistance of the DFM film will be shown, with the XPS analysis results, in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>. The thickness of the films (∼10 nm) has exaggerated the concentration of impurities (O, C) present on the surface after the exposure to the ambient condition. Nonetheless, it is necessary to examine this thickness region because the fabricated OTS device had a similar thickness.</p><p>The XPS analysis result presented in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref> supports the difference in the chemical stability of the films against oxidation depending on the deposition method used. For this comparison, the XPS measurements were done without surface etching. (When in situ etching was performed to remove the surface contaminants, the XPS peaks were unstable for the short etching times. After the extended etching times, the film recovered the original peaks due to the immediate reoxidation of the exposed surface.) Consistent with the AES result in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>, the Ge-oxide peaks in figures 7(a) and (b) show that almost the entire thickness of the films was contaminated by oxygen, possibly during the air exposure. The 1:1 stoichiometry of GeSe observed in the AES depth profiles also supports this idea because the higher binding energy between Ge and O than that between Ge and Se would have led to a higher Ge/Se ratio, which is inconsistent with the AES results. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>(a) shows that the Geoxide peak was substantially larger than the Ge-Se peak for the conventional ALD process. In the case of the ALD-DFM process, the Ge-Se peak was significant (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7(b)</ref>). The locations of the Ge 3d and Se 3d peaks well match the binding energy in GeSe (Ge 3d B.E.: ∼30.7 eV; Se 3d B.E.: ∼54.3 eV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26]</ref>. As the Se 3d peak was observed at the previously reported binding energy without a significant shift (figures 7(c) and (d)), it can be concluded that Se was always bonded to two Ge atoms, consistent with the stoichiometric composition of GeSe. The results indicate that oxidation progressed less for the film grown through the ALD-DFM process than for the films grown through the conventional ALD process. It is possible that the lower density of the conventional ALD film allowed the easier penetration of the film by oxygen during the air exposure due to the highly porous surface. In either case, the observations suggest that the screening effect of the physisorbed molecules deteriorates the film quality, and that DFM can improve the quality by increasing the frequency of purging.</p><p>For the detailed amorphous structure, the FFT analysis results were obtained from the TEM images of the GeSe samples. It was confirmed that the thickness of the GeSe films was similar to that in the XRR data for both deposition methods (figures 8(a) and (b)). In addition, the structural order was slightly observed in the GeSe film deposited through the conventional ALD process (right panel of figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8(a)</ref>, where the FFT indicates some ordered phase rather than the perfect amorphous phase) while the case of the ALD-DFM process showed a perfect amorphous phase.</p><p>The crystallization behavior of the GeSe film was studied before testing the OTS devices. A resistivity-temperature experiment was carried out to confirm the feasibility of GeSe as OTS for the films deposited through the conventional ALD process and the ALD-DFM process shown in figures 9(a) and (b), respectively. The transition temperatures to the low resistance state appeared at ∼337 °C for the conventional ALD process and at ∼348 °C for the ALD-DFM process due to the crystallization of the films. The GAXRD results in figures 9(c) and (d) confirmed the crystallization temperature of GeSe consistent with the resistivity-temperature results. In the film deposited through the conventional ALD process, crystallization of the GeSe film was observed at 340 °C, but in the case of the film deposited through the ALD-DFM process, the film was crystallized at 350 °C. The results of the GeSe films grown through the ALD-DFM process corresponded well to the crystallization temperature of the bulk GeSe (∼350 °C) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The higher crystallization temperature of the ALD-DFM film suggests that DFM enhances the amorphous stability of the GeSe film, as supported by the TEM results in figure 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">OTS behavior of the GeSe films</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref> shows the experiment set-up for the electrical measurement using a pulse generator (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10(a)</ref>). The results of the measurements of the reference voltage V Ch1 at channel 1 and V Ch2 at channel 2 were used to calculate the voltage (V DUT ) of the device-under-test (DUT). The R Ch1 =1 MΩ, and the R Ch2 = 50 Ω. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10(b)</ref> shows the device structure on a hole-patterned substrate. The Si/W/GeSe(∼10 nm)/Pt(∼50 nm) structure was constructed from the ALD deposition of the GeSe film with the conventional or ALD-DFM processes (100 cycles) and based on the subsequent lift-off pattern of the electron-beam-deposited Pt electrode.</p><p>Time-resolved I-V measurement was performed to confirm the OTS behavior of the GeSe selector devices. First, the rising and falling times of the voltage pulse were set to 2 μs for creating a triangle wave with a pulse amplitude V Ch1 of ∼3 V, as shown in figures 11(a) and (b). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11(a)</ref> shows that the device constructed from the conventional ALD process did not exhibit the OTS behavior, but only leakage current appeared, possibly due to the distribution of Ge oxide    throughout the GeSe films, as shown above. The following mechanism can be suggested as the reason for such behavior. Many types of research have suggested that electronic switching of the chalcogenide materials occurs via the involvement of the valence alternation pairs (VAPs). The group VI element chalcogens (C) readily undergo a disproportionate reaction, as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">2C C C . 1 2 0 3 1  + + - ( )</formula><p>The disproportionation reaction from the neutral atoms (C 2 0 ) to two charged chalcogen atoms (C 3 + and C 1 -) is energetically favorable. (The subscripts and superscript of C represent the coordination number and the charge of the chalcogen atom (C), respectively.) These charged defects form localized states acting as deep and shallow traps near the Fermi level and the conduction band, respectively. When a voltage is applied, the traps provide a current path with a lowered energy barrier. It is hard for devices fabricated through the conventional ALD process, however, to possess such traps due to the stronger binding energy of Ge-O. For disproportionation to occur, the Coulombic repulsion energy (U c ) should be compensated for by polaron shift (w). In particular, the negative-U model can be established when w &gt;U c /2 is satisfied <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>. The polaron shift is defined as Q 2 /2k in the mechanical analogy of the negative-U effect (Q: deformation potential for the localized carriers; k: spring constant), where k can be considered the binding energy value <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>. The model can explain the difference between SiO 2 and SiTe in VAPs formation. In SiO 2 (B.E. ∼799.6 kJ mol -1 ), polaron shift cannot proceed due to the difficulty in lattice deformation; as such, the formation of VAPs is suppressed. The lower binding energy of SiTe (B.E. ∼425 kJ mol -1 ), however, allowed the OTS behavior in it. In this study, Ge-O (B.E. ∼659.4 kJ mol -1 ) had a stronger bond than GeSe (B.E. ∼484.7 kJ mol -1 ), making it difficult to form VAPs <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[35]</ref>. As a result, OTS behavior could not occur due to the high level of oxygen in the film deposited through the conventional ALD process.</p><p>Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11(b</ref>)-(d) show the OTS behavior of the device fabricated through the ALD-DFM process. A sudden decrease in V DUT , called 'voltage snapback,' can be observed in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11(c</ref>) due to the sudden reduction in the resistance of the GeSe films at ∼1.04 μs. The V Ch1 at this point can be defined as the threshold voltage (V th ). The device exhibited a short switching time of ∼40 ns (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11(c</ref>)) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Low resistance (on-state) was maintained until the voltage dropped to the holding voltage (V h ), and switching to the off-state occurred again at about 3.23 μs due to the increase in resistance of the GeSe films (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11(d))</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">12</ref>(a) presents an I DUT -V DUT curve of the device obtained from the pulse response measurement. The curve clearly shows the threshold switching of the device resistance to around 1.9 V. At the low resistance state, a ∼10 -2 A onstate current (I on ) measurement was obtained. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">12(b</ref>) presents a similar result, but the response was measured using a voltage sweep method with a compliance current of 10 -3 A. The off-state current (I off ) and reading current (I read ) were about ∼10 -9 and ∼10 -6 A, respectively, when the reading voltage for I read was one half of V th . Based on the I on measurement value shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">12</ref>(a), the ON/OFF current ratio of the device was calculated as ∼10 7 . The reading selectivity defined as the current ratio between the cells under operation and the other cells in passive arrays were estimated to be ∼10 4 when the selected cell for operation was assumed to be under an operation voltage while the remaining cells were under a half of the operation voltage. This value is among the best-reported selectivity values of OTS devices Here, q is the elementary charge; N T is the density of traps between the conduction band and the Fermi level (E c ′ and E F0 ); and Δz and 0 t are the inter-trap distance between the localized states and the attempt-to-escape time for the trapped electrons, respectively. In the low-voltage range, (in the off-state) N T and Δz can be obtained by fitting through equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. The value of E c ′-E F0 was assumed to be 0.54 eV, as reported by Naga et al, and 0 t is assumed to be 1 fs <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[38]</ref>. The fitted values were N T =5.36×10 20 cm -3 and Δz=1.41×10 -7 cm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>In this work, GeSe films were deposited through the ALD method to fabricate an OTS selector device for the phasechange-memory-based crossbar array. HGeCl 3 and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se were used as Ge and Se precursors, respectively, and the typical ALD temperature was 70 °C. The 1:1 stoichiometric composition of GeSe was achieved by the decomposition of HGeCl 3 into divalent GeCl 2 and the subsequent ligand exchange reaction with the [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Se. This is a mechanism similar to the previously reported GeTe ALD using an identical Ge precursor and [(CH 3 ) 3 Si] 2 Te. Nonetheless, the much higher polar nature of the Ge-Se bond compared with the Ge-Te bond induced an inefficient purging of the physisorbed Ge precursor molecules, which subsequently induced a very long purge time. This process showed problems in guaranteeing a high-quality film, and the resulting films were highly vulnerable to the oxidation during the air exposure after the ALD. The adverse oxidation totally prohibited the desired OTS switching behavior of the fabricated device. In contrast, the film grown through the ALD-DFM process, which effectively purged out the excessive Ge precursor molecules during the ALD, resulted in a much denser and smooth film. DFM induced a growth rate at a total Ge precursor pulse time of 3 s that was identical to that at a total Ge precursor pulse time of 7 s in the conventional ALD process. This higher density film effectively suppressed the adverse oxidation of the film, which allowed the fluent operation of the device in the OTS mode. The achieved switching time was as short as 40 ns, and the selectivity was as high as 10 4 , among the highest reported for the chalcogenide-based OTS selectors. The fitting of the currentvoltage curve to the modified PF equation revealed that the trap density was 5.36×10 20 cm -3 .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. (a) Conventional ALD sequence and (b) ALD sequence with DFM for the deposition of GeSe films.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,307.34,69.08,240.13,80.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. (a) Proposed deposition mechanism of GeSe films from HGeCl 3 and GeCl 2 with HCl on the film surface. (b)-(e) Saturation behavior in the conventional ALD through the Ge and Se precursors' pulse and purge time split.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,110.42,69.08,376.87,630.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. (a) Growth rates of the GeSe films grown via the ALD-DFM and conventional ALD process. (b) Growth rates according to the pulse pressure adjusted through the metering valve. (c) Model for the film growth during the ALD-DFM process for the efficient removal of the physisorbed molecules.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,119.54,69.08,358.63,648.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>) and (b)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. (a) Layer densities versus cycle number to confirm the saturation growth rate without an incubation cycle. (b) Effect of the substrate temperature on the growth rate.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,110.42,69.08,376.87,165.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. SEM (top) and AFM (bottom) images of the samples grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process on a SiO 2 substrate.Figure 6. XRR result (top) and AES analysis (bottom) for the films grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,50.42,290.00,239.83,227.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 5. SEM (top) and AFM (bottom) images of the samples grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process on a SiO 2 substrate.Figure 6. XRR result (top) and AES analysis (bottom) for the films grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,307.34,290.00,240.07,249.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. XPS results of the films grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,50.30,69.08,240.07,262.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. TEM images (left) and associated FFT analysis (right) of the samples grown through (a) the conventional ALD process and (b) the ALD-DFM process.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,50.30,69.08,240.13,221.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Resistivity-temperature experiments (top) and GAXRD patterns (bottom) of the as-deposited and annealed GeSe films grown through (a), (c) the conventional ALD process and (b), (d) the ALD-DFM process to verify the crystallization temperature.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,50.30,366.98,240.13,247.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. (a) Schematic of the set-up for TS measurement. (b) Structure of the GeSe selector device.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,307.34,69.08,240.07,101.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Time-resolved TS behavior of the GeSe selector devices through fabrication using (a) the conventional ALD process and (b) the ALD-DFM process. Magnified view of the transition region in (b) to the (c) ON-state and (d) OFF-state.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,307.34,214.40,240.13,221.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><figDesc>[10]. The red line in figure 12(b) shows a simulation fit to a modified PF model proposed by Ielmini et al to describe the off-state current density (J) of the amorphous chalcogenides under the applied electric field F [36, 37]:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12. Experimental and simulated I-V curves of the OTS device. (a) I-V characteristics by plotting I DUT -V DUT . (b) I-V characteristics for the I off region by voltage sweep. Both experiments were performed using devices fabricated via the ALD-DFM process.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,307.34,69.08,240.07,123.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Nanotechnology 29 (2018) 365202 W Kim et al</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was supported by the <rs type="programName">Global Research Laboratory Program</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2012K1A1A2040157</rs>) of the <rs type="funder">Ministry of Science, ICT, and Future Planning of Korea</rs>. Authors would like to acknowledge <rs type="institution">Versum Materials, Inc.</rs> for the kind supply of HGeCl 3 precursor.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5jjbWte">
					<idno type="grant-number">2012K1A1A2040157</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Global Research Laboratory Program</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.3301579</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phase change memory technology J. Vac. Sci. Technol. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase change materials and their application to nonvolatile memories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Welnic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ielmini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cr900040x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase-change memories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lacaita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D J</forename><surname>Wouters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pssa.200723561</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Status Solidi a</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2281" to="2297" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent progress in phase-change memory technology IEEE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/JETCAS.2016.2547718</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Emerg. Sel. Top. Circuits Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Phase change materials and phase change memory MRS Bull</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wuttig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1557/mrs.2014.139</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="710" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Access devices for 3D crosspoint memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shenoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Virwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Narayanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Padilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kurdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.4889999</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40802</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies of amorphous Ge-Se-Te alloys 1. Preparation and calorimetric observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D J</forename><surname>Sarrach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Deneufville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W L</forename><surname>Haworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-3093(76)90057-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012 Threshold resistive and capacitive switching behavior in binary amorphous GeSe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cheong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.4714705</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102807</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovative PCM + OTS device with high sub-threshold non-linearity for non-switching reading operations and higher endurance performance Symp</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.23919/VLSIT.2017.7998208</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.23919/VLSIT.2017.7998208" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">VLSI Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In-depth ivestigation of programming and reading operations in RRAM cells integrated with ovonic threshold switching (OTS) selectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/IEDM.2017.8268311</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1109/IEDM.2017.8268311" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Electron Devices Meeting (IEDM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ge concentration in Ge x Se 1-x chalcogenide glass on the electronic structures and the characteristics of ovonic threshold switching (OTS) devices ECS Solid State Lett</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S D</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cheong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D W And</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/2.001310ssl</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved electrical performance thanks to Sb and N doping in Se-rich GeSe-based OTS selectror devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Verdy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Noè</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bourgeois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Garrione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perniola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/IMW.2017.7939088</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1109/IMW.2017.7939088" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE International Memory Workshop (IMW</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Step coverage modeling of thin films in atomic layer deposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2714685</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">73502</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combined ligand exchange and substitution reactions in atomic layer deposition of conformal Ge 2 Sb 2 Te 5 film for phase change memory application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Eom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ivanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.5b00805</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3707" to="3713" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">)(x) layers by atomic layer deposition for nanoscale phase change memories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Eom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cm300539a</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conformal formation of</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2099" to="2110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Eom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M C</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ivanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Atomic layer deposition of GeTe films using Ge{N[Si(CH3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">}(2), {(CH3)(3)Si}(2)Te, and methanol</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b03704</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7158" to="7166" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic layer deposition of GeTe and Ge-Sb-Te films using HGeCl</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.7b01236</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">OC2H5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8065" to="8072" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and {(CH3 ) Si}(2)Te and their reaction mechanisms Sb</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of the kinetic adsorption process on the atomic layer deposition process of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Eom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cm4034885</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">GeTe 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1583" to="1591" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>)(x) layers using Ge4+-alkoxide precursors</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved growth and electrical properties of atomic-layer-deposited metal-oxide film by discrete feeding method of metal precursor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cm100900k</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1654" to="1658" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation and test of Pauling&apos;s electronegativity scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L R</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T L</forename><surname>Meek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Allred</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allen L C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/jp000288e</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5867" to="5871" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface-induced dipole-moments of adsorbed atoms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Antoniew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.32.1424</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1424" to="1425" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic layer deposition: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cr900056b</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dasgupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H B R</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P S</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b00673</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1943" to="1947" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Popescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Non-Crystalline Chalcogenides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X-ray photoelectron and auger-electron spectroscopic studies of chemical-shifts in amorphous Ge-Se system Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ueno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1143/JJAP.22.1349</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1349" to="1352" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J R</forename><surname>Rumble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bickham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C J</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sia.740190147</idno>
		<title level="m">The NIST x-ray photoelectron-spectroscopy database Surf. Interface Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="246" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the threshold switching mechanism of a Te-SbO selector device for crosspoint nonvolatile memory applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.4998493</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">183501</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valence-alternation model for localized gap states in lone-pair semiconductors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kastner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Adler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fritzsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.37.1504</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1504" to="1507" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bonding bands, lone-pair bands, and impurity states in chalcogenide semiconductors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kastner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.28.355</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">355</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electronic switching in phase-change memories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pirovano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lacaita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Benvenuti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pellizzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TED.2003.823243</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Electron Devices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="452" to="459" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electrical conduction in chalcogenide glasses of phase change memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nardone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Karpov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V G</forename><surname>Karpov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.4738746</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">71101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermochemical data for gaseous monoxides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pedley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E M</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.555698</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Ref. Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="1031" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P A G</forename><surname>Ohare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Thermodynamic properties of gaseous silicon monotelluride and the bond-dissociation enthalpy D-M</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Site) at T-</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.555932</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Ref. Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1458" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamics of (germanium plus selenium): a review and critical assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P A G</forename><surname>Ohare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zywocinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L A</forename><surname>Curtiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/jcht.1996.0045</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Thermodyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Simple binary ovonic threshold switching material SiTe and its excellent selector performance for high-density memory array application IEEE Electron Device Lett</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Koo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/LED.2017.2685435</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="568" to="571" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analytical model for subthreshold conduction and threshold switching in chalcogenide-based memory devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ielmini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2773688</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54517</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Threshold switching mechanism by high-field energy gain in the hopping transport of chalcogenide glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ielmini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevB.78.035308</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35308</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doped GeSe materials for selector applications 47th European Solid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Avasarala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/ESSDERC.2017.8066618</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1109/ESSDERC.2017.8066618" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">State Device Research Conference (ESSDERC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
