<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Ultralow surface recombination of substrates passivated by plasma-assisted atomic layer deposited </title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">OTB Solar</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Netherlands Technology Foundation STW</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hoex</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Ultralow surface recombination of substrates passivated by plasma-assisted atomic layer deposited </title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EAD60932097BB4DD3DA55C3E274A128E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2240736</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Surface passivation of n -type Czochralski silicon substrates by thermal-SiO 2 /plasma-enhanced chemical vapor deposition SiN stacks</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Excellent surface passivation of c-Si has been achieved by Al 2 O 3 films prepared by plasma-assisted atomic layer deposition, yielding effective surface recombination velocities of 2 and 13 cm/ s on low resistivity n-and p-type c-Si, respectively. results obtained for ϳ30 nm thick Al 2 O 3 films are comparable to state-of-the-art results when employing thermal oxide as used in record-efficiency c-Si solar cells. A 7 nm thin Al 2 O 3 film still yields an effective surface recombination velocity of 5 cm/s on n-type silicon. © 2006 American Institute of Physics. ͓DOI: 10.1063/1.2240736͔ Surface passivation of crystalline silicon ͑c-Si͒ is of key importance for the performance of high efficiency industrial solar cells. The surface to volume ratio is increasing due to the cost-driven reduction of the solar cell thickness, which makes surface passivation a decisive factor for the final solar cell efficiency. Hydrogenated amorphous silicon nitride ͑a-SiN x :H͒ is routinely applied in solar cell production as an antireflection coating on the front side and provides good surface passivation of low resistivity n-and p-type c-Si. However, the surface passivation of a-SiN x : H on highly doped p-type silicon ͑e.g., p-type emitters͒ is rather poor. When a-SiN x : H is applied on the back of a p-type solar cell the high positive built-in charge induces a parasitic junction, limiting the solar cell efficiency. 1 Thermally grown oxide is the state-of-the-art surface passivation layer for n-and p-type c-Si of arbitrary doping level and is used in the record-efficiency passivated emitter and rear localy-diffused ͑PERL͒ c-Si solar cell. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The surface passivation of the asgrown thermal oxide is moderate, but is significantly improved by a subsequent annealing in a forming gas ͑H 2 in N 2 ͒. The best results are obtained by the so-called alneal scheme, where a sacrificial layer of Al is evaporated on the film prior to annealing. The oxidation of the Al film during the annealing releases atomic hydrogen that strongly reduces the number of interface defect states. However, the high processing temperatures ͑ϳ950-1100 °C͒ and elaborate processing necessary to obtain such a high quality thermal oxide are not always desirable. Therefore considerable effort is put in the development of low temperature surface passivation schemes that do not show the limitations of thermal oxide and a-SiN x : H. Materials such as amorphous silicon carbide ͑a-SiC x :H͒ and hydrogenated amorphous silicon ͑a-Si: H͒ have recently demonstrated a good level of surface passivation on both n-and p-type c-Si. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> However, both materials have significant absorption in the visible part of the solar spectrum. These films are also thermally unstable; hence, only steps with a low thermal budget can be used after deposition of these films.</p><p>Another interesting option is the use of the high bandgap dielectric Al 2 O 3 as a surface passivation layer. With a refractive index of ϳ1.65 and no significant absorption in the visible part of the solar spectrum, Al 2 O 3 is well suited to improve the optical quality at the front or the back of the solar cell. Hezel and Jaeger already demonstrated that Al 2 O 3 grown by the pyrolysis of aluminium-tri-isopropoxide can show a reasonable level of surface passivation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> More recently, Agostinelli et al. have shown that Al 2 O 3 films grown by thermal atomic layer deposition provide a good level of surface passivation on p-type c-Si. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> In this letter we will show that ultrathin films of Al 2 O 3 exhibit a similar level of surface passivation as alnealed thermal silicon oxide on both n-and p-type silicon. These films were prepared by plasma-assisted atomic layer deposition ͑PA-ALD͒ allowing monolayer growth control of high quality thin films, while the plasma step enables the use of relatively short purging times and low deposition temperatures.</p><p>Al 2 O 3 films with a thickness of 7 -30 nm were grown in a homebuilt PA-ALD reactor at a substrate temperature of 200 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> The films were prepared by alternating trimethylaluminium exposure and a remote O 2 plasma with a total cycle time of ϳ30 s. The film growth was monitored by means of in situ spectroscopic ellipsometry ͑250-1000 nm range͒ and revealed a growth rate in the 1.2 Å range per cycle. The atomic composition of the films was determined by means of Rutherford backscattering ͑RBS͒ and elastic recoil detection ͑ERD͒. The films were oxygen rich ͑Al: O = 2 : 3.14͒, and a small amount of hydrogen ͑ϳ3 at. % ͒ was detected in the films. The carbon content was below the detection limit of RBS ͑Ͻ2 at. % ͒. The surface passivation was tested by depositing identical Al 2 O 3 films on both sides of low resistivity p-type ͑300 m, ͗111͘, 2.0 ⍀ cm͒ and n-type ͑275 m, ͗100͘, 1.9 ⍀ cm͒ float zone c-Si substrates. The substrates received a standard RCA clean with a final HF dip prior to deposition to remove the native oxide. After deposition, the lifetime samples were annealed in a N 2 environment for 30 min at 425 °C in a rapid thermal annealing furnace. The effective lifetime eff was measured using a lifetime tester ͑Sinton WCT-100͒ in both the quasi-steadystate and transient mode. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> The level of surface passivation is quantified by the effective surface recombination velocity. Assuming an infinite bulk lifetime, the upper limit of the effective surface recombination velocity S eff can be calculated by a͒ Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; electronic mail: w.m.m.kessels@tue.nl</p><p>APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS 89, 042112 ͑2006͒ 0003-6951/2006/89͑4͒/042112/3/$23.00 © 2006 American Institute of Physics 89, 042112-1</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S eff ഛ W 2 • eff , ͑1͒</formula><p>with W the substrate thickness. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> the effective lifetime as a function of the injection level is shown for the low resistivity p-type substrates passivated by 15 and 30 nm thin Al 2 O 3 films. The postdeposition annealing was necessary to obtain the reported effective lifetimes, as the effective lifetime of the samples with the as-deposited Al 2 O 3 films was only in the range of 2-8 s. Effective lifetimes up to 1.2 ms were measured for a substrate passivated by 30 nm Al 2 O 3 film corresponding to a S eff ഛ 13 cm/ s. No difference in effective lifetime is observed when a 15 nm Al 2 O 3 film is used instead of a 30 nm Al 2 O 3 film, except for the behavior for lower injection levels.</p><p>The surface passivation of Al 2 O 3 was also tested on n-type c-Si. In Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> the effective lifetime for 1.9 ⍀ cm n-type silicon passivated by 7, 14, and 26 nm Al 2 O 3 is shown. A maximum lifetime of 6.6 ms was measured for an n-type substrate passivated by a 26 nm Al 2 O 3 film corresponding to a S eff ഛ 2 cm/ s. For Al 2 O 3 film thicknesses of 7 and 15 nm comparable results were obtained and effective lifetimes up to 3.0 ms were measured, corresponding to a S eff ഛ 5 cm/s.</p><p>The postdeposition annealing was essential for a good level of surface passivation; however, from RBS/ERD no significant changes could be detected in the atomic composition of the annealed Al 2 O 3 films. From high resolution transmission electron microscopy ͑HR-TEM͒ it was found that both the as-deposited and annealed Al 2 O 3 films are amorphous in composition, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> for the annealed film. An interfacial oxide layer of ϳ1.5 nm ͑ϳ1.2 nm prior to anneal͒ is present between the c-Si and Al 2 O 3 as a result of the deposition process, possibly from the exposure of the substrate to the O 2 plasma in the first ALD cycles. In a separate experiment it was verified that the oxide layer formed during the O 2 plasma exposure in itself does not yield any surface passivation, also not after annealing.</p><p>The effective lifetimes measured for a p-type c-Si substrate passivated by a 15 nm Al 2 O 3 film in this study are significantly higher compared to the results reported for substrates passivated by a-SiC x : H films or Al 2 O 3 films grown by thermal ALD. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> The results are comparable to the best results obtained for alnealed thermal SiO 2 and nearly stoichiometeric a-SiN x : H and approach the results obtained for a-Si: H. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> It should be noted that the reported literature values were obtained for films with thicknesses in the range of 20-100 nm and that the level of surface passivation of a-SiC x : H and a-SiN x : H is reported to deteriorate for films with thicknesses below 40 and 20 nm, respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> On the other hand, the effective lifetimes for n-type c-Si passivated with a 26 nm Al 2 O 3 film are comparable to the best results obtained for alnealed thermal SiO 2 , a-SiN x : H, and a-Si: H films and significantly higher than reported for a-SiC x : H films. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> All lifetime curves in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> and <ref type="figure">2</ref> show the expected decrease in effective lifetime at higher injection levels due to Auger recombination. For the p-type wafer in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> passivated with a 30 nm Al 2 O 3 , the effective lifetime shows the typical injection level dependence also reported for p-type wafers passivated by a-SiN x :H, a-SiC x : H, or thermal oxide, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> probably caused by Shockley-Read-Hall ͑SRH͒ recombination in the bulk or at the surface through a midgap defect. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> Remarkably, the lifetime curve for the p-type wafer passivated by a 15 nm film is constant for lower injection level. For the n-type wafers passivated by 7 -26 nm Al 2 O 3 , the effective lifetime slightly decreases for lower injection level comparable to results obtained for n-type wafers passi- FIG. 2. Effective lifetime as a function of the excess carrier density for low resistivity n-type ͑275 m, ͗100͘, 1.9 ⍀ cm͒ float zone c-Si substrate passivated with 30, 15, and 7 nm thick Al 2 O 3 films. FIG. 3. High resolution TEM image a 20 nm thick Al 2 O 3 film on c-Si after a 30 min annealing at 425 °C in a N 2 environment.</p><p>vated by a-SiC x : H and a-Si: H. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> This decrease can again be attributed to SRH recombination in the bulk or at the surface.</p><p>The excellent surface passivation by the Al 2 O 3 film is mainly determined by the field effect passivation due to a large ͑ϳ10 13 cm -2 ͒ built-in negative charge as indicated by C-V measurements. This negative built-in charge for Al 2 O 3 was also reported by Hezel and Jaeger 6 and Agostinelli et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> The negative charge in Al 2 O 3 is suggested to be present at the unique tetrahedrally coordinated Al site present at the interface that has a net negative charge, in contrast to the octahedrally coordination site where Al has a charge of 3+. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> For the commonly used thermal oxide and a-SiN:H positive built-in charges in the range of 10 10 -10 12 cm -2 are reported, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> and for a-SiC : H the sign of the built-in charge is reported to depend on the wafer doping type. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> A negative built-in charge is especially beneficial for passivation of highly doped p-type silicon.</p><p>The fact that the high level of surface passivation could only be obtained by a postdeposition annealing of the Al 2 O 3 films ͑deposited at 200 °C͒ could be caused by a local reconstruction of the Al 2 O 3 the interface, consequently increasing the negative built-in charge. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> In addition, hydrogen from the Al 2 O 3 bulk could diffuse and provide chemical passivation at the c-Si/ Al 2 O 3 interface, thereby reducing defect related recombination. A factor of 10 reduction of the interface defect density was reported for a metal-insulatorsemiconductor structure with Al 2 O 3 as the insulator after a 15 min annealing at 500 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> In conclusion, we have shown that excellent surface passivation, similar to alnealed thermal oxide, can be obtained on n-and p-type c-Si by thin Al 2 O 3 films prepared by the PA-ALD technique. An ultrathin film of 7 nm thick Al 2 O 3 yields a S eff ഛ 5 cm/s on n-type c-Si. By optimization process, cycle times could be reduced to a ͑sub͒ second level and the total process, growth, and annealing would be significantly faster compared to the state-of-the-art passivation schemes applied presently.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>Ultralow surface recombination of c-Si substrates passivated by plasma-assisted atomic layer deposited Al 2 O 3 B. Hoex, S. B. S. Heil, E. Langereis, M. C. M. van de Sanden, and W. M. M. Kessels a͒ Department of Applied Physics, Eindhoven University of Technology, P.O. Box 513, 5600 MB Eindhoven, The Netherlands ͑Received 19 April 2006; accepted 9 June 2006; published online 27 July 2006͒</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. Effective lifetime as a function of the excess carrier density for low resistivity p-type ͑300 m, ͗111͘, 2.0 ⍀ cm͒ float zone c-Si substrate passivated with 30 and 15 nm thick Al 2 O 3 films.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,77.79,52.76,192.00,149.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>The authors thank <rs type="person">M. J. F. van de Sande</rs>, <rs type="person">J. F. C. Jansen</rs>, and <rs type="person">J. J. A. Zeebregts</rs> for their skillful technical assistance, <rs type="person">H. C. M. Knoops</rs> and <rs type="person">P. Kudláček</rs> for their help with the depositions, and <rs type="person">Dr. F. Roozeboom</rs> and <rs type="person">Dr. J. Klootwijk</rs> from <rs type="affiliation">Philips Research</rs> for the HR-TEM measurements. <rs type="person">Dr. J. Schmidt</rs> from <rs type="affiliation">ISFH</rs> is thanked for the insightful discussions. This work is supported by the <rs type="funder">Netherlands Technology Foundation STW</rs>. The work of one of the authors ͑B.H.͒ is financially supported by <rs type="funder">OTB Solar</rs>. The research of another author ͑W.M.M.K.͒ has been made possible by a fellowship of the <rs type="institution">Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences ͑KNAW͒</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dauwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mittelstadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hezel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Photovoltaics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ferrazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1998</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dauwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hezel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 29th IEEE Photovoltaic Specialist Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 29th IEEE Photovoltaic Specialist Conference<address><addrLine>Orlando, Florida ͑IEEE, New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">1246</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orpella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Puigdollers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alcubilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2199" to="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orpella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Voz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Puigdollers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alcubilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hezel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1989</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Agostinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vitanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Alexieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harizanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F W</forename><surname>Dekkers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Beaucarne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th European PVSEC</title>
		<meeting>the 19th European PVSEC<address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">132</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kemmeren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">L5 ͑2005͒</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2510" to="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semicond. Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semicond. Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sol. Energy Mater. Sol. Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2001</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ferre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alcubilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
			<date>202109</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lauinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Aberle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hezel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1952</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shockley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Read</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1952</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lucovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baumvol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<date>1353 ͑2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Aberle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glunz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Warta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1992</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hyun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2563" to="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
