<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
				<funder ref="#_HMDAvHD">
					<orgName type="full">Korean Government ͑MOEHRD</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_atyEsrr">
					<orgName type="full">POSTECH ͑Core Research Program͒</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Korea Research Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">62172D7638138E09925B9E177796151C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nitride mediated epitaxy of CoSi 2 through self-interlayer-formation of plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition Co</head><p>Han-Bo-Ram Lee, J. Y. Son, and H. Kim a͒ The silicide formation by annealing plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition ͑PE-ALD͒ Co and physical vapor deposition ͑PVD͒ Co was comparatively studied. Very pure Co films were deposited by PE-ALD with CoCp 2 and NH 3 plasma. However, various analyses have shown that amorphous SiN x interlayer was formed between PE-ALD Co and Si due to the NH 3 plasma exposure in contrast with PVD Co. Due to the nitride interlayer, CoSi 2 was epitaxially grown from PE-ALD Co by rapid thermal annealing through nitride mediated epitaxy. This process scheme is expected to provide a simple route for contact formation in future nanoscale devices. © 2007 American Institute of Physics. ͓DOI: 10.1063/1.2742791͔ CoSi 2 has been widely studied for the contact materials of nanoscale metal-oxide-semiconductor filed effect transistor due to the absence of narrow line effect. However, agglomeration and void formation during the silicidation or postthermal process due to grain grooving and interface roughening of polycrystalline silicide could become a potential problem. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Epitaxial CoSi 2 with lower contact resistance is one of the candidates to solve these problems, especially for shallow junction devices due to its good layer uniformity and high thermal stability. Interlayer mediated epitaxy ͑IME͒ is one of the promising techniques for CoSi 2 epitaxy since it is compatible with current Si technology and does not require expensive processing tools. For this purpose, various interlayer materials have been employed including oxide, 2 nitride, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> and CoN x . <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> So far, additional process step has been carried out to form appropriate interlayer. For example, nitride interlayer was formed by very high temperature ͑900 °C͒ nitridation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> We recently developed plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition ͑PE-ALD͒ Co process with high purity and low resistivity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> In this study, we investigated the interface between PE-ALD Co and Si substrate, comparatively with physical vapor deposition ͑PVD͒ Co. Due to the use of NH 3 plasma as a reactant, a few nanometer thick nitride interlayer was formed during the deposition process. By rapid thermal annealing ͑RTA͒ of the PE-ALD Co, CoSi 2 was formed epitaxially through nitride mediated epitaxy ͑NME͒ without separate interlayer formation step.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Department of Material</head><p>Co films were deposited on Si͑001͒ substrate by using PE-ALD chamber connected to dc magnetron sputtering chamber via load lock to form a cluster system, enabling the in situ deposition of capping layer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> CoCp 2 and NH 3 plasma were used as a Co precursor and a reactant, respectively. The standard NH 3 plasma exposure time ͑t r ͒ was 6 s and the growth temperature was 300 °C. Further details of PE-ALD Co film growth can be found in our previous report. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> For comparison, Co films were also deposited by dc magnetron sputtering at room temperature with plasma power of 120 W. The chemical bonding structure and impurity level of Co films were investigated by Rutherford backscattering, x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy ͑XPS͒, and secondary ion mass spectroscopy ͑SIMS͒. Synchrotron radiation x-ray diffraction ͑SR-XRD͒ and high resolution transmission electron microscope ͑HR-TEM͒ were used for microstructure analysis. Postdeposition annealing to form silicide was carried out for 30 s by a RTA system in N 2 environment. For silicidation, 20 nm thick Ti capping layer was deposited by in situ sputtering on PE-ALD and PVD Co without vacuum breaking.</p><p>As reported previously, PE-ALD Co films have shown low resistivity of 10 ⍀ cm due to high purity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> Figures 1͑a͒ and 1͑b͒ are cross sectional HR-TEM images of PVD and PE-ALD Co on Si substrates, respectively. Both of PVD and PE-ALD Co films were polycrystalline, which agrees with XRD spectra showing ␤-Co diffraction peaks. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1͑a͒</ref> shows the formation of 3 nm thick interlayer between PVD Co and Si. There have been several reports on the formation of amorphous CoSi x interlayer for PVD Co on Si substrate even at room temperature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> Similar TEM image to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1͑a͒</ref> was reported in Ref. 6, indicating that the interlayer for our case is also CoSi x . As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1͑b͒</ref>, however, the 2 -3 nm thick amorphous interlayer between PE-ALD Co and Si substrate has apparently different contrast and structure from that of PVD Co and Si.</p><p>To investigate the interlayer of Co and Si substrate, SIMS depth profiles were obtained ͑data not shown͒. The PE-ALD Co was very pure, with very small oxygen and nitrogen contaminations in the film. In fact, the nitrogen and oxygen contents in the film were smaller than those of PVD Co. Significant nitrogen peak intensity, however, was ob-a͒ Electronic mail: hyungjun@postech.ac.kr APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS 90, 213509 ͑2007͒ 0003-6951/2007/90͑21͒/213509/3/$23.00 © 2007 American Institute of Physics 90, 213509-1</p><p>served only for the interface of PE-ALD Co and Si in contrast to the PVD Co case. For better analysis of this interlayer, XPS analysis was carried out after the Co layer was removed by selective etching ͑H 2 SO 4 :H 2 O 2 =4:1, volume ratio͒. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows the XPS spectra for Si binding energy region. The deconvolution of the XPS spectrum in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows that it is composed of three peaks at 98.6, 101, and 102.6 eV. The peak at 98.6 eV ͑solid line͒ was assigned to the Si-Si bond from the Si substrate, while two lower energy peaks were assigned to Si-N ͑dash line͒ and Si-O ͑dot line͒ bonding, respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> XPS spectrum for N binding energy region was composed mostly of N-Si bond, and the Co peak intensity was very small in contrast to PVD Co for which significant Co XPS peaks were observed. These results, together with SIMS depth profile, strongly suggest that the interlayer for PE-ALD Co is amorphous SiN x not CoSi x .</p><p>One of the plausible reasons for SiN x interlayer formation during the PE-ALD Co is a direct exposure of Si substrate by NH 3 plasma at initial deposition cycles. In fact, the nitridation process using NH 3 plasma has been investigated for various applications in microelectronics technology. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> To estimate the SiN x formation in our experimental conditions, the Si͑001͒ substrates were exposed to NH 3 plasma at 300 °C. A few nanometer thick SiN x film formation was confirmed by spectroscopic ellipsometer. In contrast with NH 3 plasma, no SiN x film was formed by NH 3 gas at 300 °C. The SiN x layer formation alters the growth characteristics of PE-ALD Co. For Co chemical vapor deposition using CoCp 2 and H 2 , the deposition selectivity on several substrates has been reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> For example, the Co films were deposited on SiO 2 and Si 3 N 4 , not on Si substrate, which was attributed to the difficulty in CoCp 2 adsorption on H-terminated surface. In our case, however, Co films were deposited by PE-ALD using NH 3 plasma without nucleation delay on Si as well as on SiO 2 . This behavior can be explained by the formation of SiN x on the Si surface by NH 3 plasma during the initial deposition cycles, which enables the nucleation of Co film and leads to nonselectivity in deposition.</p><p>To investigate the effects of SiN x interlayer on solid state reaction between Co and Si, PE-ALD and PVD Co films with in situ PVD Ti capping layer were annealed at various annealing temperatures. For 20 nm Ti/ 20 nm PVD Co/ Si͑001͒ sample, weak CoSi ͑210͒ peak was observed at T a = 600 °C, and strong CoSi 2 ͑220͒ was observed with small ͑111͒ peaks at T a ജ 700 °C. These results are consistent with previous reports on silicide formation from PVD Co on Si substrate, for which polycrystalline CoSi 2 were formed at a high enough annealing temperature, while monosilicide phase is formed at a low annealing temperature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> In contrast with PVD Co case, however, SR-XRD spectra for the annealed 20 nm Ti/ 20 nm PE-ALD Co/ Si͑001͒ sample has shown clearly different results, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. First of all, no silicide related peaks were observed at up to 700 °C. At T a = 800 °C, only CoSi 2 ͑002͒ diffraction peak was observed at 2 = 33.5°. With further increase in annealing temperature to 900 °C, the CoSi 2 ͑002͒ peak intensity has grown significantly.</p><p>Further analysis was carried out for the sample annealed at 800 °C. Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the high resolution cross sectional TEM image. We can see a newly formed 5 nm thick layer with darker contrast than Si substrate was formed. SiN x layer, which was originally located between Co and Si, resides now above this layer. This was confirmed to be a CoSi 2 layer by energy dispersive spectroscopy analysis during the HR-TEM analysis with 0.5 Å spot size. The registry of lat- FIG. 3. XRD spectra of 20 nm Ti/ 20 nm PE-ALD Co/ Si͑001͒ after RTA at various annealing temperatures. FIG. 4. Cross sectional HR-TEM images of PE-ALD Co film annealed at 800 °C. tice was complete at interface between CoSi 2 and Si, indicating that the CoSi 2 was epitaxially grown and fully coherent with Si͑001͒ substrate. To check the in-plane orientation, we performed x-ray scattering with ⌽ scan geometry along the azimuthal direction with the slant angle of 45 °on the surface normal using Cu K␣ source. For this analysis, the capping layer and remaining Co film were selectively etched prior to the analysis. Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the F scans of the ͑220͒ peak of the CoSi 2 thin film on the Si͑001͒ substrate. The fourfold symmetry of ͑220͒ peak of the CoSi 2 thin film was observed, and the full width at half maximum of an in-plane ͑220͒ peak was equal to 0.4°, indicating that a high quality CoSi 2 epitaxial film was formed. The HR-TEM and XRD results indicate that the CoSi 2 is epitaxial with Si͑001͒ substrate with a cube-on-cube relationship, CoSi 2 ͓100͔ ʈ Si͓100͔.</p><p>It is worth noting that no monosilicide phase or other Co rich phase has been formed by annealing the PE-ALD Co sample at a low temperature. This absence of monosilicide or metal rich phase formation is a typical characteristic of IME process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Since we did not intentionally form an interlayer for IME, we attribute this epitaxial growth to NME due to the amorphous SiN x interlayer, formed by NH 3 plasma reaction with substrate. In NME, the nitride interlayer does not react with Co but limits the Co diffusion when the interlayer is very thin, Ͻ5 nm.</p><p>As seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>, the interface between CoSi 2 and Si was relatively nonuniform with ͕111͖ facets. These are common observations for IME when the capping layer and Co thickness are not fully optimized. For instance, in a previous report on NME, the CoSi 2 was grown as an island shape and was not continuous because of nonoptimization of Co thickness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Another study on IME using CoN x interlayer has shown that the interlayer thicknesses and chemical composition affect the thickness and interface of epitaxial CoSi 2 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Thus, the control of interlayer thickness is one of the requirements to control the IME of CoSi 2 . In a separate experiment, the SiN x interlayer thickness was reduced from 3 to 1 nm by decreasing the plasma expose time ͑t r ͒ from 6 to 2 s. Thus, SiN x interlayer thickness can be readily controlled by changing t r for our process scheme. However, since the required junction depth is below 10 nm, which will be decreased to below 5 nm in 2012 according to the International Technology Roadmap for Semiconductors, 11 even the very thin epitaxial CoSi 2 layer shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> can be utilized for contact in ultrashallow junction.</p><p>So far, the interlayers for IME were fabricated through separate process steps. For example, oxide interlayer was fabricated by wet chemical process, while nitride layer was fabricated by thermal nitridation at annealing temperature over 900 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> In another report, the CoN x interlayer for IME was formed by a separate deposition step followed by Co deposition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> In the present study, however, the interlayer was formed without additional process through self-interlayer formation during the PE-ALD. Additionally, high conformality of PE-ALD Co film is another big advantage, which cannot be achieved by PVD. Thus, the current process scheme provides a simple route for the formation of epitaxial CoSi 2 contact for future nanoscale devices.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>Science and Engineering, Pohang University of Science and Technology (POSTECH), San 31, Hyoja-Dong, Nam-Gu, Pohang, Kyungbuk 790-784, Korea ͑Received 21 March 2007; accepted 2 May 2007; published online 23 May 2007͒</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. Cross sectional HR-TEM images of ͑a͒ PVD Co film grown at t r = 6 s and ͑b͒ PE-ALD Co.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,329.21,617.77,216.00,108.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIG. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIG. 2. XPS spectrum of PE-ALD Co for silicon core-level region after selective etching of Co film.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,65.79,52.76,216.00,166.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>, and Kim Appl. Phys. Lett. 90, 213509 ͑2007͒</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support of <rs type="institution">Korea Electronic Technology Institute</rs>, <rs type="programName">BK21 Program</rs>, and <rs type="funder">POSTECH ͑Core Research Program͒</rs>. Also, this work was partially supported by <rs type="funder">Korea Research Foundation</rs> Grant funded by <rs type="funder">Korean Government ͑MOEHRD</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">KRF-2005-003-D00144͒</rs>. The XRD -2 and F scans were carried out at Pohang Light Source 5C2 beam line and <rs type="institution">Yoon Hee Jeong's Laboratory at POSTECH</rs>, respectively.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_atyEsrr">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">BK21 Program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_HMDAvHD">
					<idno type="grant-number">KRF-2005-003-D00144͒</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Maex</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng., R</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1993</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1996</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K K</forename><surname>Chong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yeadon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Boothroyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1833" to="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B R</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochem. Solid-State Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ruterana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Houdy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1990</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ze-Qiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1995</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2906">2906</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kurata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Inokuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hasegawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Dormans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cryst. Growth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1991</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FIG. 5. XRD F scan of 20 nm Ti/ 20 nm PE-ALD Co/ Si͑001͒ annealed at 800 °C. The capping layer and remaining Co film were selectively etched before analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Detavernier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Meirhaeghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cardon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Maex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Vandervorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">3170 ͑2000͒. 11 International Technology Roadmap for Semiconductors</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
