<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Trimethylaluminum as the Metal Precursor for the Atomic Layer Etching of Al 2 O 3 Using Sequential, Self-Limiting Thermal Reactions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-04-11">April 11, 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Younghee</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jaime</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steven</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Colorado</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>80309</postCode>
									<settlement>Boulder</settlement>
									<region>Colorado</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">S Supporting Information</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Trimethylaluminum as the Metal Precursor for the Atomic Layer Etching of Al 2 O 3 Using Sequential, Self-Limiting Thermal Reactions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-04-11">April 11, 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">05078EE02BADEB38328FB28F90BDA010</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b00111</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: January 10, 2016 Revised: April 10, 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Trimethylaluminum (TMA, Al(CH 3 ) 3 ) was used as the metal precursor, together with HF, for the atomic layer etching (ALE) of Al 2 O 3 using sequential, self-limiting thermal reactions. Al 2 O 3 ALE using TMA demonstrates that other metal precursors, in addition to Sn(acac) 2 , can be employed for Al 2 O 3 ALE. The use of TMA for Al 2 O 3 ALE is especially interesting because TMA can also be used for Al 2 O 3 atomic layer deposition (ALD). Quartz crystal microbalance (QCM) experiments monitored Al 2 O 3 ALE at temperatures from 250 to 325 °C. The Al 2 O 3 ALE was linear versus the number of HF and TMA reaction cycles. The QCM studies showed that the sequential HF and TMA reactions were selflimiting versus reactant exposure. The Al 2 O 3 etching rates increased at higher temperatures. The QCM analysis measured mass change per cycle (MCPC) values that varied from -4.2 ng/(cm 2 cycle) at 250 °C to -23.3 ng/(cm 2 cycle) at 325 °C. These MCPCs correspond to Al 2 O 3 etch rates from 0.14 Å/cycle at 250 °C to 0.75 Å/cycle at 325 °C. X-ray reflectivity and spectroscopic ellipsometry analyses confirmed the linear removal of Al 2 O 3 and etching rates. Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy measurements monitored Al 2 O 3 ALE by observing the loss of infrared absorbance from Al-O stretching vibrations. Surface intermediates were also identified after the HF and TMA exposures. Al 2 O 3 ALE with TMA is believed to occur by the reaction Al 2 O 3 + 4Al(CH 3 ) 3 + 6HF → 6AlF(CH 3 ) 2 + 3H 2 O. The proposed mechanism involves fluorination and ligandexchange reactions. The HF exposure fluorinates the Al 2 O 3 and forms an AlF 3 surface layer and H 2 O as a volatile reaction product. During the ligand-exchange transmetalation reaction, TMA accepts F from the AlF 3 surface layer and donates CH 3 to produce volatile AlF(CH 3 ) 2 reaction products. The QCM measurements were consistent with an AlF 3 surface layer thickness of 3.0 Å on Al 2 O 3 after the HF exposures. The larger etch rates at higher temperatures were attributed to the removal of a larger fraction of the AlF 3 surface layer by TMA exposures at higher temperatures.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Atomic layer etching (ALE) involves the removal of thin films based on sequential, self-limiting surface reactions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> ALE is the reverse of atomic layer deposition (ALD). <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Atomic layer processes, such as ALE and ALD, are crucial to engineer film thicknesses with atomic scale precision and to build nanoscale semiconductor devices. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Most of the reported ALE processes to date have used halogenation reactions followed by energetic ion or noble gas atom bombardment to etch the material. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> The use of energetic ions or atoms for etching is useful to achieve anisotropic etching. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In contrast, thermal ALE processes enable conformal and isotropic etching of threedimensional structures. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Thermal ALE may also achieve etching without damaging the underlying film.</p><p>Thermal ALE processes have been developed only recently. The first reported thermal ALE system was Al 2 O 3 ALE using HF and Sn(acac) 2 as the reactants. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Subsequently, HfO 2 ALE <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> and AlF 3 ALE 10 were also demonstrated using HF and Sn(acac) 2 . The chemistry of thermal ALE is based on fluorination and ligand-exchange reactions. Sn(acac) 2 is a good metal precursor for the ligand-exchange reaction. The ligand-exchange reaction can be characterized as a metal exchange transmetalation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> or a redistribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> reaction. In the ligand-exchange reaction, ligands are transferred between adjacent metal centers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> The transition state is generally believed to be a four-center ring based on a variety of transmetalation reaction studies, such as Stille cross-coupling between Pd and organotin compounds. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> For thermal ALE, the four-center ring would be formed by the metal in the metal precursor and the metal in the metal fluoride with fluorine and ligand bridging species. Fluorine facilitates the four-center ring transition state because of its ability to form bimetallic bridges. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> Transmetalation reactions are known to be favored if an empty orbital is available on both metals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> In addition, thermodynamics predicts that the halide atom prefers to transfer to the most electropositive atom during transmetalation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> Sn(II) compounds with SnX 2 stoichiometry like Sn(acac) 2 are good candidates for transmetalation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> Sn has a medium electronegativity of 1.8. Sn(II) complexes with SnX 2 stoichiometry also have an empty 5p orbital and an unshared 5s electron pair. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> The empty 5p orbital and unshared 5s electron pair yield Lewis acid and Lewis base properties that give chemical versatility to Sn(acac) 2 . Sn also can form relatively strong bonds with fluorine. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> Other metal precursors may also display favorable properties for the ligand-exchange reaction. Another promising metal precursor is trimethylaluminum (TMA). TMA has an open outer shell and is a strong Lewis acid because Al has only three valence electrons and does not obey the octet rule. Al has a low electronegativity of 1.5. Al is also known to form strong bonds with fluorine. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> TMA is a popular reactant resulting from its high volatility and excellent reactivity. For example, sequential TMA and H 2 O exposures are well-known to form Al 2 O 3 ALD films. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> The use of TMA for Al 2 O 3 ALE is particularly intriguing because TMA could serve to either grow Al 2 O 3 by ALD or etch Al 2 O 3 by ALE depending on the other reactant used together with TMA.</p><p>The use of different metal precursors for thermal ALE could also lead to selective ALE. Different metal precursors introduce various ligands that may transfer during the ligand-exchange transmetalation reaction. If the transferred ligand produces a metal product that is stable and volatile, then the metal product may leave the surface and produce etching. If the possible metal product is not stable or volatile, then the ligand-exchange reaction may not occur or may not produce a volatile etch product. In the previous work using Sn(acac) 2 as the metal precursor for ligand-exchange, Sn(acac) 2 transferred acac ligands to produce stable and volatile Al and Hf reaction products. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> In comparison, TMA can transfer CH 3 ligands that may lead to reaction products with different stabilities and volatilities that may provide for selective ALE.</p><p>In this paper, sequential exposures of HF and TMA were employed for thermal Al 2 O 3 ALE. The etching rates and individual HF and TMA reactions during thermal Al 2 O 3 ALE were examined using quartz crystal microbalance (QCM) studies. The Al 2 O 3 film thicknesses versus number of sequential HF and TMA exposures were also measured using X-ray reflectivity (XRR) and spectroscopic ellipsometry analyses. In addition, Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy measurements were used to observe the loss of infrared absorbance from Al-O stretching vibrations and monitor the surface species during the sequential HF and TMA exposures. These studies demonstrate that other metal precursors, in addition to Sn(acac) 2 , can be employed for the ligand-exchange reactions in thermal ALE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. EXPERIMENTAL SECTION</head><p>II.A. In situ QCM Studies in Viscous Flow Reactor. The ALE reactions were performed in a viscous flow, hot wall ALD reactor. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> An in situ quartz crystal microbalance (QCM) was mounted inside of the isothermal, hot wall ALD reactor. The quartz crystal (gold coated and polished, RC-cut 6 MHz, Colnatec) was placed in a sensor housing (BSH-150, Inficon). This sensor housing was then sealed with high temperature epoxy (Epo-Tek H21D, Epoxy technology). The mass changes during the ALE reactions were recorded by a thin film deposition monitor (Maxtek TM-400, Inficon). A proportionalintegral-derivative (PID) temperature controller (2604, Eurotherm) maintained the reaction temperature at 250, 275, 300, and 325 °C. The temperature was controlled to within ±0.04 °C of the exact set point. This temperature stability was important for accurate QCM measurements. The change of the reaction temperature required more than 2 h of stabilization. A capacitance manometer (Baratron 121A, MKS) monitored the pressure in the reactor.</p><p>The Al 2 O 3 films were grown on the QCM crystal with Al 2 O 3 ALD using TMA (97%, Sigma-Aldrich) and H 2 O (Chromasolv for HPLC, Sigma-Aldrich). The Al 2 O 3 ALE reactions were accomplished using sequential exposures of TMA and HF derived from HF-pyridine (70 wt % HF, Sigma-Aldrich). HF-pyridine is a liquid and HF gas has a vapor pressure of 90-100 Torr over the HF-pyridine solution at room temperature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> The pyridine partial pressure is negligible. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> The use of gaseous HF from the HF-pyridine solution allows for the safe handling of anhydrous HF. HF-pyridine was transferred to a gold-plated stainless steel bubbler using a dry N 2 -filled glovebag. The HF-pyridine, TMA, and H 2 O precursors were at room temperature.</p><p>A constant flow of 150 sccm of ultra high purity (UHP) N 2 gas was delivered into the reactor using mass flow controllers (Type 1179A, MKS). An additional flow of 20 sccm of N 2 gas through a metering bellows-sealed valve (SS-4BMG, Swagelok) prevented deposition on the backside of the QCM crystal. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> The total N 2 gas flow of 170 sccm produced a base pressure of ∼1 Torr in the reactor pumped by a mechanical pump (Pascal 2015SD, Alcatel).</p><p>II.B. Si Wafers, X-ray Reflectivity, Spectroscopic Ellipsometry and X-ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy. Al 2 O 3 ALD films were grown on boron-doped Si(100) wafers (p-type, Silicon Valley Microelectronics). These Al 2 O 3 ALD films were used as the substrates for the ALE reactions. The bare Si substrates were cut into samples with dimensions of 2.5 cm by 2.5 cm before the Al 2 O 3 ALD.</p><p>The ex situ X-ray reflectivity (XRR) scans were measured by a high resolution X-ray diffractometer (Bede D1, Jordan Valley Semiconductors) using Cu Kα (λ = 1.540 Å) radiation. The filament voltage and current in the X-ray tube were 40 kV and 35 mA, respectively. A 10 arcsec step size and a 5 s acquisition time were used for recording all XRR scans with a range of 300 to 6000 arcsec. The analysis software (Bede REFS, Jordan Valley Semiconductors) determined film thickness, film density and surface roughness by fitting the XRR scans.</p><p>Ellipsometry was performed using a spectroscopic ellipsometer (M-2000, J. A. Woollam) with a spectral range of 240 to 1700 nm and an incidence angle of 75°. The analysis software (CompleteEASE, J. A. Woollam) fitted the Ψ and Δ values based on a Sellmeier model to determine the thicknesses and refractive index of the film. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> The film composition was confirmed using X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS). The XPS instrument (PHI 5600) was equipped with a monochromatic Al Kα X-ray source.</p><p>II.C. In situ Fourier Transform Infrared (FTIR) Spectroscopy Studies. The in situ FTIR spectroscopy studies were performed in a reactor equipped with an FTIR spectrometer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> The FTIR experiments utilized high surface area, ZrO 2 nanoparticles (99.95%, US Research Nanomaterials) with an average diameter of 20 nm. The ZrO 2 nanoparticles absorb infrared radiation between ∼400-800 cm -1 and leave an open window at &gt;800 cm -1 to monitor absorbance from the surface species.</p><p>The ZrO 2 nanoparticles were mechanically pressed into a tungsten grid support to obtain the transmission FTIR measurements. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> The tungsten grids were 2 cm × 3 cm, 50 μm thick, with 100 grid lines per inch. The tungsten grid could be resistively heated and temperature controlled as described previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> The Al 2 O 3 films were grown on the ZrO 2 nanoparticles with Al 2 O 3 ALD using TMA (97%, Sigma-Aldrich) and H 2 O (Chromasolv for HPLC, Sigma-Aldrich). The Al 2 O 3 ALE reactions were performed using sequential exposures of TMA (97%, Sigma-Aldrich) and HF derived from HF-pyridine (70 wt % HF, Sigma-Aldrich).</p><p>Static dosing of both the ALD and ALE precursors was performed to achieve self-limiting behavior on the high surface area particle substrates. Each reactant exposure consisted of a ∼ 1 Torr static dose for 10 s followed by a 240 s purge. The Al 2 O 3 film on the ZrO 2 nanoparticles was grown using 15 cycles of Al 2 O 3 ALD at 150 °C. Subsequently, 8 cycles of Al 2 O 3 ALE were performed at 300 °C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>III.A. QCM Measurements.  Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> shows an enlargement of the mass changes versus time at 300 °C in the steady state region of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Each reactant exposure leads to pronounced mass changes. The TMA exposure results in a mass decrease. This behavior indicates TMA can remove the AlF 3 surface layer on the Al 2 O 3 film. A mass loss of ΔM TMA = -29 ng/cm 2 was observed after 2.0 s of TMA exposure. In contrast, the HF exposure leads to mass gain. A mass gain of ΔM HF = 13 ng/cm 2 was observed after 1.0 s of HF exposure. This mass gain is consistent with the fluorination of Al 2 O 3 to form an AlF 3 surface layer. This AlF 3 surface layer is then ready for the ligand-exchange reaction during the next TMA exposure.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref> shows the MCPC and the ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio during 100 Al 2 O 3 ALE cycles at 300 °C. The ΔM TMA and ΔM HF mass changes are very constant. The MCPC is defined by MCPC = ΔM TMA + ΔM HF . Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref> displays ΔM TMA , ΔM HF and MCPC for the same 100 cycles of Al 2 O 3 ALE reaction at 300 °C shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. A short nucleation period was observed before reaching steady state with MCPC = -15.9 ng/(cm 2 cycle). Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref> displays the ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio during the same 100 cycles. The ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio shows a steady-state value of 1.8 after the first three ALE cycles. The   ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio will be employed to define the stoichiometry of the Al 2 O 3 ALE reactions.</p><p>The self-limiting behavior can be confirmed by monitoring mass change as a function of exposure for each reactant. Selflimiting ALE reactions are important for conformal or isotropic etching. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref> examines the self-limiting nature of the Al 2 O 3 ALE reactions at 300 °C. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4a</ref> shows ΔM TMA , the mass change after the TMA exposure, using different TMA exposure times with a single 1.0 s exposure of HF. A constant N 2 purge of 30 s was used after each exposure. This reaction sequence can be represented as x-30-1-30. ΔM TMA versus the TMA exposure time decreases and levels off slowly.</p><p>Nearly self-limiting behavior at ΔM TMA = -29 ng/cm 2 is observed after 2.0 s of TMA exposure. This slow approach to self-limiting behavior may result from the difficulty in removing all of the AlF 3 surface layer. An initial fraction of the AlF 3 surface layer may be easily removed by TMA. The removal of more of the AlF 3 surface layer may then become progressively difficult. Additional analysis of the temperature dependence of the TMA reaction presented below will reveal that only a fraction of the AlF 3 surface layer is removed even at the highest temperatures.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4b</ref> monitors ΔM HF , the mass change after the HF exposure, using different HF exposure times with a single 2.0 s exposure of TMA. This reaction sequence can be denoted as 2-30-x-30. ΔM HF versus the HF exposure time increases and then levels off at approximately ΔM HF = 13 ng/(cm 2 cycle) after a 1.0 s HF exposure. This self-limiting behavior is consistent with HF fluorinating the Al 2 O 3 film and forming an AlF 3 surface layer that passivates the underlying Al 2 O 3 film.</p><p>This surface fluoride layer on Al 2 O 3 is similar to the native oxide layers formed on metals <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> or silicon <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> that protect the metals or silicon from further oxidation. The AlF 3 surface layer is expected to passivate the Al 2 O 3 film because the Pilling-Bedworth ratio, R PB , is &gt;1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> R PB is the ratio of the molar volume, V, of the top layer to the molar volume of the underlying material. The molar volume, V = M/ρ, where M is the molar mass and ρ is the density. V AlF3 = M AlF3 /ρ AlF3 = 29 cm 3 /mol because M AlF3 = 84 g/mol and ρ AlF3 = 2.9 g/cm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> . V Al2O3 = M Al2O3 /ρ Al2O3 = 33 cm 3 /mol because M Al2O3 = 102 g/ mol and ρ Al2O3 = 3.1 g/cm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> . Using these values, R PB = (V AlF3 × 2)/V Al2O3 = 1.8. The factor of 2 accounts for the aluminum stoichiometry difference between AlF 3 and Al 2 O 3 .</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref>     HF exposures on initial, hydroxylated Al 2 O 3 substrates prior to TMA exposures showed very similar mass gains of ΔM HF = 35-38 ng/cm 2 at 150-250 °C. 7 This similarity of the mass gains for HF exposure on the initial hydroxylated Al 2 O 3 substrate and for HF exposure on the Al 2 O 3 substrate after the TMA exposure results from the similar molar mass of the AlCH 3 * and AlOH* species. The AlCH 3 * and AlOH* species lead to the production of CH 4 and H 2 O, respectively. The mass changes resulting from these reactions, together with the mass gains occurring during the fluorination of Al 2 O 3 to produce an AlF 3 surface layer, are nearly equivalent. The mass gain of ΔM HF = 33-36 ng/cm 2 at 250-325 °C can be employed to estimate the thickness of the AlF 3 surface layer on the Al 2 O 3 substrate. This estimation assumes that the mass change from the reaction AlCH 3 * + HF → AlF* + CH 4 is negligible compared with the fluorination of Al 2 O 3 . The fluorination reaction Al 2 O 3 + 6HF → 2AlF 3 + 3H 2 O will result in a mass increase of 65%. This mass increase is expected from the masses of 102 amu for Al 2 O 3 and 168 amu for 2AlF 3 . Therefore, the average value of ΔM HF = 34 ng/cm 2 corresponds to the conversion of 52.5 ng/cm 2 of Al 2 O 3 into 86.5 ng/cm 2 of the AlF 3 layer. Based on the density of 3.1 g/ cm 3 for Al 2 O 3 , 22 the mass of 52.5 ng/cm 2 for Al 2 3 is equivalent to an Al 2 O 3 thickness of 1.7 Å. Likewise, based on the density of 2.9 g/cm 3 for AlF 3 , 22 the mass of 86.5 ng/cm 2 for AlF 3 is equivalent to an AlF 3 thickness of 3.0 Å. XPS measurements also examined the film composition after the HF exposures during Al 2 O 3 ALE at 300 °C. The Al 2 O 3 films were exposed to atmosphere after the Al 2 O 3 ALE and prior to the XPS studies. The XPS analysis yielded F concentrations of 4-6 at. % including the adventitious carbon. Fluorine concentrations of 4-6 at. % are in approximate agreement with the expected photoelectron yield from a layered sample consisting of a 6 Å thick adventitious carbon layer 35 on a 3 Å thick AlF 3 layer on an Al 2 O 3 substrate. The model for the photoelectron sources employed the C, F, Al and O number densities in each layer and the Beer-Lambert equation integrated over the film thicknesses. The Beer-Lambert equation is I = I 0 exp[-d/λ sin Θ] where I 0 is the initial photoelectron intensity, d is the distance traveled through the layer and Θ is the angle to the surface normal. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> The electron mean free path, λ, was based on approximate expressions for λ given in the literature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> After the first HF exposure, the next TMA exposure removes the AlF 3 layer on the Al 2 O 3 substrate. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref> shows that mass losses during the TMA and HF cycles begin with the second TMA and HF cycle for temperatures from 275-325 °C. The TMA and HF cycles at 250 °C show a mass loss after the third ALE cycle. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref> reveals that higher temperatures produce both a larger mass loss for the removal of AlF 3 by TMA and a larger mass gain for the subsequent fluorination of Al 2 O 3 by HF.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7</ref> shows enlargements of the mass changes during three cycles in the steady state etching regime for Al Earlier experiments observed the continuous etching of an AlF 3 film by Al(CH 3 ) 3 at 300 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> This behavior suggests that the formation of volatile AlF(CH 3 ) 2 product is favorable. Mass spectrometry studies are needed to confirm these proposed volatile reaction products.</p><p>The mass losses are larger at higher temperatures. A small mass decrease is observed after the TMA exposure at 250 °C.   TMA exposure for 2.0 s at 275 °C. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7c</ref> displays an even larger mass loss of ΔM TMA = -41.9 ng/cm 2 after a TMA exposure for 2.0 s at 325 °C.</p><p>In contrast, mass increases are observed after the HF fluorination reactions. These mass increases are consistent with the fluorination of Al 2 O 3 to AlF 3 . A mass increase of ΔM HF = 6.3 ng/cm 2 is observed after the HF exposure for 1.0 s at 250 °C as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7a</ref>. HF exposures for 1.0 s produce larger mass gains of ΔM HF = 9.9 ng/cm 2 at 275 °C and ΔM HF = 18.6 ng/cm 2 at 325 °C as shown in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7b</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7c</ref>, respectively. However, these ΔM HF values in the steady state regime are much less than the ΔM HF values observed in the first Al 2 O 3 ALE cycle on initial, hydroxylated Al 2 O 3 substrates in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>. The smaller mass gains observed for ΔM HF in the steady state regime suggest that the HF exposures may be removing surface species in addition to fluorinating Al 2 O 3 . The TMA exposures may also not be removing all the AlF 3 layer prior to the subsequent HF fluorination reaction.</p><p>From the QCM measurements in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>, the average value of ΔM HF = 34 ng/cm 2 during the first HF exposure corresponds to the conversion of 52.5 ng/cm 2 of Al 2 O 3 into 86.5 ng/cm 2 of the AlF 3 layer. If TMA can remove the entire AlF 3 layer on Al 2 O 3 , then ΔM TMA is limited to a maximum value of ΔM TMA = -86.5 ng/cm 2 . Because TMA can also form AlCH 3 * surface species after AlF 3 removal, the AlCH 3 * surface species could add 30 ng/cm 2 based on the averaged results for the first TMA exposure on the Al 2 O 3 substrate at different temperatures shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>. Consequently, ΔM TMA is limited to a maximum value of ΔM TMA = -56.5 ng/cm 2 .</p><p>Calculations were performed to estimate the amount of AlF 3 removal during the TMA exposures at different temperatures using the measured ΔM TMA values. The percentage of AlF 3 removed is based on the maximum value of ΔM TMA = -56.5 ng/cm 2 expected if the entire AlF 3 layer is removed by TMA. These calculations revealed that the percentage of AlF 3 removed by the TMA exposures increases with temperature. The percentages increased from 19% at 250 °C to 74% at 325 °C. The percentages of AlF 3 removal at all the temperatures are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>The ΔM TMA , ΔM HF , and MCPC values at all the reaction temperatures are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">8</ref>. All ALE reactions were performed using a reaction sequence of 2-30-1-30 on initial Al 2 O 3 substrates. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">8a</ref> displays the ΔM TMA and ΔM HF values obtained at different reaction temperatures. ΔM TMA shows progressively larger mass losses at higher temperatures. In contrast, ΔM HF reveals progressively larger mass gains at higher temperatures. The temperature dependence of ΔM TMA dominates the temperature dependence observed in the MCPC shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">8b</ref>. ΔM TMA , ΔM HF , MCPC, the etch rate, and the ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>III.B. XRR and SE Measurements. Al 2 O 3 ALE was also examined using ex situ XRR studies. For these experiments, Al 2 O 3 ALD films with a thickness of 141 Å were grown on Si(100) wafers at 300 °C. In addition, Al 2 O 3 ALD films with a thickness of 170 Å were grown on Si(100) wafers at 200 °C. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">9</ref> shows the XRR measurements of the initial Al 2 O 3 film thickness and the Al 2 O 3 film thickness after 25, 50, 100, and 200 ALE cycles at 300 °C. The initial Al 2 O 3 films grown at 300 and 200 °C had initial thicknesses of 141 and 170 Å, respectively. The film thickness versus number of ALE cycles in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">9a</ref> is linear and yields an etch rate of 0.46 Å/cycle. The spectroscopic ellipsometry (SE) measurements on these same samples also yield an etch rate of 0.46 Å/cycle. The different growth temperatures for the two Al 2 O 3 films did not affect the Al 2 O 3 etch rate. In addition, the etch rates determined by XRR and SE are similar to the etch rate obtained by the in situ QCM experiments at 300 °C.</p><p>The y intercepts from the linear least-squares fitting in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">9a</ref> are 142 Å for the Al 2 O 3 films grown at 300 °C for both the XRR and SE measurements. These thicknesses are slightly higher than the initial thicknesses of 141 and 139 Å measured by XRR and SE, respectively. These slightly larger thicknesses originate from the mass gain that occurs during the nucleation of the ALE process on the first ALE cycle. The SE analysis also determined a refractive index of n = 1.67 for the Al 2 O 3 film grown at 300 °C at a wavelength of 589 nm. This refractive index for the Al 2 O 3 film remained at n = 1.68 after 25, 50, 100, and 200 ALE cycles. Similar behavior was observed for the  Al 2 O 3 films grown at 200 °C and etched at 300 °C as shown in Figure 9b. III.C. FTIR Spectroscopy Measurements. An Al 2 O 3 ALD film was first grown using 15 cycles of TMA and H 2 O at 150 °C on ZrO 2 nanoparticles. FTIR spectroscopy measurements of the Al 2 O 3 ALD film growth are presented in Figure S2 in the Supporting Information. Following the Al 2 O 3 ALD, the sample temperature was raised to 300 °C, and the Al 2 O 3 film was etched using sequential exposures of TMA and HF. FTIR spectra recorded during the TMA and HF exposures at 300 °C are shown in Figure 10. These spectra were recorded after the HF exposures and are again referenced to the starting ZrO 2 nanoparticle substrate. The progressive loss in absorbance between 800 and 1000 cm -1 with ALE cycles is in agreement with the etching of the Al 2 O 3 film.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">11</ref> displays the FTIR difference spectra at 800-1300 cm -1 after consecutive TMA and HF exposures during the fifth ALE cycle at 300 °C. These difference spectra are referenced to the spectra after the previous reactant exposure. After TMA exposures, an increase in absorbance at ∼1212 cm -1 is observed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">11a</ref> that is in accord with the addition of AlCH 3 * surface species. These AlCH 3 * species may be present as either AlF(CH 3 ) 2 *, AlF 2 (CH 3 )*, or -OAl(CH 3 ) 2 *. All of these species would be expected to show a methyl deformation mode at ∼1212 cm -1 . However, since AlF(CH 3 ) 2 is expected to have a higher volatility than other species , the vibrational feature at 1212 cm -1 is likely attributed to AlF 2 (CH 3 )* or -OAl(CH 3 ) 2 *. In addition, a decrease in absorbance between ∼850 and 975 cm -1 is observed that is consistent with the loss of absorbance from Al-F stretching vibrations as TMA removes the AlF 3 surface layer.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">11b</ref> shows the absorbance after the subsequent HF exposure. The absorbance is completely removed for the vibrational feature attributed to the addition of AlCH 3 * species. This loss of absorbance is in accord with the conversion of AlCH 3 * surface species to AlF* species. The HF exposure also results in a broad absorbance loss between 800 and 1100 cm -1 that is in agreement with the conversion of Al 2 O 3 into AlF 3 by the reaction Al 2 O 3 + 6HF → 2AlF 3 + 3H 2 O. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">11b</ref> also reveals an absorbance increase on the broad absorbance loss between ∼850 and 950 cm -1 that is consistent with the formation of the AlF 3 layer.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">12</ref> shows the difference spectra from 2500 to 4000 cm -1 for the same consecutive TMA and HF exposures at 300 °C that are displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">11</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">12a</ref> shows the difference spectrum after the TMA exposure. An increase in absorbance is observed at ∼2900 and 2950 cm -1 that is in agreement with the addition of symmetric and asymmetric stretching vibrations of AlCH 3 * species, respectively. This absorbance gain is in accord with the formation of AlF 2 (CH 3 )* or -OAl(CH 3 ) 2 * species after TMA exposures. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">12b</ref> shows the difference spectrum after the HF exposure. The   spectrum observes an absorbance decrease at ∼2900 and ∼2950 cm -1 that is consistent with the removal of the previously added AlCH 3 * species.</p><p>There are also no vibrational features in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">12a</ref> and b between ∼3000 and 3675 cm -1 that would indicate HF* surface species. Vibrational features for HF* were observed during AlF 3 ALD using TMA and HF at lower temperatures. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> HF* species are important intermediates during AlF 3 ALD growth. The desorption of HF* surface species at higher temperatures allows TMA to accept fluorine from the underlying AlF 3 film and form volatile etch products that lead to Al 2 O 3 etching. At lower temperatures, HF* surface species remain on the surface and react with TMA to form AlF 3 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> Temperature can determine whether TMA and HF lead to either AlF 3 ALD or Al 2 O 3 ALE.</p><p>III.D. Proposed Al 2 O 3 ALE Mechanism. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">13</ref> shows the schematic for the proposed ALE reaction mechanism. This mechanism is based on the mass changes during the TMA and HF exposures as determined by the QCM measurements. This visualization does not include surface species that do not change during the HF and TMA reactions. During the fluorination reaction (A), HF reacts with AlCH 3 * surface species to form AlF* surface species and CH 4 reaction product. HF also reacts with the underlying Al 2 O 3 film to form an AlF 3 surface layer and H 2 O as a reaction product. The AlF 3 layer is then ready for the next TMA reaction.</p><p>During the ligand-exchange reaction (B), TMA reacts with the AlF 3 surface layer on the Al 2 O 3 substrate to form volatile AlF(CH 3 ) 2 reaction products. AlF(CH 3 ) 2 has a vapor pressure of 80 Torr at 100 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> There also may be AlF 2 (CH 3 )* surface species produced by the TMA exposures. These AlF 2 (CH 3 )* surface species could be removed by additional TMA exposure. The reaction for the removal of AlF 2 (CH 3 )* surface species is Al(CH 3 ) 3 + AlF 2 (CH 3 )* → 2AlF(CH 3 ) 2 . After the removal of fluorine-containing species, Al(CH 3 ) 3 could also react with the underlying Al 2 O 3 substrate to form Al(CH 3 )*.</p><p>The simplest overall proposed reaction can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">+ + → + Al O 6HF 4Al(CH ) 6AlF(CH ) 3H O 2 3 3 3 3 2 2 (1)</formula><p>This overall reaction can be divided into the HF and TMA reactions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">| †+ → | †+ (A)Al O Al O 6HF Al O 2AlF 3H O 2 3 2 3 2 3 3 2</formula><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">| † + → † + (B)Al O 2AlF 4Al(CH ) Al O 6AlF(CH ) 2 3 3 3 3 2 3 3 2<label>(3)</label></formula><p>The daggers indicate the species involved in the etching, and the vertical lines are used to separate the various surface species. The amount of Al 2 O 3 that is etched during the ALE reactions is given by Al 2 O 3 † in eqs 2 and 3.</p><p>The reactions described by eqs 1-3 are incomplete because TMA can also interact with the etched surface. For example, the reaction of TMA with Al 2 O 3 is known to form AlCH 3 * surface species. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref>  </p><p>TMA may also interact with AlF 3 species remaining on the etched surface. To incorporate the Al(CH 3 ) 3 * species, the HF and TMA reactions need be modified:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">| *+ + → | *+ + x x x x (A) Al O Al(CH ) (<label>6</label></formula><p>3 )HF 2AlF AlF 3H O 3 CH 2 3 3 3 3 3 2 4 (5) | * + + → *+ + x x x x (B) 2AlF AlF (4 3 )Al(CH ) Al(CH ) (6 3 )AlF(CH ) 3 3 33 3 3 3 2</p><p>The conventions are slightly different in the HF and TMA reactions given by eqs 2 and 3 and eqs 5 and 6. The amount of Al 2 O 3 that is etched during the ALE reactions is given by Al 2 O 3 in eqs 5 and 6. x is a parameter that defines the number of Al(CH 3 ) 3 * species relative to the number of Al 2 O 3 units that are etched during the ALE reaction.</p><p>The overall proposed reaction can then be expressed as  x can be calculated from the ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio using the equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">+ + + + → + + + x x x x Al O (<label>6</label></formula><p>= × -Δ x M (2 84 102( /MCPC))/(72 84) TMA (8)</p><p>where 84, 102, and 72 are the molecular weights for AlF 3 , Al 2 O 3 , and Al(CH 3 ) 3 , respectively. To obtain agreement with the relative ΔM TMA and ΔM HF mass changes in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, x = 7.7, 2.5, 1.6, and 1.4 at 250, 275, 300, and 325 °C, respectively. Although x decreases at higher temperatures, the product xMCPC is fairly constant over the entire temperature range. This behavior results from the increase in MCPC and the decrease in x at higher temperatures. These temperature dependences yield a nearly constant xMCPC product versus temperature. Because x is defined relative to the amount of Al 2 O 3 that is etched during the ALE reaction, the absolute Al(CH 3 ) 3 * coverages are proportional to xMCPC. The nearly constant xMCPC values in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> indicate that the absolute Al(CH 3 ) 3 * coverages are similar at all the etching temperatures. The larger etch rates at higher temperatures are attributed to the higher percentage of the AlF 3 surface layer removed by ligand-exchange reactions during TMA exposures at higher temperatures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Al 2 O 3 ALE was demonstrated using sequential, self-limiting thermal reactions with HF and TMA as the reactants. TMA is an effective metal precursor for the ligand-exchange transmetalation reaction during thermal ALE. Al 2 O 3 ALD can be performed using TMA and H 2 O. Al 2 O 3 ALE can be accomplished using TMA and HF. The ability of TMA to lead to either Al 2 O 3 ALD or Al 2 O 3 ALE suggests that metal ALD precursors for a particular material may also be employed for the ALE of the same material.</p><p>Al 2 O 3 ALE was studied at temperatures from 250 to 325 °C using QCM experiments. The QCM studies revealed that the Al 2 O 3 ALE was linear versus the number of HF and TMA reaction cycles. The sequential HF and TMA reactions were self-limiting versus reactant exposure. The Al 2 O 3 etching rates were larger at higher temperatures. The etch rates varied from 0.14 Å/cycle at 250 °C to 0.75 Å/cycle at 325 °C. XRR and SE studies confirmed the linearity of Al 2 O 3 ALE and the etching rates. FTIR spectroscopy studies observed the loss of infrared absorbance from the Al-O stretching vibrations during Al 2 O 3 ALE. The FTIR studies also identified AlF* surface species after the HF exposures and AlCH 3 * species after the TMA exposures.</p><p>The overall reaction for Al 2 O 3 ALE is believed to be described by Al 2 O 3 + 4Al(CH 3 ) 3 + 6HF → 6AlF(CH 3 ) 2 + 3H 2 O. This overall reaction is the result of individual fluorination and ligand-exchange reactions. The HF exposure fluorinates the Al 2 O 3 substrate and forms an AlF 3 surface layer and H 2 O as the reaction products. In a ligand-exchange transmetalation reaction, TMA accepts F from the AlF 3 layer and donates CH 3 to the AlF 3 layer to produce volatile AlF(CH 3 ) 2 reaction products. The AlF 3 surface layer was estimated to have a thickness of 3.0 Å on Al 2 O 3 after the HF exposures. The larger etch rates at higher temperatures result from the removal of a larger fraction of the AlF 3 surface layer by TMA at higher temperatures. The ability to change the metal precursor and the ligands during the ligand-exchange reaction may also provide pathways to selective ALE.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>shows the mass change during 100 ALE cycles using sequential exposures of TMA and HF on an Al 2 O 3 substrate at 300 °C. The initial Al 2 O 3 ALD film on the QCM crystal was deposited by 100 cycles of Al 2 O 3 ALD using TMA and H 2 O at 300 °C. One ALE cycle consisted of a TMA dose of 2.0 s, an N 2 purge of 30 s, a HF dose of 1.0 s, and a second N 2 purge of 30 s. This reaction sequence is represented as 2-30-1-30. Pressure transients during TMA and HF exposures were ∼40 mTorr and ∼80 mTorr, respectively. These pressure transients were observed on top of the base pressure of ∼1 Torr in the reactor.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>displays linear etching of the Al 2 O 3 film. A slope of the mass change versus time yields a mass change per cycle (MCPC) of -15.9 ng/(cm 2 cycle). This MCPC represents the removal of 9.4 × 10 13 "Al 2 O 3 " units/(cm 2 cycle). This MCPC is also equivalent to an etch rate of 0.51 Å/cycle based on the Al 2 O 3 ALD film density of 3.1 g/cm 3 determined by XRR. All ALE cycles show mass loss except during the first ALE cycle. The first cycle displays mass gains of ΔM TMA = 32 ng/cm 2 and ΔM HF = 33 ng/cm 2 . The mass gain for ΔM TMA during the first TMA exposure is attributed to the formation of AlCH 3 * surface species on the initial hydroxylated Al 2 O 3 substrate. The asterisks designate a surface species. The mass gain for ΔM HF during the first HF exposure is attributed to the fluorination of the Al 2 O 3 substrate. The HF exposure reacts with AlCH 3 * to form AlF* surface species. HF exposure can also fluorinate the underlying Al 2 O 3 film to form an AlF 3 surface layer. The reaction Al 2 O 3 + 6HF → 2AlF 3 + 3H 2 O is spontaneous with ΔG= -49 kcal at 300 °C. 27 This first cycle establishes the initial AlF 3 layer on the Al 2 O 3 substrate.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Mass change versus time for Al 2 O 3 ALE using sequential TMA and HF exposures at 300 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,60.49,117.18,239.98,187.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Enlargement of linear region of Figure 1 showing the individual mass changes during the sequential TMA and HF exposures at 300 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,324.45,69.17,239.98,181.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. (a) Mass change after the TMA exposure (ΔM TMA ), mass change after the HF exposure (ΔM HF ) and mass change per cycle (MCPC) versus number of ALE cycles at 300 °C. (b) ΔM TMA /MCPC ratio versus number of ALE cycles.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,324.45,367.88,239.98,245.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>displays the mass change during 100 ALE cycles at 250, 275, 300, and 325 °C using the reaction sequence of 2-30-1-30. The initial Al 2 O 3 ALD films were grown by 100 cycles of Al 2 O 3 ALD at the same temperatures. The mass changes versus time during Al 2 O 3 ALE are linear at all temperatures. The MCPC increases with temperature from -4.2 ng/(cm 2 cycle) at 250 °C to -23.3 ng/(cm 2 cycle) at 325 °C. These MCPCs correspond to etch rates that increase from 0.14 Å/cycle at 250 °C to 0.75 Å/cycle at 325 °C. The determination of these etch rates is based on the Al 2 O 3 ALD film density of 3.1 g/cm 3 . These results indicate that the Al 2 O 3 etch rate can be controlled by the reaction temperature. The nucleation of Al 2 O 3 ALE was examined at different temperatures during the first several TMA and HF exposures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>shows an enlargement of the mass changes during the first two Al 2 O 3 ALE cycles for the different temperatures in Figure 5. The first TMA exposure displays mass gains of ΔM TMA = 27-32 ng/cm 2 at 250-325 °C. These mass gains result from the reaction of AlOH* surface species with TMA according to AlOH* + Al(CH 3 ) 3 → AlOAl(CH 3 ) 2 * + CH 4 . The first HF exposure in Figure 6 then shows mass gains of ΔM HF = 33-36 ng/cm 2 at 250-325 °C. These mass gains result from the reaction of AlCH 3 * surface species with HF according to AlCH 3 * + HF → AlF* + CH 4 . In addition, some of the underlying Al 2 O 3 is also converted to an AlF 3 surface layer. The fluorination reaction Al 2 O 3 + 6HF → 2AlF 3 + 3H 2 O is spontaneous over the temperature range from 250 to 325 °C. The Gibbs free energy changes are negative and change slightly from ΔG= -53.8 kcal at 250 °C to ΔG = -46.8 kcal at 325 °C. 27 Figure 6 shows that the fluorination of Al 2 O 3 to form an 2AlF 3 surface layer is nearly constant at all temperatures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. (a) Mass change after TMA exposure (ΔM TMA ) versus TMA exposure time at 300 °C (b) Mass change after HF exposure (ΔM HF ) versus HF exposure time at 300 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,60.49,146.67,239.98,274.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Mass change versus time for Al 2 O 3 ALE using sequential TMA and HF exposures at 250, 275, 300, and 325 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,324.45,223.71,239.98,172.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><figDesc>2 O 3 ALE at 250, 275, and 325 °C. Mass losses are observed after the TMA exposures. These mass losses suggest that Al(CH 3 ) 3 can remove the AlF 3 surface layer as volatile AlF(CH 3 ) 2 product according to the reactions AlF 3 * + Al(CH 3 ) 3 → AlF 2 CH 3 * + AlF(CH 3 ) 2 and AlF 2 (CH 3 )* + Al(CH 3 ) 3 → 2AlF(CH 3 ) 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><figDesc>Figure 7a displays a mass loss of ΔM TMA = -10.5 ng/cm 2 after the TMA exposure for 2.0 s at 250 °C. Larger mass decreases are observed after the TMA exposures at 275 and 325 °C. Figures 7b shows a mass loss of ΔM TMA = -20.5 ng/cm 2 after a</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Expansion of first two ALE cycles in Figure 5 showing the individual mass changes during the sequential TMA and HF exposures at 250, 275, 300, and 325 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,60.49,69.17,239.98,189.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Enlargement of linear region of Figure 5 showing the individual mass changes during the sequential TMA and HF exposures at (a) 250, (b) 275 and (c) 325 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,324.45,223.71,239.98,311.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>These Al 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>O 3 ALD films were deposited using 150 cycles of TMA and H 2 O with a reaction sequence of 1-20-1-20. The XRR scans of the Al 2 O 3 ALD films on the Si wafers grown at 300 °C versus the number of TMA and HF reaction cycles at 300 °C are displayed in Figure S1 in the Supporting Information.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Temperature dependence of (a) ΔM TMA and ΔM HF and (b) MCPC for Al 2 O 3 ALE.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,324.45,154.21,239.98,244.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. X-ray reflectivity and spectroscopic ellipsometry measurements of Al 2 O 3 film thickness versus number of Al 2 O 3 ALE cycles for initial Al 2 O 3 ALD films grown using 150 Al 2 O 3 ALD cycles.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,60.49,69.17,239.98,190.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Infrared absorbance showing the loss of Al-O stretching vibration in bulk Al 2 O 3 versus number of Al 2 O 3 ALE cycles at 300 °C. These FTIR spectra were referenced to the initial ZrO 2 nanoparticles.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,60.49,497.37,239.98,219.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Difference infrared absorbance spectra from 800 to 1300 cm -1 during Al 2 O 3 ALE at 300 °C. The difference spectra recorded after the (a) TMA and (b) HF exposures were referenced using the spectra after the previous HF and TMA exposures, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,324.45,102.67,239.98,214.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><figDesc>This reaction of Al(CH 3 ) 3 with Al-O-Al bonds on the Al 2 O 3 substrate can be expressed as-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12. Difference infrared absorbance spectra from 2500 to 4000 cm -1 during Al 2 O 3 ALE at 300 °C. The difference spectra recorded after the (a) TMA and (b) HF exposures were referenced using the spectra after the previous HF and TMA exposures, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,60.49,69.17,239.98,206.59" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13. Schematic of proposed reaction mechanism for Al 2 O 3 ALE showing (A) HF reaction and (B) TMA reaction.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,60.49,556.04,239.98,171.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>MCPC, Etch Rate, ΔM TMA , ΔM HF , Ratio, x, xMCPC, and %AlF 3 removed for Al 2 O 3 ALE at Different Temperatures temperature (°C) MCPC ng/(cm 2 cycle) etch rate (Å/cycle) ΔM TMA ng/(cm 2 cycle) ΔM HF ng/(cm 2 cycle) ratio</figDesc><table><row><cell>x</cell><cell>xMCPC %AlF 3 removed</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>DOI: 10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b00111 Chem. Mater. 2016, 28, 2994-3003</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overview of Atomic Layer Etching in the Semiconductor Industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kanarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sriraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vahedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gottscho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">20802</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching: An Industry Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Carver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plombon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Romero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tronic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Turkot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS J. Solid State Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5005" to="N5009" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Deposition: An Overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching: What Can We Learn from Atomic Layer Deposition?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Faraz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS J. Solid State Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5023" to="N5032" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasma Atomic Layer Etching Using Conventional Plasma Equipment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kushner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching at the Tipping Point: An Overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Oehrlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Metzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS J. Solid State Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5041" to="N5053" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism of Thermal Al 2 O 3 Atomic Layer Etching Using Sequential Reactions with Sn(acac) 2 and HF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3648" to="3657" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching of Al 2 O 3 Using Sequential, Self-Limiting Thermal Reactions with Sn(acac) 2 and HF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACS Nano</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2061" to="2070" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching of HfO 2 Using Sequential, Self-Limiting Thermal Reactions with Sn(acac) 2 and HF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS J. Solid State Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5013" to="N5022" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Etching of AlF 3 Using Sequential, Self-Limiting Thermal Reactions with Sn-(acac) 2 and Hydrogen Fluoride</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25385" to="25393" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Osakada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Transmetalation</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fundamentals of Molecular Catalysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kurosawa</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Amsterdam</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redistribution and Exchange Reactions in Groups IIB-VIIB</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lockhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Spessard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Miessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Organometallic Chemistry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b00111</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemistry of Materials Article</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2994" to="3003" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fluorine as a Structure-Directing Element in Organometallic Fluorides: Discrete Molecules, Supramolecular Self-Assembly and Host-Guest Complexation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Roesky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Haiduc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2249" to="2264" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<pubPlace>Dalton Trans</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stannocene as Cyclopentadienyl Transfer Agent in Transmetalation Reactions with Lanthanide Metals for the Synthesis of Tris(cyclopentadienyl)lanthanides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Janiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">636</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2387" to="2390" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesis and Spectroscopic Properties of Bis(trimethylsilyl)amides of the Alkaline-Earth Metals Magnesium, Calcium, Strontium, and Barium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Westerhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inorg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gielen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pannell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tiekink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Tin Chemistry: Fundamentals, Frontiers and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>West Sussex, United Kingdom</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bis-(Pentane-2,4-Dionato)-Tin(II),Bis(1,1,1-Trifluoropentane-2,4-Dionato)-Tin(II), and Bis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F R</forename><surname>Ewings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fenton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1,1,1,5,5,5-Hexafluoropentane-2,4. 1975</date>
			<pubPlace>Dalton Trans</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Derivatives of Divalent Germanium, Tin, and Lead -Dionato)-Tin(II)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D B</forename><surname>Darwent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Dissociation Energies in Simple Molecules; National Bureau of Standards</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>United States Department of Commerce</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface Chemistry of Atomic Layer Deposition: A Case Study for the Trimethylaluminum/Water Process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">121301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscous Flow Reactor with Quartz Crystal Microbalance for Thin Film Growth by Atomic Layer Deposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Elam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Groner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Sci. Instrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2981" to="2987" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Deposition of AlF 3 Using Trimethylaluminum and Hydrogen Fluoride</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14185" to="14194" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Refractive Index and Dispersion of Fluorides and Oxides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Medenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Ref. Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="931" to="970" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pyrolysis of Alucone Molecular Layer Deposition Films Studied Using In Situ Transmission Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14603" to="14612" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission Infrared-Spectroscopy of High Area Solid-Surfaces -A Useful Method for Sample Preparation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ballinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C S</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1676" to="1678" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Layer Deposition of Ultrathin and Conformal Al 2 O 3 films on BN Particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">371</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Outokumpu Research Oy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<publisher>Pori</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Finland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>HSC Chemistry</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Thickness of Native Oxides on Aluminum Alloys and Single Crystals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Evertsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bertram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rullik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Merte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shipilin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Soldemo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vinogradov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Carla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weissenrieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goẗhelid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mikkelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lundgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Mechanism of Low Temperature Oxidation (23-450 C) of Polycrystalline Nickel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigation on Initial Oxidation Kinetics of Al, Ni, and Hf Metal Film Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Placido</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. Opt. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SiO 2 Ultra Thin Film Growth Kinetics as Investigated by Surface Techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Derrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Commandre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation of Ultrathin Oxide Films on Silicon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fehlner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1723" to="1727" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxidation Kinetics of Si(111)7 × 7 in the Submonolayer Regime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Coon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B: Condens. Matter Mater. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7739" to="7749" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Oxidation of Metals at High Temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bedworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Inst. Met</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="1923">1923</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accounting for Nanometer-Thick Adventitious Carbon Contamination in X-ray Absorption Spectra of Carbon-Based Materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mangolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mcclimon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Carpick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12258" to="12265" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of X-Ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy in Corrosion Science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Castle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative Electron Spectroscopy of Surfaces: A Standard Data Base for Electron Inelastic Mean Free Paths in Solids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Seah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dench</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Interface Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vibrational Spectra of Dimethyl and Diethyl Aluminum Fluoride</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weidlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Krieg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Organomet. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface Chemistry of Al 2 O 3 Deposition Using Al(CH 3 ) 3 and H 2 O in a Binary Reaction Sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Way</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.chemmater.6b00111</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemistry of Materials Article</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2994" to="3003" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Surf. Sci.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
