<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism and kinetics of thin zirconium and hafnium oxide film growth in an ALD reactor</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Motorola DigitalDNA Labs</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Maxim</forename><surname>Deminsky</surname></persName>
							<email>m.deminsky@kintech.ru</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrei</forename><surname>Knizhnik</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ivan</forename><surname>Belov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stanislav</forename><surname>Umanskii</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Rykova</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Bagaturõyants</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Boris</forename><surname>Potapkin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kinetic Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">RRC &apos;&apos;Kurchatov Institute&apos;&apos;</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kurchatov Sq. 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>123182</postCode>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Stoker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">DigitalDNA Labs Semiconductor Products Sector</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Motorola Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2100 E. Eliott</addrLine>
									<postCode>85284</postCode>
									<settlement>Tempe</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anatoli</forename><surname>Korkin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">DigitalDNA Labs Semiconductor Products Sector</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Motorola Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2100 E. Eliott</addrLine>
									<postCode>85284</postCode>
									<settlement>Tempe</settlement>
									<region>AZ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism and kinetics of thin zirconium and hafnium oxide film growth in an ALD reactor</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A70927AA67592BE6094DC29BC1E61BED</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.susc.2003.10.056</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 11 December 2002; accepted for publication 3 October 2003</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-07-04T09:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Zirconium</term>
					<term>Hafnium</term>
					<term>Growth</term>
					<term>Surface chemical reaction</term>
					<term>Dielectric phenomena</term>
					<term>Models of surface kinetics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A mechanism of HfO 2 and ZrO 2 film growth in an ALD reactor from metal chlorides and water vapor is proposed to explain the experimentally observed features of the process: the formation of less than one monolayer per cycle and the dependence of the film growth rate (mass or thickness increment per cycle) and the residual chorine concentration on the process temperature. Energy parameters of the relevant gas-surface reactions are estimated from quantum-chemical density functional theory calculations. The rate constants of the elementary reactions are calculated using RRKM theory. ALD process simulations, based on the proposed mechanism and a transient plug-flow reactor model, are consistent with the available experimental data, indicating a decrease in deposition rate with increasing temperature. The reduction in deposition rate is attributed to the increased dehydroxylation of the film surface as the temperature is increased. The H 2 O adsorption energy was found to increase with increasing dehydroxylation from 33 to 53 kcal/mol for ZrO 2 and from 35 to 51 kcal/mol for HfO 2 . A kinetic Monte Carlo model of film growth, based on the proposed mechanism, describes the observed temperature dependence of the residual chlorine concentration in the film in terms of the steric repulsion between chemisorbed surface groups and adsorbed MCl 4 molecules (M ¼ Zr, Hf).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Zirconium and hafnium oxide films are characterized by specific electrical, optical, and chemical properties, which make them of great interest as catalysts <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref> and as candidates for SiO 2 gate dielectric replacement in the next generation of field effect transistors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. Atomic layer chemical vapor deposition (ALCVD or ALD) is one of the most promising methods of oxide film growth and is being studied intensively <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In particular, this interest is due to the capability of controlling epitaxial or amorphous film growth to an atomic layer precision.</p><p>The growth of hafnium and zirconium oxide films (MO x , M ¼ Hf, Zr) in an ALD reactor with MCl 4 and water as precursors, the structural properties and chemical composition of these films were comprehensively studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. It was shown that at low temperatures the ALD method produced uniform amorphous films. However, these films were of low density and were highly contaminated with chlorine atoms. The subsequent annealing, commonly used to densify the films and to remove contaminations, leads to the formation of polycrystalline structures, which often suffer from high leakage current densities. Films grown at higher temperatures had a low chlorine contamination, but even as-deposited films were polycrystalline in this case. Hence, a fundamental understanding of the chemistry and kinetics of oxide film growth in an ALD reactor is of primary interest and importance in order to find the best conditions for obtaining high-quality films.</p><p>In the experimental works cited above a qualitative chemical mechanism of MO x film growth was suggested and discussed. The thermodynamic characteristics of the main surface half-reactions proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> were theoretically estimated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> using quantum-chemical density functional theory (DFT) calculations of relatively small molecular clusters. Nevertheless, a quantitative description of film growth kinetics has not been developed so far, in spite of the availability of numerous experimental data on MO 2 film growth in an ALD reactor. Moreover, as it will be shown below, the existing interpretation of MO 2 film growth experiments meets significant difficulties.</p><p>This work is dedicated to a theoretical investigation of the mechanism and kinetics of MO 2 film growth in an ALD reactor using MCl 4 and water as precursors. We performed a detailed analysis of the deposition mechanism and estimated the rate parameters of elementary reactions using quantum-chemical methods and RRKM theory. These parameters were then incorporated into the reactor-scale and kinetic Monte Carlo (kMC) simulations. This paper is organized as follows. The chemical mechanism of the ALD process is analyzed in detail in Section 2. A preliminary ab initio estimation of rate constants for the main chemical reactions is given in Section 3, and technical details of quantum-kinetic calculations are given in Appendix A. An extended mechanism and the results of formal kinetic and Monte Carlo simulations of MO 2 film growth are presented in Section 4. Finally, some conclusions and implications are outlined in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Mechanism of MO 2 film growth in an ALD reactor: state of the art and problems</head><p>The main experimental features of MO 2 film growth kinetics in the ALD process can be summarized as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>:</p><p>(a) the MO 2 film growth rate (mass or thickness increment per cycle) on hydroxylated surfaces is much higher than on bare metal oxide surfaces; (b) the maximum amount of the deposited oxide (film mass increment) per cycle is 30-50% of MO 2 monolayer (ML), depending on process conditions; (c) the average film mass and thickness increments per ALD cycle decrease with increasing temperature (more than a factor of 2 in the temperature range 200-800 °C); (d) the Cl:M ratio ðxÞ in the chemisorbed MCl x surface groups at the surface of a growing film varies from x ¼ 2 (MCl 2 ) at low temperature (200 °C) to x ¼ 3-4 at high temperature (600 °C); (e) the residual chlorine concentration in the film decreases from $5% to less than 1% as temperature increases from 200 to 600 °C.</p><p>The following simplified empirical mechanism was suggested by Kytokivi and co-workers <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref> for MO 2 film growth at low temperatures, when the surface is normally hydroxylated:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">MðOHÞ 2 =s= þ MCl 4 () MO 2 =b= þ MCl 2 =s= þ 2HCl<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">MCl 2 =s= þ 2H 2 O () MðOHÞ 2 =s= þ 2HCl<label>ð2Þ</label></formula><p>Here, we use the notation for surface sites in accordance with that generally accepted in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Designations /s/ and /b/ correspond to the surface groups and the bulk oxide, respectively. Overall reactions (1) and (2) compose one ALD cycle. Each of them can be naturally represented as a sequence of simple reaction steps shown schematically in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>. These reactions lead to the formation of a stoichiometric single (though, incomplete, see point (b) above) MO 2 submonolayer (see point (b) above) on a hydroxylated metal oxide surface. This scheme of complex chemical reactions of MCl 4 and H 2 O with the surface of a growing film is based on the results of quantum-chemical calculations <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref> of the t-ZrO 2 (0 0 1) surface. It was shown that water adsorption at this surface should proceed with dissociation (a dissociatively adsorbed water molecule was found to be somewhat more stable than a molecularly adsorbed one) to form two bibridged hydroxyl groups in accordance with experimental data <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>To explain the decrease in the film growth rate (see points (a) and (c) above) and the variation of the composition of chemisorbed MCl x surface groups (point (d)) with temperature, it was assumed that the concentration of surface OH groups is controlled by the dehydroxylation (water desorption) reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> MðOHÞ</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">2 =s= () MO=s= þ H 2 O<label>ð3Þ</label></formula><p>drawn schematically in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>.</p><p>An increase in temperature leads to a decrease in the number of reactive -OH surface sites through reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. Hence, the probability of the formation of the bridged MCl 2 /s/ groups in the reaction of MCl 3 /s/ groups with the neighboring hydroxyl (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>) becomes lower at higher temperatures, and MCl 3 /s/ groups become the dominating surface species after the MCl 4 pulse is introduced in the ALD chamber. The chemisorbed MCl 3 /s/ groups can react with water in the same way as MCl 2 /s/ in reaction (2), thus allowing the completion of the ALD cycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Surface dehydroxylation (reaction (3)) explains the decrease in the mass increment per cycle and the increase in the number of Cl atoms per metal in the surface MCl x /s/ groups. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, it was suggested that the growth rate can also be affected by the chemical readsorbtion of HCl. Therefore this process will also be taken into account in the kinetic scheme developed below.</p><p>The high Cl:M ratio ðx &gt; 3Þ in MCl x surface groups observed after the MCl 4 pulse at temperatures higher than 400 °C (point (d)) was explained by the dissociative chemisorption of MCl 4 on the fully dehydroxylated surface areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> MO=s= þ MCl 4 ()</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">MClOðMCl 3 Þ=s=<label>ð4Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">MClOðMCl 3 Þ=s= þ 2H 2 O () MO 2 =b= þ MO=s= þ 4HCl<label>ð5Þ</label></formula><p>According to the experimental data (see point (a)), reaction (4) should result in a lower mass increment per cycle than reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</p><p>It should be noted that both MCl 2 /s/ and MCl 3 / s/ are bulky groups, which screen the nearest active sites, preventing their reactions with gas-phase MCl M OH OH M O H 2 O Fig. 2. Water desorption reaction.</p><p>of MO 2 deposition in an ALD cycle (see point (b)) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>Hence, important features of the MO 2 ALD process (points (a)-(d)) can be explained by the mechanism that combines low-temperature deposition at a more reactive hydroxylated surface (reactions (1) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>)), surface dehydroxylation (reaction (3)) and high-temperature deposition at a less reactive dehydroxylated surface (reactions ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">4</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">5</ref>)).</p><p>Although the suggested simplified mechanism (reactions (1)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">5</ref>)) can qualitatively explain some important features of the MO 2 ALD process <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, its application to the quantitative description of film growth kinetics meets significant difficulties. First, this mechanism cannot explain the slow decrease in the film growth rate with increasing temperature observed experimentally (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>). The recombination reaction of surface -OH groups (3), which diminishes the surface density of active -OH sites, should give a sharp decrease in the mass increment per cycle Dm 0 with temperature at a constant adsorption energy E ad . Indeed, the mass increment per cycle should be proportional to the number density of surface OH groups [OH] s , which is described by the well-known Langmuir equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Dm 0 $ ½OH s $ 1=ð1 þ K expðÀE ad =RT ÞÞ; K % 4n s x=nv:<label>ð6Þ</label></formula><p>Here n is the water vapor number density, v is the average velocity of gas-phase molecules, n s is the total number density of surface sites available for water adsorption, and x is the characteristic desorption frequency of water molecules. The hydroxylation degree (b ¼ ½OH s =2n s ) calculated by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">6</ref>) as a function of temperature for typical values of E ad (in the range 25-45 kcal/mol <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>) is given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>. It is evident that an increase in temperature by only DT $ 100 °C leads to about 90% surface dehydroxylation for all E ad values, indicating that virtually all of the variation in the deposition rate with temperature should occur within a 100 °C temperature range. However, this behavior is obviously in contradiction with the available experimental data, also shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, in which the deposition rate gradually decreases over a range of more than 400 °C <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</p><p>Another deficiency of the existing mechanism is concerned with the chlorine contamination in the film. Because the water concentration during the water pulse is in significant excess with respect to the total amount of surface sites and the chemical readsorption of HCl is presumably low, the water reaction with surface chlorine atoms can be accurately described by the first-order kinetic equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">d½Cl=dt $ ÀkðT Þ½Cln H 2 O ; ½Cl $ expðÀkðT Þ Â n H 2 O Â sÞ;<label>ð7Þ</label></formula><p>where kðT Þ is the effective rate constant of the water reaction with surface chlorine and s is the duration of the water treatment. Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>) is valid if the dependence of the effective rate constant kðT Þ on the local environment of chemisorbed Cl atoms is disregarded as was implicitly assumed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><p>According to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>), the residual chlorine concentration should depend exponentially on T and s. It should be noted first that the experimental dependence of the residual chlorine concentration on the substrate temperature (see point (e)) is very far from the exponential form of Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. The exponential dependence on s is also in strong contradiction with the experimental data. Squares and circles are experimental thickness and mass increments per ALD cycle in ZrO 2 film growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Curves are the hydroxylation degree calculated by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">6</ref>) for E ad ¼ 25 kcal/mol (dashed-dotted line), E ad ¼ 35 kcal/mol (dashed line) and 45 kcal/mol (dashed-dotted line).</p><p>Since the steady state film growth rate is lower than 0.5 ML per ALD cycle (see point (b)), several ALD cycles are required to bury a chemisorbed chlorine atom inside the growing film (more than three cycles to form a monolayer over a chlorine atom). Hence, according to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>), in order that about 5% Cl remain in the growing film (see point (e)), about 37% ð0:37 3 % 0:05Þ of the surface chlorine atoms adsorbed during the previous metal precursor pulse should not react with water during each pulse. However, such a significant amount of unreacted Cl atoms was not observed in mass increment measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The problems outlined above show that the existing mechanism of HfO 2 and ZrO 2 film growth in an ALD reactor needs a qualitative modification. To eliminate the contradiction between the theoretical curves obtained based on the current understanding of the film growth mechanism and the experimental temperature dependence of the film growth rate as demonstrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, we suggest that the water adsorption energy decreases with increasing hydroxylation degree. In this case the hydroxylation degree and, hence, the film growth rate (see Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">6</ref>)) will decrease much slower with temperature than for a constant water adsorption energy.</p><p>Estimations of the ratio of film growth rates at low and high temperatures based on Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> show that an agreement with experiment can be achieved if the increase in the water adsorption energy through the temperature range from 200 to 600 °C is $15 kcal/mol. This value is in agreement with thermogravimetric experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref> of water adsorption on ZrO 2 samples. Similar results were obtained in quantum-chemical calculations of water adsorption energy <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>In order to describe the smooth dependence of the residual chlorine concentration in the as-grown film on the water pulse duration and the substrate temperature, we made an additional assumption that the rate constants of reactions (2) and (5) depend on the local chemical environment of the chemisorbed chlorine atom. It is reasonable to assume that a Cl atom becomes stronger bound to the surface as the number of the nearest neighboring metal atoms increases and, hence, the number of short M-Cl contacts also increases. In this case, the activation energy of possible reactions between water and chemisorbed chlorine will also increase. Steric hindrances from neighboring chemisorbed surface groups will act in the same direction. Therefore, as the film grows, the reaction of water with a chemisorbed chlorine atom will slow down. This effect results in the fact that the residual chlorine concentration is not described by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>) and the chlorine atoms can be can be readily captured in the growing film. It should be noted here that the processes of chlorine diffusion should also be taken into account under real deposition conditions.</p><p>Thus, the analysis presented above indicates that the mechanism and kinetics of the ALD process cannot be interpreted even qualitatively without taking into account stereochemical effects, in particular, the effects of surface coverage on the reactivity of chemisorbed surface species. An appropriate approach to the description of the ALD process should involve atomistic concepts and a more detailed formulation of the mechanism in terms of surface groups and elementary reactions of key chemical steps.</p><p>At present, even approximate estimates of the necessary rate constants for the gas-surface reactions involved in Zr(Hf)O 2 ALD are unavailable in the literature. Therefore, we performed ab initio quantum-chemical and quantum-kinetic calculations to evaluate some of the most important reaction constants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Preliminary ab initio evaluation of reaction rate parameters for the key reaction steps of MO 2 deposition</head><p>A great diversity of surface reactions can proceed on the growing Zr(Hf)O 2 surface, which is covered by various chemisorbed surface groups. These reactions include reactions of incident gasphase molecules (MCl 4 , H 2 O, and HCl) with the surface, yielding ''primary'' surface groups MCl 3 / s/, MCl 2 /s/, and OH/s/. These groups can further react with incident gas-phase molecules yielding longer and more complicated surface groups like</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">-MCl 2 -OH, -O-MCl 3 , -MCl 2 -O-MCl 3 , -O- MCl 2 -OH, -O-MCl 2 -O-MCl 3 , etc.</formula><p>Reactions between chemisorbed surface groups, assisted with their surface diffusion, lead to the formation of a new surface layer (densification). It is hardly possible to describe all these reactions at the ab initio level. However, a chemical consideration shows that most of them involve interaction between an M-Cl bond of an MCl x moiety and an O-H bond of an H 2 O molecule or of an M-OH fragment. Chemically, there is no significant difference between these interactions and interactions involved in basic reactions ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>), because these interactions are essentially local.</p><p>Therefore, the main goal of this section was to use ab initio quantum-chemical calculations and the quantum-statistical theory of chemical reactions in order to determine the basic features of the elementary steps of the proposed overall mechanism (reactions (1a), (1b), (2a), (2b), see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>) and to obtain basic estimates for their rate constants. Because of the local character of interactions involved in these processes, on the one hand, and in order to avoid indeterminacy associated with the local chemical environment on the surface, on the other hand, we approximated real surface reactions with appropriate prototype gas-phase molecular systems. Thus, steps (1a) and (1b) of reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> were approximated by the molecular reaction</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">MðOHÞ 4 þ MCl 4 ! MðOHÞ 4 Á Á Á MCl 4 ! MðOHÞ 3 À OMCl 3 þ HCl;</formula><p>whereas steps (2a) and (2b) of reaction (2) were approximated by the molecular reaction</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">MðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 þ H 2 O ! MðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 Á Á Á H 2 O ! MClðOHÞ 3 þ HCl</formula><p>In general, calculations of the rate constants of surface reactions require rather sophisticated models. However, a comparison of the results obtained in our work using periodic-type slab models <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and cluster models of surface reactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> with the results obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> showed that even rather small molecular models of surface sites qualitatively reproduce interaction energies in chemical systems typical for ZrO 2 and HfO 2 deposition processes. Moreover, the use of simple molecular models excludes the uncertainties associated with the real structure of surface active sites and their variety. In addition, this approach avoids complicated problems connected with the treatment of vibrational degrees of freedom.</p><p>We calculated the energies and the structural and vibrational parameters for the reagents, the transition states, and the products of these model gas-phase reactions. Then, we applied statistical theory to calculate reaction rate parameters for the corresponding gas-surface reactions within an ad hoc quantum-kinetic model that takes into account the effects of energy exchange with the bulk and the freezing of some degrees of freedom at the surface.</p><p>Ab initio calculations were performed within the framework of DFT with the hybrid threeparameter Becke-Lee-Yang-Parr (B3LYP) exchange-correlation functional <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref> using the Gaussian 98 program package <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. The Zr, Hf, and Cl atoms were described using the Hay-Wadt pseudopotentials <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>) and LANL2DZ basis set; for Cl atoms, the LANL2DZ basis set was augmented with polarization d functions (with an exponent of 0.75). The O and H atoms were described with the 6-31G(d,p) basis set <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>.</p><p>The frequencies of normal vibrations were calculated for all fully optimized structures and used to verify whether the stationary points found were true minima or first-order saddle points. These frequencies were also used in the subsequent quantum-kinetic calculations of gas-surface reaction rate parameters. The results of quantumchemical calculations for the model gas-phase reactions are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Qualitative shapes of the corresponding reaction path profiles U rp ðq r Þ (q r is the reaction coordinate) are presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. The energies of transition complexes (TC f ) and products are measured from the energy of the corresponding isolated reagents.</p><p>The results of quantum-chemical calculations show that the reactions under consideration proceed via stable intermediate complexes M(OH)-OMCl 3 /s/ and MCl(OH) 3 /s/ formed by the gas-phase reagent (MCl 4 or H 2 O) with the active surface site (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>) through a typical donoracceptor coordination bond. These intermediate complexes may play an important part in the kinetics of film growth. It will be shown below that the stabilization of these complexes at low tem-peratures leads to the blocking of active surface sites and, hence, to a decrease in the film growth rate (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> and <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</p><p>The quantum-chemical calculations performed using molecular models do not take into account energy relaxation into the bulk. We developed a special approach in which the total set of degrees of freedom for a large molecule is divided into two sets (see, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>). One set including the majority of the degrees of freedom acts as a thermal bath. The other set is directly related to the active reacting center and includes the reaction coordinate. This set includes only a relatively small number of degrees of freedom.</p><p>We assumed that a gas-surface reaction that proceeds through a precursor can be treated in terms of the well-developed statistical theory of gasphase bimolecular reactions proceeding through a long-lived intermediate complex (see, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35]</ref>). The surface centers A/s/ (reagent), C/s/ (product), and AB/s/ (precursor) are considered in the model as the gas-phase molecules A and C and the donoracceptor complex AB embedded into the bulk (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). The A, C, and AB particles themselves are treated here based on the results of gas-phase quantum-chemical calculations.</p><p>The most important effect of the bulk is the relaxation of the internal energy of the A/s/, C/s/ </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">E ad AB/s/ E f TC f E r C/s/+D ZrðOHÞ 2 =s= þ ZrCl 4 ! ZrðOHÞOZrCl 3 =s= þ HCl ZrðOHÞ 4 þ ZrCl 4 ! ZrðOHÞ 4 -ZrCl 4 ! ZrðOHÞ 3 -OZrCl 3 þ HCl Fig. 4a</formula><p>)26.9 )6.8 )11.7 HfðOHÞ 2 =s= þ HfCl 4 ! HfðOHÞOHfCl 3 =s= þ HCl HfðOHÞ 4 þ HfCl 4 ! HfðOHÞ 4 -HfCl 4 ! HfðOHÞ 3 -OHfCl 3 þ HCl Fig. 4a )24.2 )8.6 )14.0 Fig. 4. Schematic reaction path profile of the gas-surface reactions via a strongly adsorbed precursor AB/s/: (a) decomposition of AB/s/ to products C/s/ and D proceeds via a rigid transition complex; (b) decomposition via a loose transition complex. TC ad and TC f are transition complexes for adsorption of B at A/s/ and for AB/s/ decomposition to products C/s/ and D.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ZrCl 2 =s= þ H 2 O ! ZrClðOHÞ 3 =s= þ HCl ZrðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 þ H 2 O ! ZrðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 -H 2 O ! ZrClðOHÞ 3 þ HCl</formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">HfCl 2 =s= þ H 2 O ! HfClðOHÞ 3 =s= þ HCl HfðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 þ H 2 O ! HfðOHÞ 2 Cl 2 H 2 O ! HfClðOHÞ 3 þ HCl</formula><p>and AB/s/ surface species. For the systems considered, vibrational energy relaxation is governed by the bulk thermal conductivity. The relaxation time can be estimated from the data for metal oxides reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> s rel $ 10 À11 -10 À12 s:</p><p>The vibrationally excited precursor AB/s/* can decay not only via energy transfer to the bulk but also via a chemical transformation (desorption of B and reaction with the formation of D and C/s/). These chemical processes can be characterized by the ''chemical'' lifetime s Ã ch , which was estimated in the framework of RRKM theory (see, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35]</ref>) using the reaction parameters of the reagents B and A/s/, the precursor AB/s/, and the transition complexes determined from the results of quantum-chemical calculations. For all the reactions considered, it was found that at T &lt; 700 °C</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">s ch &gt;$ 10 À10 s:<label>ð9Þ</label></formula><p>Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">s rel ( s Ã ch ;<label>ð10Þ</label></formula><p>and, therefore, the vibrationally excited AB/s/* complex relaxes to attain the Boltzmann energy distribution before the chemical transformation occurs. This fact leads to two consequences:</p><p>1. The direct reactions (proceeding without the formation of an intermediate adsorption com</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">- plex) B þ A=s= () k ðdÞ f k ðdÞ r D þ C=s=<label>ð11Þ</label></formula><p>are suppressed by energy relaxation and can be excluded from the kinetic scheme. 2. The formation of the adsorption complex, its decay to the reagents, and its transformation to the products</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">B þ A=s= () ka k d AB=s=;<label>ð12Þ</label></formula><p>AB=s= ()</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">k f kr D þ C=s=<label>ð13Þ</label></formula><p>proceeds to thermal equilibrium. Therefore, the rate constants k a , k d , k f and k r can be calculated using transition state theory (see, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>). The details of these calculations are described in Appendix A. The calculations of rate constants were performed in the temperature range 25-700 °C and were further used in the kinetic calculations described in Section 4 (reactions ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>).</p><p>Thus, the analysis of reactions with water and chlorine precursors given above shows that even the separate steps of reactions ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>) cannot be considered elementary and must be described by a multistage mechanism that includes the formation of an intermediate adsorption complex (B + A/s/ fi AB/s/). The intermediate complexes have a significant adsorption energy (E ad $ 15-20 kcal/mol), which becomes important at low temperatures T &lt; 200 °C (see below), where the film growth rate can decrease significantly because of the stabilization of the adsorption complex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Kinetic modeling of MO 2 film growth</head><p>Now we will show that the inclusion of the qualitative concept of the dependence of reaction parameters on the local chemical environment allows us to describe the main quantitative kinetic and mechanistic features of the ALD process. We used two different approaches for the simulation of MO 2 film growth: ALD reactor modeling in the framework of formal kinetics and kMC modeling.</p><p>The first approach was used to model the principal features of the film growth rate and to verify the kinetic parameters calculated using quantum-chemical methods. An accurate description of the processes of film contamination with Cl impurities requires a detailed consideration of the actual local surface structures, which cannot be readily implemented using simple rate expressions. Therefore, we used the kMC approach, which allows the local atomistic effects to be implemented in a natural way, to model Cl incorporation in the films.</p><p>We restricted our simulations to the temperature range T &lt; 700 °C, which is typical for conventional process conditions of zirconium and hafnium oxide ALD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Formal kinetic modeling</head><p>The kinetic scheme and rate parameters used in the simulations are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. To describe the surface of the growing film within formal kinetics, we introduced various groups of surface sites:</p><p>(1) sites that describe the varying degree of surface hydroxylation: M(OH) 2 /s/ (hydroxylated surface site), MO/s/ (dehydroxylated surface site, see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>); (2) sites that describe the physical adsorption of a metal precursor: MCl 4 M(OH) 2 /s/; (3) sites that describe the chemical adsorption of a metal precursor on hydroxylated sites: MOM(OH)Cl 3 /s/, MO 2 MCl 2 /s/ (see Fig. 1); (4) sites that describe the physical adsorption of a water: MO 2 MCl 2 H 2 O/s/, MO 2 MClOHH 2 O/s/; (5) sites that describe the products of water treatment: MO 2 MClOH/s/ (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>).</p><p>Reactions ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> correspond to the overall mechanism described by Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. The rate coefficients of these reactions were taken from the results of the ab initio calculations described in the previous section (see <ref type="bibr">Table 1)</ref>.</p><p>Reactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) describe the process of surface dehydroxylation/hydroxylation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>). We used a value of 10 13 1/s as an estimation of the pre-exponential factor (this value corresponds to the characteristic frequency of internal vibrations of the reaction center) for the desorption reaction. The activation energy of hydroxylation reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>, as it was mentioned above, depends on the degree of surface dehydroxylation. Therefore, it was treated as a variable parameter. In this study, we considered that the water adsorption energy is a linear function of the hydroxylation degree b for 1=2 &lt; b &lt; 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">E ad ¼ E 0 ad À De Á ð2b À 1Þ; 1=2 &lt; b &lt; 1; E 0 ad ; b &lt; 1=2:<label>ð14Þ</label></formula><p>The mechanism in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> was implemented in a non-steady-state plug-flow reactor model to simulate real ALD processes. The model assumes a uniform distribution of gas-mixture velocities at a given reactor cross section. Real experimental conditions (the reactor geometry is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>) are different from the proposed model. Indeed, the uniform distribution of gaseous species in the reactor cross section suggests the absence of diffusion and convection transport effects on the rates of surface chemical reactions. However, because the main objective of this work is to determine the principal features of the chemical mechanism, the aspects of detailed flow dynamics can be neglected at this stage of consideration. The goal of the simulations was to determine the remaining adjustable parameters based on the available experimental data. The following experimental data were used to verify the kinetic scheme and to adjust the reactor parameters: the dependence of the film growth rate on the process temperature, the time dependence of the film mass increment during the MCl 4 pulse, the ratio of the total film mass increment attained in an ALD cycle m 0 to the mass increment during the MCl 4 pulse m 1 the Cl:M ratio ðxÞ in the chemisorbed MCl x surface groups as a function of temperature, and the chlorine concentration in the film <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Calculations were carried out for the following experimental conditions of HfO 2 and ZrO 2 ALD <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>: carrier gas (N 2 ) pressure, 250 Pa; temperature range, 180-600 °C; reactor volume, 160 cm 3 ; substrate surface area, 220 cm 2 ; reactor cross section, 10.2 cm 2 ; substrate length, 6 cm; and carrier gas flow rate, 150 cm 3 /s.</p><p>In the experiments on ZrO 2 film growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, the durations of the ZrCl 4 pulse, the water vapor pulse, and the purge gas pulse following the ZrCl 4 pulse were each 2 s. The duration of the purge gas (N 2 ) pulse following the water pulse was 5 s. In the HfO 2 film growth experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the duration of the precursor (HfCl 4 , H 2 O) pulses and the purge gas pulses were all 2 s. The flow rates of precursors were estimated from the available data of their vapor pressure in the effusion cell: 1.8-3 cm 3 /s for MCl 4 and 2.4-3 cm 3 /s for water vapor. The partial pressures of precursors in the reaction chamber that correspond to the experimental conditions used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> can be approximately estimated at 2-4 Pa for MCl 4 precursors and at 4-6 Pa for H 2 O.</p><p>According to our discussion in Section 2, the growth of the oxide film at low temperatures is fully determined by reactions on the hydroxylated surface (reactions ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). The parameters of these reactions are known from our quantum-chemical and quantum-kinetic calculations. Therefore, the remaining process parameters that do not relate to the kinetic scheme in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> can be adequately determined using the experimental results for the low-temperature region within a reduced kinetic scheme that includes only reactions ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>. We found that the number density of available surface metal atoms n s ¼ 6Â 10 14 cm À2 for the growing ZrO 2 surface and n s ¼ 5 Â 10 14 cm À2 for the growing HfO 2 surface, the MCl 4 flow rate is 1.8 cm 3 /s, and the H 2 O flow rate is 2.4 cm 3 /s.</p><p>The variation of the film mass increment during one ALD cycle calculated with these parameters and the corresponding experimental data are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>. The theoretical curve describes well the typical behavior of the chloride-water ALD process: an increase in the film mass due to the adsorption of precursors, the flat portion of the curve during the purge pulse, a sharp decrease in the film mass during the water vapor pulse, and an additional mass decrease due to release of the adsorbed water. However, the theoretical curve somewhat deviates from experimental data in the transition region at the end of the MCl 4 pulse, where the curve flattens out. This deviation indicates that the rate of the MCl 4 reaction with surface OH/s/ groups may also depend on the degree of surface coverage by MCl x /s/ groups, as we suggested for water adsorption and for water interaction with MCl x /s/ groups (see Section 2). Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> demonstrates the dependence of the film mass increment Dm 0 on the temperature in the ZrCl 4 effusion cell, which, in its turn, determines the ZrCl 4 flow rate. The theoretical data were obtained using the values of the ZrCl 4 saturated vapor pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> to estimate the variation of the ZrCl 4 flow rate with temperature. For the case of low effusion cell temperatures, where the ZrCl 4 flow rate is insufficient to saturate the substrate surface during the ZrCl 4 pulse, Dm 0 increases rapidly with increasing effusion cell temperature. On the other hand, when the amount of ZrCl 4 is sufficient to saturate the surface, Dm 0 depends on the total number density of the available surface sites n s and becomes independent of the effusion cell temperature. Hence, we can see in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> that the relationship between n s and the ZrCl 4 flow rate is correctly reproduced with our choice of parameters. The behavior of curves reflects the fact that an increase in the temperature of the ZrCl 4 effusion cell from 145 to 160 °C leads to an increase in the precursor flow rate by a factor of $5. Therefore, within this temperature range, the system passes from the regime of precursor deficit to the saturation regime.</p><p>The results of the experiments [6,8,10] and simulations of the ZrO 2 and HfO 2 film growth rates as functions of the process temperature are shown, respectively, in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> and <ref type="figure">8</ref>. In accordance with the proposed model, water desorption/adsorption reactions ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>), which are sensitive to the surface coverage (see Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>)) determine the temperature dependence of the growth rate. The best agreement with the experimental data was achieved with E 0 ad ¼ E a ð28Þ À E a ð29Þ ¼ 45 and 47 kcal/mol Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. ZrO 2 film mass increment as a function of the precursor source temperature. Circles and solid line are experimental <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and modeling results at the reaction chamber temperature 290 °C; squares and dashed line are experimental <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and modeling results at the reaction chamber temperature 180 °C.  and De ¼ 25 and 22.5 kcal/mol for HfO 2 and ZrO 2 , respectively (where E a ð28Þ and E a ð29Þ are the activation energies of reactions ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). Thus, mechanism ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) describes satisfactorily the experimental temperature dependence of the growth rate and can be interpreted as a ''minimum'' mechanism in this sense. The values of the rate coefficients of all reactions of the ''minimum'' mechanism are determined from QC calculations. Therefore, the validity of the results is determined by the accuracy of the QC analysis and by our suggestion about the reasons for the decrease in the growth rate with increasing temperature.</p><p>However, one can see that the minimum mechanism suffers from essential drawbacks from the viewpoints of both its physical validity and experimental verification. First, the minimum mechanism neglects surface diffusion processes, which may be important in the water desorption mechanism. This assumption is valid only at high surface hydroxylation degrees. However, at low coverages, dehydroxylation is controlled by two processes: the diffusion-assisted reaction of hydroxyl groups to form a pre-desorption complex and the decomposition of this complex to desorb water. The first process is of the second order with respect to the concentration of surface hydroxyl groups, whereas the second one is of the first order. Depending on the reaction parameters and the hydroxylation degree, the overall rate of surface dehydroxylation can be limited by either process. It can, in its turn, affect the overall growth rate in the high temperature region, where the coverage decreases with increasing temperature. Second, the minimum mechanism cannot explain the experimental fact of the change in the Cl:M ratio ðxÞ in the chemisorbed MCl x surface groups from x ¼ 2 to x ¼ 3, because it operates with a single type of hydroxylated sites, namely, M(OH) 2 .</p><p>Because of the reasons discussed above, the minimum scheme was extended to take into account both the change in the state of chemisorbed MCl x surface groups and the diffusion processes in the framework of the formal kinetic approach (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). We introduced the following additional groups of surface sites (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>): It is reasonable to assume that the area r occupied by a surface site is proportional to the number of metal (M) atoms in this site, e.g.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">r(M(OH) 2 )/r(M(OH)O(OH)M) ¼ 1/2.</formula><p>Reactions ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">34</ref>) describe dehydroxylation/ hydroxylation in the case of control by the diffusion-assisted reaction of hydroxyl groups. The preexponential factor of the rate constant of this reaction is of the same order of magnitude as the Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. HfO 2 film growth rate (average film mass and thickness increments per cycle) as a function of the process temperature: squares and circles correspond to experimental results <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. Dashed and solid lines correspond to the calculated results by the minimum and extended mechanism. Dashed area corresponds to sensitivity analysis for the extended mechanism. </p><formula xml:id="formula_21">Reactions of H 2 O MðOHÞOMOMCl 3 =s= þ H 2 O ) MðOHÞOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ HCl<label>ð49Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">MðOHÞOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ H 2 O ) MðOHÞOðOHÞM=s= þ MO 2 =b= þ 2HCl<label>ð50Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Cl 3 MOMOMOMCl 3 =s= þ H 2 O ) Cl 3 MOMOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ HCl<label>ð51Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">Cl 3 MOMOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ H 2 O ) Cl 2 ðOHÞMOMOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ HCl<label>ð52Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">Cl 2 ðOHÞMOMOMOMðOHÞCl 2 =s= þ H 2 O ) Cl 2 ðOHÞMOMOMðOHÞ þ 2HCl þ MO 2 =b=<label>ð53Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">Cl 2 ðOHÞMOMOMðOHÞ þ H 2 O ) MðOHÞOðOHÞM=s= þ MO 2 =b= þ 2HCl<label>ð54Þ</label></formula><p>)13.00 0.00 10.00 )13.00 0.00 10.00 pre-exponential factor of the surface diffusion coefficient, $10 À2 cm 2 /s <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. As in the case of reaction ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>), the activation energy of the reaction (32) was considered coverage-depending in accordance with Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>). Reactions ( <ref type="formula">35</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">54</ref>) describe film growth on partially dehydroxylated surfaces. Because there is no information on the kinetic parameters of these reactions, these parameters were estimated or were taken by analogy with reactions ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) of the minimum mechanism.</p><p>The results of simulations of ZrO 2 and HfO 2 film growth rates based on the extended mechanism are shown, respectively, in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> and <ref type="figure">8</ref> in comparison with the results of the minimum mechanism. Since there was some arbitrariness in choosing the rate parameters of the extended mechanism, these results are presented like areas in the figures. These areas correspond to the variation of the pre-exponential factors of reaction ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">54</ref>) by one order of magnitude and the variation of the activation energies of dehydroxylation reactions (28), ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">32</ref>) over the range ±3 kcal/mole. The best agreement with the experimental data was obtained with E 0 ad ¼ E a ð28; 32Þ À E a ð29; 34Þ ¼ 41 and 43 kcal/mol and De ¼ 16 and 20 kcal/mol for HfO 2 and ZrO 2 , respectively, (solid line in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> and <ref type="figure">8</ref>). These values are consistent with the results of thermogravimetric experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and firstprinciples plane-wave DFT calculations <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>Note that the extended mechanism gives lower values of the adsorption energy than the minimum one. As it was mentioned above, the overestima-tion of the adsorption energy in the minimum mechanism is due to neglecting diffusion controlled reactions and of the film growth processes on the partially dehydroxylated sites.</p><p>At T &gt; 200 °C, the film growth rate essentially decreases with increasing temperature. In the framework of the proposed mechanism, this behavior is determined by the decrease in the number density of the available active sites due to the recombination of OH/s/ surface groups. In this case, the formation of a new layer proceeds through precursor reactions ( <ref type="formula">35</ref>)-(48) with OH/s/ groups on a partially dehydroxylated surface. This leads to a change in the Cl:M ratio ðxÞ in the chemisorbed MCl x surface groups from x ¼ 2 to x ¼ 3. This behavior is demonstrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref>, where the experimental and theoretical data on the dependence of x on the process temperature are shown.</p><p>In the low-temperature region T &lt; 150 °C, where experimental points are absent, the results of our simulations (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> and <ref type="figure">8</ref>) predict that the film growth rate decreases with process temperature. It was emphasized above (see Section 3) that this behavior is explained by the stabilization of the adsorption complex at low temperatures.</p><p>The mechanism introduced above describes the growth of an ''ideal'' MO 2 film (no defects or spatial non-uniformities were considered). The real film contains residual chlorine. The concentration of chlorine in the film obviously relates to its concentration on the surface during deposition. In our calculations, the surface chlorine concentra- tion after a water pulse was found to be a very sensitive function of the process temperature and the water pulse duration, which, as was discussed above (see Section 2, Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>)) is in contradiction with the experimental data <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. According to this discussion, this discrepancy can be removed by taking into account the dependence of the chemical activity of surface chlorine on its chemical environment and chlorine diffusion processes, which in principle is outside the scope of formal kinetic modeling. To take into account these effects, we applied the kMC approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Kinetic Monte Carlo modeling of ZrO 2 film growth</head><p>We used a lattice kMC model to explicitly take into account the following effects of the inhomogeneous local chemical environment on the film growth kinetics:</p><p>(1) dependence of the water adsorption energy on the surface hydroxylation degree; (2) effect of steric repulsion between neighboring MCl x /s/ surface groups; (3) dependence of the activation energy of the hydrolysis of M-Cl bonds on the chemical environment of the chlorine atom.</p><p>Like in the formal kinetic scheme above, the first effect allows us to describe the temperature dependence of the surface hydroxylation degree and, hence, the temperature dependence of the film growth rate. The second effect restricts the maximum coverage of the metal oxide surface by metal precursors and, hence, determines the highest possible film growth rate. The third effect is responsible for the enhanced incorporation of chlorine atoms in the growing film and is used here to explain the experimental temperature dependence of the residual chlorine concentration in the as-deposited film.</p><p>The description of film growth within the lattice kMC approach requires detailed information about the structure of the growing film. The structure of ZrO 2 films deposited by the ALD process under consideration was investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. It was found that metastable tetragonal ZrO 2 with the preferred (0 0 1) orientation is the main crystalline phase in thin films 10-50 nm thick deposited at 200-400 °C. Therefore, we used the t-ZrO 2 crystal lattice as a rigid grid of adsorption sites for zirconia film growth in the lattice kMC model and studied film growth along the [0 0 1] direction.</p><p>In this lattice the deposited zirconia atoms from metal precursors occupy their inherent cation Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref>. Surface state of the adsorbed complex -MCl x of the precursor vs. process temperature. Circles and squares correspond to experiments with ZrO 2 from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, respectively; triangles corresponds to HfO 2 experiment <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>; dashed and dashed-dotted lines correspond to the present study modeling for ZrO 2 and HfO 2 , respectively. positions in the crystal lattice. In accordance with experiment <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref> and quantum-chemical calculations <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, the adsorption of water molecules on the t-ZrO 2 (0 0 1) surface results in the formation of two bibridged hydroxyl groups whose oxygen atoms are located close to the oxygen anion sublattice sites previously unoccupied in the crystal lattice. Therefore, in our lattice kMC model, we assumed that the adsorbed oxygen atoms occupy the available anion sites on the surface of tetragonal zirconia. The hydrogen atoms were not considered explicitly, and the chemisorbed hydroxyl groups were considered as single entities. It was also assumed that chlorine atoms occupy oxygen positions in the crystal lattice (substitutional chlorine impurity). This suggestion is based on the fact that the Zr-Cl bond length in the ZrCl 4 precursors r Zr-Cl % 2:35</p><p>A A falls well within the range 2.05-2.45</p><p>A A of the Zr-O bond distances in bulk t-zirconia.</p><p>The set of chemical reactions used in the kMC model includes the chemical adsorption of the ZrCl 4 molecule on one, two, and three surface hydroxyl groups (similar to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>). The effect of the inhomogeneous chemical environment was modeled using the following two rules:</p><p>(a) a cation lattice site is unavailable for the adsorption of a ZrCl x group if at least one of the neighboring anion lattice sites is already occupied by a chlorine atom; (b) a chlorine atom in the film must have at least one Zr vacancy in its nearest neighborhood, because the chlorine ionic radius r ion ðClÞ % 1:84 A A is much larger than the oxygen ionic radius r ion ðOÞ % 1:2 A A.</p><p>Rule (a) states that an adsorbed ZrCl x (x ¼ 1-3) group prevents the chemisorption of ZrCl 4 with the formation of ZrCl x groups on the nearest neighboring sites. This rule results in the maximum surface coverage by ZrCl x groups of 50% for the regular structure on the planar fully hydroxylated surface (staggered adsorption) and about 35% coverage for random adsorption on the surface. The fulfillment of rule (b) leads to the formation of zirconium vacancies in the growing zirconia film together with residual chorine impurities.</p><p>The hydrolysis of Zr-Cl bonds and the reactions of adsorbed ZrCl x groups with neighboring surface hydroxyl groups (ZrCl x /s/ + OH/s/ fi OZrCl xÀ1 /s/ + HCl) are considered irreversible, because the resulting HCl molecules are rapidly carried out from the reactor volume with the inertgas flow. It was also assumed that chlorine atoms can also be removed from the film bulk if there exists a continuous free diffusion path connecting the given chlorine atom to the surface through oxygen vacancies. Here, when determining the free diffusion path, we consider that, in accordance with rule (b), a chlorine atom can occupy an anion sublattice site only if there is at least one cation vacancy in its coordination shell.</p><p>The dissociative adsorption of water proceeds on a surface M-O pair with the formation of two neighboring OH groups on the surface. It was assumed that the energy of the reversible dissociative adsorption of water depends on the chemical environment of the corresponding surface lattice sites</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">E ad ¼ E 0 ad À DE ad Á N OH ;<label>ð55Þ</label></formula><p>where N OH is the total number of the neighboring hydroxyl groups for the two specified surface sites. This relationship plays the same role in the kMC scheme as Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>) in the formal kinetic scheme. The chemical reactions discussed above are sufficient in the case of an ideal film. However, in the case of real films with impurities and structural defects (e.g., lattice vacancies), it is necessary to supplement the set of chemical reactions with the physical processes of diffusion and relaxation (healing of defects). Therefore, we added surface and bulk diffusion processes for zirconium, chlorine, oxygen, and hydrogen atoms; hydroxyl groups; and ZrOH y Cl x /s/ surface species (here, only surface diffusion). Within the rigid lattice model, the diffusion of atoms and groups proceeds only through vacant lattice sites (note the above definition of the free diffusion path for chlorine atoms based on rule (b)). The diffusion of hydrogen atoms proceeds via jumps from one oxygen atom to another. The mobility of a zirconium group bearing a chlorine atom was also limited by rule (b). Unfortunately, information available in the literature on the diffusion coefficients in zir-conia films is very scarce. However, under real experimental conditions (gas pressure and process temperature) the processes of diffusion over vacant lattice sites must be much faster than all gas-surface chemical reactions. In our kMC simulations, this fact was taken into account by setting the rates of all diffusion processes ten times greater than the rates of typical gas-phase reactions.</p><p>In the computational procedure, the kMC solver chooses one chemical reaction at each instant of time based on the rate of the given reaction and the total rate of all possible chemical reactions using the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">p l k ¼ r l k P i P j r i j ;<label>ð56Þ</label></formula><p>where r i j is the jth reaction rate at the ith atom, the first summation in the denominator runs over all atoms in the system, and the second, over all possible reactions at the particular atom. Since the intermediate surface complexes were not considered in the lattice kMC scheme, the reaction rates were calculated based on the data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> within the quasi-equilibrium approach, in which it is assumed that an equilibrium exists between gas reagents and intermediate surface complexes. The time step of kMC integration is determined by the sums in the denominator, and, thus, one and only one chemical reaction is treated at each time step. In this way, we generated about 30000 chemical events for each pulse of an ALD cycle. The initial substrate contained (5 • 5) cells of t-ZrO 2 oriented along the [0 0 1] direction.</p><p>First, we investigated the maximum coverage of the fully hydroxylated zirconia surface with ZrCl 4 . The calculated coverage of the fully hydroxylated (0 0 1) surface of t-ZrO 2 averaged over a set of simulations is about 35%. In film growth simulations, it has been found that the growing film thickness is proportional to the number of ALD cycles, and the maximum film growth rate is about 0.4 ML per ALD cycle. This value is in reasonable agreement with experimental results reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> (about 0.4 ML per ALD cycle) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> (about 0.6 ML per ALD cycle). Moreover, the temperature dependence of the film growth rate is similar to that in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> obtained within the formal kinetic approach: there is a maximum of the film growth rate at low temperatures ($200 °C) and a slow decrease in the film growth rate at higher temperatures. Here, the best fit was obtained for E 0 ad ¼ 42 kcal/mol and DE ad ¼ 2:4 kcal/mol. These values are in adequate agreement with the corresponding values obtained in the formal kinetic simulations. Indeed, with regard to the normalization of DE ad to one OH group in kMC and to one surface site in formal kinetics, De ¼ DE ad N ¼ 14:4 kcal/mol, where N ¼ 6 is the number of the neighboring OH/ s/ groups per one dissociatively adsorbed water molecule.</p><p>Next, we investigated the dependence of the chlorine atom concentration in the growing film on the process conditions. To take into account the effect of the local chemical environment of a surface chlorine atom on its probability of reacting with a water molecule, we used the following dependence of the activation energy of this reaction on the number of the nearest neighboring Zr atoms in the chlorine coordination shell:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E a ¼ E 0 a À DE a Á N Zr ;<label>ð57Þ</label></formula><p>where N Zr is the number of zirconium neighbors. Taking into account this dependence for the reaction probability, we calculated the residual chlorine concentration in the as-deposited zirconia film (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">11</ref>). The results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref> were obtained with E 0 a ¼ 2:5 kcal/mol and DE a ¼ 1:2 kcal/ mol, which corresponds to the best fit to experimental data. Thus the relatively weak dependence of the activation energy on the chemical environment of the chlorine atom can explain the chlorine concentration observed experimentally in the asdeposited film.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">General conclusions and outlook</head><p>An extended kinetic mechanism of the ALD growth of Zr(Hf)O 2 films from Zr(Hf)Cl 4 and water has been developed. This mechanism takes into account the formation of relatively stable intermediate surface complexes, the effects of the local chemical environment on the reaction rate parameters, possible surface reactions (in addition to gas-surface reactions), and diffusion. This mechanism has been implemented using a formal kinetic approach and the kMC method. The rate parameters for the basic chemical reactions have been evaluated using ab initio quantum-chemical calculations and microscopic kinetic theory.</p><p>The results of simulations based on the mechanism developed in this work quantitatively describe the main experimental features of the film growth process. In particular, both the formal kinetic and kMC approaches correctly describe the experimental temperature dependence of the growth rate, which decreases slowly over the temperature range 200 °C &lt; T &lt; 600 °C. This slow decrease in the growth rate is explained within our mechanism on the assumption that the water desorption energy increases with increasing degree of surface dehydroxylation.</p><p>It is also shown that the kMC approach based on the detailed chemical mechanism developed in this work not only reproduces the kinetic behavior but also adequately describes the accumulation of chlorine atoms in the growing film. The main problem in this case is that the incorporation of impurity chlorine atoms in the growing film is mainly determined by their interactions with neighboring metal atoms. In order to describe these interactions correctly, an atomistic model of the growing film capable of describing the local environment of each chlorine atom becomes necessary.</p><p>The results of this work indicate that an integrated multilevel approach to kinetic modeling, which combines first-principle modeling at the atomistic and mesoscale levels with macro-kinetic modeling at the reactor-scale, can provide valuable insights into the understanding of complicated processes like ALD.</p><p>determining the structure of the corresponding loose transition complex and its location in the reaction path. To find the structure of the transition complex and to calculate the rate constants in this case, we used the interpolation version of the variational transition state theory developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>.</p><p>For definiteness consider reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. In the variational transition state theory, the position q # r of transition complex TC ad in the reaction path (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>) corresponds to a maximum of the Helmholtz free energy a # ðq r Þ of the trial transition complex TC ad ðq r Þ considered as a function of the reaction coordinate.</p><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, it is assumed that the dissociating system is a surface complex AB/s/, which can be represented as two fragments (escaping molecule B and surface center A/s/) interacting along the reaction coordinate q r through the Morse potential U ðq r Þ ¼ Df1 À exp½Àaðq r À q re Þg 2 : ðA:1Þ</p><p>Here, D is the classical desorption energy, q re is the equilibrium distance, and a is an adjustable parameter. The classical desorption energy is given by D ¼ E ad þ e z À e z;B À e z;A=s= ; ðA:2Þ where e z ; e z;B , and e z;A=s= are the zero-point vibrational energies of AB/s/, B, and A/s/, respectively. The Helmholtz free energy a # ðq r Þ is defined by the following equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">a # ðq r Þ ¼ a # th ðq r Þ þ U ðq r Þ þ e # z ðq r Þ; a th ðq r Þ ¼ Àk B T ln Q # ðq r Þ;</formula><p>ðA:3Þ</p><p>where Q # ðq r Þ is the partition function and e # z ðq r Þ is the zero-point vibrational energy of the transition complex TC ad ðq r Þ.</p><p>It is assumed that the degrees of freedom of TC ad include s # vibrations that are close to the vibrations of the non-interacting B and A/s/, two surface-restricted rotations corresponding to the ''soft'' rocking vibrations of B in AB/s/, and r B free rotations similar to the rotations of free B as a whole, where r B ¼ 3 if B is nonlinear; 2 if B is linear:</p><p>ðA:4Þ</p><p>For the calculation of e # z ðq r Þ and the free energy of the internal degrees of freedom a # th ðq r Þ, the following interpolation equations are used <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>: e # z ðq r Þ ¼ e z À hx r 2 À e z;roc À e z;B À e z;A=s= Â exp½Àcðq r À q re Þ þ e z;B þ e z;A=s= ; ðA:5Þ where e z;roc is the zero-point energy of the two ''soft'' rocking vibrations mentioned above and x r is the frequency of the normal mode of C/s/ corresponding to the reaction coordinate. Hence,</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">a # th ðq r Þ ¼ ½a þ k B T ln Q ðrÞ 1v À a roc À a B À a A=s= Â exp½Àcðq r À q re Þ À k B T ln Q r;rest ðq r Þ þ a B þ</formula><p>a A=s= : ðA:6Þ Here, Q ðrÞ 1v ¼ 1 1 À exp À hx r k B T ðA:7Þ is the partition function of the normal mode of C/s/ corresponding to the reaction coordinate; a, a A=s= , and a B are the Helmholtz free energies of the internal degrees of freedom of AB/s/, A/s/, and B; a roc is that of the two ''soft'' rocking vibrations mentioned above; and Q r;rest ðq r Þ ¼ k B T B eff ðq r Þ ; ðA:8Þ</p><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">B eff ðq r Þ ¼ 2q r q r À R B h 2 2m B q 2 r ðA:9Þ</formula><p>is the partition function of the two equivalent surface-restricted rotations (m B is the mass of B and R B is its van der Waals radius).</p><p>The parameter c determines the distance at which the free energy of AB/s/ transforms to that of non-interacting B and A/s/. Following the recommendations in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, we used c ¼ 0:75ða=2Þ in actual calculations.</p><p>Given the parameters a and c and the necessary characteristics of AB/s/, A/s/, and B, the maximum Helmholtz free energy of the transition complex a # max ¼ a # ðq # r Þ can be found numerically, and k d can be calculated using the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">k d ¼ k B T 2p h exp À a 6 ¼ max À a k B T : ðA:10Þ</formula><p>The adsorption rate constant k ad is calculated using k d given by Eq. (A.10) and the detailed balancing principle.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2 Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>212</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Reaction steps of MO 2 film growth in the ALD process: (1a) the formation of a chemisorbed MCl 3 group, (1b) the formation of a chemisorbed MCl 2 group, (2a) the hydrolysis of the first M-Cl bond in a chemisorbed MCl 2 group, and (2b) the hydrolysis of the second M-Cl bond in a chemisorbed MCl 2 group.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Temperature dependence of the film growth rate.Squares and circles are experimental thickness and mass increments per ALD cycle in ZrO 2 film growth<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Curves are the hydroxylation degree calculated by Eq. (6) for E ad ¼ 25 kcal/mol (dashed-dotted line), E ad ¼ 35 kcal/mol (dashed line) and 45 kcal/mol (dashed-dotted line).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>HfðOHÞ 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 4b)20.1 5.3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4b)20.3 2.7</figDesc><graphic coords="7,107.72,305.90,322.20,129.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig.7. ZrO 2 film growth rate (average film mass and thickness increments per cycle) as a function of the process temperature: squares and circles correspond to experimental average film thicknesses and mass increments per cycle<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Dashed and solid lines correspond to the calculated results by the minimum and extended mechanism. The dashed area corresponds to sensitivity analysis for the extended mechanism.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,285.44,426.51,207.72,160.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Variation of the film mass increment during one ALD cycle; the solid line corresponds to ZrO 2 ALD experiments [10] (the process temperature is 300 °C, the temperature in the ZrCl 4 effusion cell is 160 °C), and the dashed line corresponds to the theoretical curve.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,43.82,93.11,212.64,178.49" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>sites that describe the variable degree of surface hydroxylation: 50% dehydroxylated site M(OH)O(OH)M/s/ and 75% dehydroxylated site M(OH)OMOMO(OH)M/s/; (2) sites that describe the physical adsorption of a metal precursor on partially dehydroxylated sites: M(OH)O(OH)MMCl 4 /s/, MCl 4 M(OH)-O(OH)MMCl 4 /s/, MCl 4 M(OH)OMOMCl 3 /s/; (3) sites that describe the chemical adsorption of a metal precursor on hydroxylated sites: M(OH)OMOMCl 3 /s/, Cl 3 MOMOMOMCl 4 /s/, Cl 3 MOMOMOMCl 3 /s/; (4) sites that describe the products of water treatment: M(OH)OMOM(OH)Cl 2 /s/, Cl 3 -MOMOMOM(OH)Cl 2 /s/, Cl 2 (OH)MOMO-MOM(OH)Cl 2 /s/, Cl 2 (OH)MOMOM(OH)/s/.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Examples of bridged structures of surface sites.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,138.14,93.11,271.08,136.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Temperature dependence of the residual chlorine concentration in the growing film; triangles are experimental points [10], and diamonds are simulation results.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,282.68,479.13,213.12,147.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Parameters of model gas-surface reactions (without ZPE corrections)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Surface reaction</cell><cell>State, kcal/mol</cell><cell>Reaction</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model reaction</cell><cell>type</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Kinetic scheme and parameters of rates of MO 2 film growth in the framework of the ''minimum'' mechanismReaction k ¼ A Ã T n expðÀE a =RT Þ</figDesc><table><row><cell>ZrO 2 mechanism</cell><cell>HfO 2 mechanism</cell></row></table><note><p>a Values for the extended mechanism.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Extension of the kinetic scheme of the ''minimum'' mechanism Reactionk ¼ A Ã T n expðÀE a =RT Þ</figDesc><table><row><cell>ZrO 2 mechanism</cell><cell>HfO 2 mechanism</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>M. Deminsky et al. / Surface Science 549 (2004) 67-86</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors are thankful to <rs type="person">J. Aarik</rs>, <rs type="person">K. Kukli</rs> and <rs type="person">M. Ritala</rs> for helpful discussions and for providing experimental data before publication. Motorola manager <rs type="person">Dr. W. Johnson</rs> is gracefully acknowledged for his support and encouragement. The work at Kinetic Technologies has been carried out under a contract with <rs type="funder">Motorola DigitalDNA Labs</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Appendix A. Calculation of rate constants of elementary gas-surface reactions Two different situations arise in the calculation of rate constants of reactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. The first situation corresponds to the reactions of type <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> with the reaction path profile shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref> (right-hand side of the potential curve). These reactions are characterized by a pronounced potential barrier. Therefore, quantum-chemical calculations provide all the necessary information on the energy, E f of the corresponding transition complex and its structure, and standard transition state theory can be used to calculate k f and k r for these reactions. For all the reactions under consideration, our quantum-chemical calculations predict that the fragment H-Cl of the transition complex TC f is structurally similar to the product gas molecule. Therefore, by analogy with the loose transition complex TC ad (which will be considered below), it was assumed that the escaping fragment H-Cl performs two surface-restricted rotations in addition to vibrations, whose frequencies were determined in the model from quantum-chemical calculations.</p><p>For all other reactions, the potential barrier is absent and there is no a priori prescription for</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pietrogiacomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Indovina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tuti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>React</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kinet. Catal. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Inaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hirashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kohama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sol-Gel Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1033</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Manchanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Van Dover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Klemens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sorsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Silverman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wilk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aravamudhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microelectron. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">351</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wilk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anthony</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5243</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sneh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Clark-Phelps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Londergan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Winkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">248</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aidla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-A</forename><surname>Kiisler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uustrate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sammelselg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aidla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mandar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uustrate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kukli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schuisky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aidla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mandar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uustrate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sammelselg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cryst. Growth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Siimon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1725</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aidla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mandar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uustrate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sammelselg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1484</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kytokivi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<pubPlace>Finland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Helsinki University of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kytokivi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E.-L</forename><surname>Lakomaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Root</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Osterholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brongersma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2717</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Widjaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Musgrave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">304</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Widjaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Musgrave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1931</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Orlando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pisani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sauet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">482</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13503</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Merle-Mejean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barberis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ben Othmane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nardou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Quintard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Eur. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1579</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cerrato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bordiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barbera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Morreta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Catal. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Thin Film Materials. Deposition and Processing of Thin Films</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nalwa</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ylilammi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nawrocki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Carr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Annen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Froelicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">261</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Riess</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Solid State Ionics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">181</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First-principle investigation of the hydroxylation of zirconia and hafnia surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Iskandarova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Knizhnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rykova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bagaturõyants</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Potapkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Korkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microelectron. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">587</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Brodskii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rykova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bagaturõyants</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Korkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">278</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Becke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5648</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Parr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">785</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gaussian</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Gaussian, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Pittsburgh, PA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rev A.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">284</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ditchfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hehre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pople</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Shalashilin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nikitin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory of Elementary Atomic and Molecular Processes in Gases</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Clarendon, Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory of Unimolecular and Recombination Reactions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Blackwell, Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of Thermophysical Properties of Solid Materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Waterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hirschhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
			<publisher>Pergamon Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fizicheskie Velichiny. Spravochnik (Physical Quantities: A Handbook)</title>
		<editor>I.S. Grigoriev, E.Z. Meilikhov</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Energoatomizdat</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Moscow</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zhdanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Elementary Physicochemical Processes on Solid Surfaces</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Merle-Mejean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barberis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ben Othmane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nardou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Quintard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Eur. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1579</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cerrato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bordiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barbera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Morreta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Quack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Troe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ber. Buns. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Troe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">226</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Troe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6017</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
