<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">High tunability &quot;Ba, Sr…TiO 3 thin films grown on atomic layer deposited TiO 2 and Ta 2 O 5 buffer layers</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2004-11-15">15 November 2004</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Il-Doo</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Harry</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tuller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hyun-Suk</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jin-Seong</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>305-701</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">High tunability &quot;Ba, Sr…TiO 3 thin films grown on atomic layer deposited TiO 2 and Ta 2 O 5 buffer layers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2004-11-15">15 November 2004</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">99C366F10523D94CDCDE710BDA303A31</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1821656</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 6 July 2004; accepted 30 September 2004</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this letter, we report on increased tunability of Ba 0.6 Sr 0.4 TiO 3 (BST) thin films by use of Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 films as buffer layers between BST and Si substrates. Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 buffer layers were grown by atomic layer deposition (ALD) onto Si substrates followed by pulsed laser deposition of Ba 0.6 Sr 0.4 TiO 3 thin films onto the buffer layers. The randomly oriented BST films deposited on TiO 2 / Si substrates exhibited a broader grain size distribution than the (110) textured BST films grown on Ta 2 O 5 / Si substrates. At an applied voltage of 10 V, the BST films grown on Ta 2 O 5 / Si and TiO 2 / Si substrates showed much enhanced tunability values of 53.1% and 72.9%, respectively, as compared to the 20.7% value obtained with BST films grown on MgO single crystal substrates. Successful integration of BST low voltage microwave tunable devices onto Si substrates thus appears possible with the aid of ALD grown Ta 2 O 5 or TiO 2 buffer layers.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The rapid worldwide growth of wireless communications, radar, and digital electronics has been a key driver in stimulating developments in the field of rf/microwave electronics with demands for ever higher frequencies, bandwidths, and data rates. Tunable high frequency devices are key components for the next generation of communications and radar systems. 1 Barium strontium titanate's (BST) capacitive properties can be tuned by more than 50% in metalinsulator-metal structures with low bias levels resulting in similar percentage changes in the frequency of tuned circuits. 2 Currently, BST-based tunable devices are typically fabricated on small area ͑1 ϫ 1 in. 2 ͒ single crystal substrates such as LaAlO 3 and MgO providing good lattice match and low substrate dielectric loss. By replacing bulky hybrid tuned circuits with thin film elements directly integrated onto silicon chips, one reduces size and power consumption and promises improved reliability, reduced cost, and high volume production by use of large diameter Si wafers. 3 However, BST films grown directly onto Si suffer from low tunability due to the formation of low-K SiO 2 thin layers between BST and Si during the requisite high temperature BST deposition process. Furthermore, high microwave losses related to low resistivity Si have served as a barrier against the realization of BST and related device integration with Si microelectronics. To solve these problems, we introduce suitable oxide buffer layers (Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 ) with high dielectric constants between the BST layers and the Si substrate. The buffer layers serve multiple purposes including electrical isolation, templates for high quality BST growth, stress control for crack-free films, and prevention of chemical reactions. <ref type="bibr">4,</ref><ref type="bibr">5</ref> In order to obtain high quality buffer layers, we utilize atomic layer deposition (ALD), which is very suitable for forming very thin, smooth and conformal layers at low deposition temperatures. 6 Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 thin films have been investigated for numerous integrated microelectronic device applications such as high-K materials and gate dielectrics. 7 Results of these studies have shown Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 thin films to possess, in addition to a high dielectric constants, low dielectric loss, leakage currents, and defect densities. However, few reports exist relative to the potential of using such buffer layers for tunable microwave applications. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> In this letter, we report the influence of ALD-grown Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 buffer layers on the tunability and dielectric loss of BST thin films grown onto Si substrates. 50-nm-thick Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 buffer layers were deposited onto Si substrates using penta-dimetylamino tantalum (͓Ta͑NMe 2 ͒ 5 ͔; PDMAT) and water at 250 °C and titanium ethoxide ͓Ti͑OCH 2 CH 3 ͒ 4 ͔ and water at 220 °C, respectively. (100) n-type Si substrates with resistivity of =10 ⍀ cm were etched in 10% HF solution for 1 min to remove the native oxide and treated by ozone to increase nucleation sites. PD-MAT and titanium ethoxide were held at 85 and 90 °C, respectively, to achieve desired vapor pressures. The water was maintained at 20 °C. One cycle consists of injection of PD-MAT or titanium ethoxide, purging with nitrogen, injection of water, and then purging with nitrogen. Each buffer layer was grown by repeating the above-mentioned cycles until the desired thickness was achieved. In order to improve the crystallinity and electrical properties of the TiO 2 / Si and Ta 2 O 5 / Si structures, the buffer layers were annealed at 700 and 800 °C, respectively, in an oxygen atmosphere for 30 min. After annealing the buffer layer, Ba 0.6 Sr 0.4 TiO 3 thin films 500 nm thick were grown onto the Ta 2 O 5 ͑50 nm͒ /Si and TiO 2 ͑50 nm͒ / Si substrates by pulsed laser deposition a)</p><p>Electronic mail: idkim@mit.edu</p><p>APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS VOLUME 85, NUMBER 20 15 NOVEMBER 2004 0003-6951/2004/85(20)/4705/3/$22.00 © 2004 American Institute of Physics 4705</p><p>(PLD). The substrate temperature and oxygen ambient pressure during PLD were 750 °C and 50 mTorr, respectively. Laser ablation was carried out at a laser fluence of 1.5 J / cm 2 and a repetition rate of 5 Hz using a KrF excimer source ͑ = 248 nm͒. A 200 nm Pt electrode was deposited onto the BST film to complete the circuit fabrication. To enhance the adhesion between the BST thin film and the platinum electrode, a thin Ti adhesion layer (25 nm) was deposited prior to Pt deposition. The IDC (interdigital capacitor) structure was designed to have 10 pairs of fingers 50 µm wide and 1000 µm long each spaced 50 µm apart. The crystallinity and the structure of the BST films were determined by x-ray diffractometry (XRD, Rigaku D/max-rc) excited with Cu K␣ radiation. The microstructure and roughness of the BST films was investigated by atomic force microscopy (AFM). The lowfrequency tuning properties of BST films were measured with an HP 4194A impedance analyzer at a frequency of 100 kHz.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the XRD patterns of 500 nm BST films grown on TiO 2 / Si and Ta 2 O 5 / Si substrates, respectively. The BST film on TiO 2 / Si showed typical polycrystalline perovskite BST. In contrast to the film grown on TiO 2 , the BST film deposited on Ta 2 O 5 / Si had highly (110) preferred orientation. X-ray diffraction also showed that the Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 films became single phase crystalline following annealing (not shown).</p><p>The tuning properties of BST films at 100 kHz were investigated by examining interdigital capacitors with configurations Pt/ Ti/ BST/ Ta 2 O 5 / Si and Pt/ Ti/ BST/ TiO 2 / Si. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows the normalized capacitance dependence of the BST thin films grown on Ta 2 O 5 / Si, TiO 2 / Si, and MgO substrates as a function of bias voltage from 0 to 35 V. In general, tunability % is defined as ͓͑⑀ max -⑀ min ͒ / ⑀ max ͔, where ⑀ max and ⑀ min are the maximum and minimum permittivities within the voltage range examined. At an applied voltage of 10 V, the tunability values of BST films grown on Ta 2 O 5 /Si and TiO 2 / Si were 53.1% and 72.9%, respectively. These values are much larger than that of BST films grown on a MgO single crystal substrate (20.7%, at 10 V). BST films grown on MgO single crystal substrates showed highly (100) preferred orientation and reached a tunability of only 41.6% with a much higher applied voltage of 35 V. The measured capacitance of BST grown on TiO 2 /Si,Ta 2 O 5 / Si, and MgO substrates at zero bias voltage was 125.8, 30.8, and 9.95 pF, respectively. In comparison to parallel-plate capacitors, coplanar designs generally require higher control voltages and offer lower tunability, potential disadvantages of the IDC structure. The drive voltage needed to obtain appropriate tunability is very high in the BST/ MgO structure given the low dielectric constant of the MgO single crystal substrate. Improved tunability and, thus, higher frequency tuning agility, has been shown to be possible in this study by incorporating TiO 2 or Ta 2 O 5 buffer layers which increase the overall average dielectric constant and thereby minimize electric field attenuation in coplanar designs as found in the interdigital capacitor structures. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> If we assume that we can ignore the formation of a SiO 2 layer between Si and the buffer layer during the annealing process in the case in which a high-K buffer layer is utilized, then the measured capacitance, C measured can be evaluated from the series connection of the bulk film capacitance, C bulk , and buffer layer capacitance, C buffer :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 C measured = 1 C bulk + 1 C buffer .<label>͑1͒</label></formula><p>Thus, the average dielectric constant ͑⑀ average ͒ can be expressed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d total ⑀ average = d bulk ⑀ bulk + d buffer ⑀ buffer ,<label>͑2͒</label></formula><p>where d total d bulk d buffer are the total film thickness, bulk BST film thickness, and buffer layer thickness, respectively. The increased capacitance of BST films grown on TiO 2 / Si and Ta 2 O 5 / Si compared with BST film grown on MgO substrate can be understood by examination of Eqs.</p><p>(1) and (2).</p><p>In addition, high permittivity buffer layers with low loss tangents can minimize the power loss via the Si substrates. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> The dielectric constant of Ta 2 O 5 films is reported to be 25. In ALD grown TiO 2 layers, the dielectric constant was 100. The FIG. 2. Normalized capacitance of BST films grown on MgO, TiO 2 / Si, and Ta 2 O 5 / Si substrates.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>FIG. 1. X-ray diffraction patterns of BST films grown on (a) TiO 2 / Si and (b) Ta 2 O 5 / Si substrates.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,77.79,52.76,192.00,239.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="4,53.79,52.76,240.00,231.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>advantages of using a TiO 2 layer are twofold; increased tunability of the BST film and minimized power loss via the Si substrate, consistent with Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the surface morphologies of Ta 2 O 5 and TiO 2 films on Si substrates. Ta 2 O 5 on Si exhibited a roughness value of 3.57 nm rms and TiO 2 a value of 5.12 nm. As shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">3(a</ref>) and 3(b), larger grain growth was observed in the TiO 2 as compared to the Ta 2 O 5 film. The Ta 2 O 5 buffer layer showed a uniform matrix of round and dense grains. The change in surface roughness and grain size distribution can affect the nucleation and subsequent grain size of BST thin films. Twodimensional atomic force microscopy images of BST films prepared on Ta 2 O 5 / Si and TiO 2 / Si substrates are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">3(c</ref>) and 3(d). Roughness values were 1.81 nm for BST/ Ta 2 O 5 / Si and 2.28 nm for BST/ TiO 2 / Si. The slightly higher BST film roughness on TiO 2 / Si presumably originated from the greater roughness of the annealed TiO 2 layer as compared with that of the annealed Ta 2 O 5 on Si. The lager grains in BST films grown on TiO 2 / Si are likely the source of the increased tunability.</p><p>For microwave device applications, Si is normally not viewed as being compatible given its high dielectric losses at microwave frequencies. Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the loss tangent of BST films grown on MgO, TiO 2 / Si, and Ta 2 O 5 / Si substrates, respectively. BST films grown on MgO showed, as expected, the lowest loss tangent. The loss tangent of BST grown on TiO 2 / Si and Ta 2 O 5 / Si is high, presumably due to the lossy Si substrate. The figure of merit (FOM), ratio of tunability to dielectric loss, is very important for microwave tunable device applications. At an applied voltage of 5 V, the FOM of BST/ TiO 2 and BST/ Ta 2 O 5 were 5.22 and 1.57, respectively. The BST films grown on TiO 2 and Ta 2 O 5 buffered Si substrates showed relatively lower FOM values as compared to the FOM (11.87) of BST/ MgO due to the lossy Si substrate in the former case. To reduce the loss tangent, one can increase the buffer layer thickness or use a higher resistance substrate. Further studies are under way for the integration of BST microwave devices using GaAs, SiO 2 / Si, and high resistivity Si substrates (more than 10 k⍀ cm). 7 In summary, TiO 2 and Ta 2 O 5 films, as buffer layers for the integration of BST films, were grown onto Si substrates by atomic layer deposition. BST films grown on TiO 2 / Si and Ta 2 O 5 / Si by PLD showed remarkably high tunability at low applied voltage. This work demonstrates the potential feasibility of integrating BST films as microwave interdigital capacitors and/or coplanar waveguide tunable devices by use of thin film buffer layers of TiO 2 and Ta 2 O 5 .</p><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. YongWoo Choi and Dr. Ytshak Avrahami for their helpful discussion during this research work. 1 B. Acikel, T. R. Taylor, P. J. Hansen, J. S. Speck, and R. A. York, IEEE Microw. Wirel. Compon. Lett. 12, 237 (2002).       Mater. Sci. Process. 76, 197 (2003).  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
