<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Intel Corporation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_6JEymXr">
					<orgName type="full">Science Foundation Ireland</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">827A36E59D9A2F5E2216D19C8114BFC5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We have studied an in situ passivation of In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As, based on H 2 S exposure ͑50-350 °C͒ following metal organic vapor phase epitaxy growth, prior to atomic layer deposition of HfO 2 using Hf͓N͑CH 3 ͒ 2 ͔ 4 and H 2 O precursors. X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy revealed the suppression of As oxide formation in air exposed InGaAs surfaces for all H 2 S exposure temperatures. Transmission electron microscopy analysis demonstrates a reduction of the interface oxide between the In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As epitaxial layer and the amorphous HfO 2 resulting from the in situ H 2 S passivation. The capacitance-voltage and current-voltage behavior of Pd/ HfO 2 / In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As/ InP structures demonstrates that the electrical characteristics of samples exposed to 50 °C H 2 S at the end of the metal-organic vapor-phase epitaxy In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As growth are comparable to those obtained using an ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivation. © 2008 American Institute of Physics. ͓DOI: 10.1063/1.2829586͔</p><p>In order to continue complementary metal oxide semiconductor ͑CMOS͒ development beyond the 22 nm node, alternative channel materials in combination with high dielectric constant ͑k͒ gate layers are currently under investigation. One of these approaches is to use high-mobility III-V materials such as InGaAs and GaAs as channel layers. <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> High mobility substrates offer the potential for increased transconductance at reduced voltages, increasing performance at supply voltages ഛ1 V. However, a significant factor which has inhibited the use of such materials is the lack of stable, high quality gate insulators on III-V channels. A gate oxide is required with high dielectric constant and sufficiently low density of interface states to avoid Fermi level pinning at the interface with the III-V substrate. As atomic layer deposition ͑ALD͒ of high-k dielectrics on Si is becoming a reality in manufactured devices, recent research is investigating this approach for use in III-V based devices. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> A number of groups have also investigated surface passivation of the In x Ga 1-x As substrate prior to oxide deposition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> In situ gaseous passivation is preferable to ex situ aqueous techniques which are more likely to introduce contaminants such as C, Na, and heavy metals, as well as increasing InGaAs surface roughness. In addition, both ALD and MOVPE are more attractive techniques than MBE for use in manufacturing technology. In this letter, we evaluate an in situ passivation performed at the end of the MOVPE growth of high indium content lattice matched In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As grown on InP substrates. The technique is based on the exposure of the In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As surface to H 2 S at the end of the growth process, prior to gate dielectric formation. The approach is particularly suited to MOVPE III-V growth as H 2 S is used as a n-type dopant source for InGaAs. The gate oxide employed in this work is ALD grown HfO 2 using the metal organic precursor Hf͓N͑CH 3 ͒ 2 ͔ 4 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As lattice-matched epitaxial layers of thickness 2 m and S doped to 4 ϫ 10 17 / cm 3 , were grown in a MOVPE system immediately following growth of a 0.1 m InP buffer layer ͑S doped, 2 ϫ 10 18 / cm 3 ͒ on n-type InP͑100͒ wafers ͑S doped, ͑1-3͒ ϫ 10 18 / cm 3 ͒. In situ passivation of the InGaAs surface was performed in the MOVPE chamber immediately after growth by flowing H 2 S over the samples at a flow-rate of 0.1 SCCM ͑SCCM denotes cubic centimeter per minute at STP͒, at three different temperatures ͑50, 200, or 350 °C͒, for 90 min in a H 2 carrier gas. Subsequently the wafers were moved to an ex situ ALD reactor involving ϳ90 s ambient exposure. HfO 2 layers ͑ϳ3-ϳ 15 nm͒ were deposited at a temperature of 250 °C by alternating pulses of H 2 O and the HfO 2 precursor Hf͓N͑CH 3 ͒ 2 ͔ 4 , the initial pulse being that of the Hf precursor. MOS structures were completed by vacuum evaporation of ϳ100 nm of Pd using a deposition rate of 2.5 Å / s, and lift-off, to define capacitors of various areas. No Ohmic back contacts to the InP were formed. Ex situ aqueous sulfur ͑S͒ passivation was performed in ambient by dipping InGaAs/ InP samples in ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S diluted to 20% in de-ionized water at ϳ60 °C for 20 min. The Pd/ HfO 2 / In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As/ InP structures examined in this work experienced no annealing following either dielectric deposition or gate metal formation.</p><p>Passivated InGaAs surfaces were studied using x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy ͑XPS͒, following ϳ60 s ambient exposure before loading to the XPS system, to evaluate the effectiveness of the in situ passivation approach in suppressing native oxide regrowth. XPS spectra of a sample passivated using ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S are also included for comparison. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1͑a͒</ref>   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1͑b͒</ref>. This XPS peak is selected to examine the effect of the passivation on suppressing native oxide growth due to the large chemical shift between the As 3d peak and that of the arsenic oxide. In the case of the unpassivated sample, a peak is observed at ϳ45 eV and assigned to As 2 O 3 . In the case of all the in situ passivated samples this peak is not evident, indicating that this approach is effective in preventing As 2 O 3 formation on the InGaAs surface. This is desirable as it has been reported that the unstable As 2 O 3 can react to form elemental As which results in Fermi level pinning. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> The absence of S on the surface of the 50 and 200 °C samples and the fact that As 2 O 3 formation was inhibited on both, indicate that S may not be the primary passivating element in this process.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2͑a͒</ref> compares high frequency capacitance voltage ͑CV͒ curves for the unpassivated device and the various in situ passivation approaches for a nominal ALD HfO 2 thickness of 9 nm. The minimum capacitance ͑C min ͒, at V g = -2 V, is approaching the expected theoretical value of 0.0019 F / m 2 , calculated for these structures assuming inversion at the InGaAs/ HfO 2 interface. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> The device fabricated on the 50 °C in situ passivated surface ͑50 °C device͒ displays the highest maximum capacitance in accumulation ͑C max ͒ and also exhibits the sharpest transition from depletion to accumulation. The inset of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2͑a͒</ref> shows the current density-voltage ͑JV͒ characteristics for unpassivated and in situ passivated MOS structures. All structures exhibit low leakage current density ͑Ͻ5 ϫ 10 -7 A / cm 2 at V fb +1 V͒, demonstrating that these ALD HfO 2 films on InGaAs are highly insulating. It is lowest in the case of the 50 °C device, ϳ5 ϫ 10 -8 A / cm 2 at V fb + 1 V. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2͑b͒</ref> shows multifrequency CV curves measured over the range of 1 kHz-1 MHz for the 50 °C device. The low frequency CV behavior observed in the 1 kHz curve has been reported previously in narrow bandgap materials. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> The inset of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2͑b͒</ref> shows the CV hysteresis curve for the 50 °C device, which has the lowest measured hysteresis, ϳ380 mV around C fb . These levels of frequency dispersion and hysteresis are to be expected as no postdeposition thermal anneal was performed on these MOS structures. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> The fact that the 50 °C passivated device, which XPS showed to have no detectable S signal at the surface, displays the best electrical properties is further evidence that S is not the primary passivating element for the in situ process. It is possible to speculate that hydrogen may be passivating the InGaAs surface. One possibility is low temperature dissociative adsorption of H 2 S to produce H-S and H species which may bond to As at the epitaxial layer surface. This has been observed in previous studies of H 2 S treatment of GaAs͑001͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> In addition, the fact that H species formed on the surface by H 2 S dissociation will be in equilibrium with the H 2 MOVPE carrier gas may assist in allowing H passivation to occur by reducing hydrogen desorption from the surface. The possibility that hydrogen passivation occurs in this process is subject to further investigation.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3͑a͒</ref> shows a bright field transmission electron microscopy ͑TEM͒ micrograph for a 50 °C in situ H 2 S passivated InGaAs device with a 9.4 nm HfO 2 layer and a 0.8 nm thick interfacial layer ͑IL͒ between the HfO 2 and InGaAs. This is less than half the thickness of the IL of 1.9 nm measured by TEM for the unpassivated device ͓Fig. 3͑b͔͒. This indicates that this in situ passivation technique is effective in significantly inhibiting interfacial oxide growth. Considering that the maximum H 2 S flow rate was limited to 0.1 SCCM in this MOVPE process, there is scope for refinement and potential improvement of this in situ passivation technique.</p><p>CV curves for a thickness series of 3, 9.4, and 16.8 nm thick ALD HfO 2 layers on 50 °C in situ passivated InGaAs are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4͑a͒</ref>. The inset plots the JV response for the three thicknesses. As expected, the leakage current density at V fb + 1 V is significantly higher for the 3 nm device, ϳ2 ϫ 10 -6 A / cm 2 , compared to ϳ3 ϫ 10 -8 A / cm 2 and 2 ϫ 10 -8 A / cm 2 for the 9.4 and 16.8 nm devices, respectively. FIG. 2. ͑a͒ High frequency ͑100 kHz͒ capacitance-voltage characteristics and inset leakage current density as a function of gate bias ͑same legend͒, for unpassivated and in situ passivated Pd/ 9 nm͑nominal͒ ALD HfO 2 / InGaAs/ InP MOS devices. ͑b͒ Multiple frequency CV, and inset hysteresis, curves for in situ 50 °C H 2 S passivated InGaAs MOS device. No capacitance correction was made for inductive and resistive elements in the circuit. The average frequency dispersion of the flatband capacitance C fb , is Ͻ3.5% per decade for all devices. The hysteresis measured around C fb at 100 kHz was 460 mV for the unpassivated device, and 380, 585, and 410 mV for the 50, 200, and 350 °C in situ H 2 S passivated devices, respectively.</p><p>For these HfO 2 layers, we estimate a HfO 2 k value of ϳ23. Figure <ref type="figure">4͑b͒</ref> compares the electrical characteristics of a 9.4 nm thick ALD HfO 2 layer ͑0.8 nm IL͒ deposited on In-GaAs passivated in situ by H 2 S flow at 50 °C, and an 11 nm thick ALD HfO 2 layer ͑1.3 nm IL͒ on InGaAs passivated ex situ in aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S. Although a slight V fb shift is apparent, a similar profile is observed in the CV curves of both devices. Both devices have a similar C max in accumulation while the in situ passivated device appears to have slightly higher interface state density. The JV plot in the inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">4͑b͒</ref> shows similar leakage current density at V fb + 1 V with a higher electric breakdown field for the in situ passivated device. This demonstrates that the in situ passivation approach employed in this work can achieve results comparable to those obtained using ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivation.</p><p>In summary, we have studied an in situ passivation of In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As performed using the H 2 S dopant source ͑50-350 °C͒ at the end of MOVPE growth prior to deposition of ALD HfO 2 . XPS analysis revealed the suppression of As oxide growth on in situ passivated InGaAs layers. The MOS device, which experienced a passivation temperature of 50 °C, displays the best electrical characteristics, with TEM indicating a significant reduction in interfacial oxide thickness compared to the unpassivated and ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivated devices. The potential for developing this passivation approach for use in future CMOS applications is demonstrated by the fact that results comparable to those obtained using ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivation can be achieved.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>In situ H 2 S</head><label>2</label><figDesc>passivation of In 0.53 Ga 0.47 As/ InP metal-oxide-semiconductor capacitors with atomic-layer deposited HfO 2 gate dielectric E. O'Connor, R. D. Long, K. Cherkaoui, K. K. Thomas, F. Chalvet, I. M. Povey, M. E. Pemble, and P. K. Hurley a͒ Tyndall National Institute, University College Cork, Lee Maltings, Prospect Row, Cork, Ireland B. Brennan and G. Hughes School of Physics, Dublin City University, Glasnevin, Dublin 9, Ireland S. B. Newcomb Glebe Scientific, Ltd., Newport, County Tipperary, Ireland ͑Received 13 July 2007; accepted 7 December 2007; published online 14 January 2008͒</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>shows a comparison of the S 2s peak for all samples. XPS does detect S on the InGaAs surface for both the 350 °C in situ passivated sample and the ex a͒ Electronic mail: paul.hurley@tyndall.ie. APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS 92, 022902 ͑2008͒ 0003-6951/2008/92͑2͒/022902/3/$23.00 © 2008 American Institute of Physics 92, 022902-1 situ aqueous S passivated sample, but in the case of the 50 and 200 °C in situ passivated samples no S is detected on the surface. XPS spectra of the As 3d core level for the unpassivated and passivated samples are shown in Fig.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. XPS spectra of ͑a͒ the S 2s peak and ͑b͒ the As 3d peak for ͑i͒ unpassivated InGaAs, ͑ii͒ 50 °C, ͑iii͒ 200 °C, ͑iv͒ 350 °C in situ H 2 S passivated InGaAs, and ͑v͒ ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivated InGaAs.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,54.39,52.76,238.80,99.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>The authors thank <rs type="person">Dan O'Connell</rs>, <rs type="affiliation">Tyndall National Institute</rs>, for sample processing. The authors acknowledge useful discussions with <rs type="person">Niti Goel</rs>, <rs type="person">Wilman Tsai</rs>, and <rs type="person">Marko Radosavljevic</rs>, <rs type="funder">Intel Corporation</rs>. The authors would like to acknowledge the following for financial support of this work: <rs type="funder">Science Foundation Ireland</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">͑05/IN/1751͒</rs>; <rs type="institution">Irish Research Council for Science, Engineering, and Technology, Intel Ireland</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_6JEymXr">
					<idno type="grant-number">͑05/IN/1751͒</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Passlack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Medendorp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Braddock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2325" to="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chabal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kortan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sergent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bude</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schulte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garfunkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gustafsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cryst. Growth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">251</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kortan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kopylov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10913" to="11999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ashley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Buckle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Datta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jefferies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H A</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wilding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference on Solid-State and IC Technology</title>
		<meeting>the Seventh International Conference on Solid-State and IC Technology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2253" to="2256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Passlack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Opila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N G</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Moriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kwo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Electron Devices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1997</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wilk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Frei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N G</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sergent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bude</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Electron Device Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wilk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
			<date>263518</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-K</forename><surname>Chiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-B</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242911" to="242006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Goel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Majhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Chui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163517" to="162006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oktyabrsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tokranov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yakimov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koveshnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng., B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shivaprasad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Aparna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">245</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kukli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pilvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sajavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Callegari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lacey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1989</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Goel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Majhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Warusawithana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schlom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dimoulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mavrou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vellianitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Evangelou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Boukos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Houssa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Caymax</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32908" to="032005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dimoulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vellianitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mavrou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Evangelou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223507" to="222005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Weinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date>1163 ͑1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HfO 2 / InGaAs/ InP MOS devices for ͑a͒ in situ 50 °C H 2 S passivated In-GaAs and ͑b͒ unpassivated InGaAs. The actual HfO 2 layer ͓and interfacial layer ͑IL͔͒ thicknesses measured by TEM were 5.2 nm ͑1.9 nm IL͒ unpassivated device</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">TEM micrographs of Pd/ 9 nm͑nominal͒ ALD</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4 nm ͑0.8 nm IL͒ 50 °C device, 13.5 nm ͑0.9 nm IL͒ 200 °C device, 10.8 nm ͑0.9 nm IL͒ 350 °C device, and 11 nm ͑1.3 nm IL͒ ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivated device</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">No significant degradation of the bulk and interface properties is observed after repeated CV measurement of the MOS structures. ͑b͒ CV ͑100 kHz͒ and inset JV ͑same legend͒ characteristics for</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">TEM were 3 nm ͑0.8 nm IL͒, 9.4 nm ͑0.8 nm IL͒, and 16.8 nm ͑0.9 nm IL͒</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>͑a͒ CV ͑100 kHz͒ curves and inset JV ͑same legend͒ for nominal 15 nm thick ALD HfO 2 layers on 50 °C in situ passivated InGaAs. The actual HfO 2 ͑and IL͒ thicknesses from in situ 50 °C H 2 S passivated and ex situ aqueous ͑NH 4 ͒ 2 S passivated devices</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
