<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structural, electrical, and optical properties of transparent gallium oxide thin films grown by plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition </title>
				<funder ref="#_GMAqP3S">
					<orgName type="full">Korea Research Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2005-08">August 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Appl</forename><surname>Phys</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Lett</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structural, electrical, and optical properties of transparent gallium oxide thin films grown by plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition </title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2005-08">August 2005</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DC8ED0EDB76C2FE5634B93A4CA38660B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1980535</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Low temperature SiO x thin film deposited by plasma enhanced atomic layer deposition for thin film encapsulation applications</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural, electrical, and optical properties of transparent gallium oxide thin films grown by plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition</head><p>Gallium oxide ͑Ga 2 O 3 ͒ thin films were deposited on silicon ͑100͒ and sapphire ͑001͒ substrates using the plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition ͑PEALD͒ technique with an alternating supply of reactant source, ͓͑CH 3 ͒ 2 GaNH 2 ͔ 3 , and oxygen plasma. The thin films were annealed at different temperatures ͑500, 700, and 900 °C, respectively͒ in a rapid thermal annealing system for 1 min. It was found that Ga 2 O 3 thin films deposited by PEALD showed excellent step coverage characteristics. X-ray diffraction measurements showed that the as-deposited thin film was amorphous. However, the thin films annealed at temperatures higher than 700 °C showed a ͑400͒ orientation of the monoclinic structure. An atomic force microscope was used to investigate the surface morphologies of the thin films. The thin films showed very smooth surfaces; the roughness of the as-deposited thin film was about 4 Å. With increasing annealing temperature, the thin film became rougher compared with that annealed at lower temperatures. A double-beam spectrophotometer was used to measure the transmittances of the thin films on the sapphire substrates. The thin films showed a very high transmittance ͑nearly 100%͒. The band-gap energies of the thin films were determined by a linear fit of the transmittance spectra and were calculated to be between 5.0 and 5.24 eV. The electrical properties of thin films of Pt/film/Si structure were also investigated. It was found that, with increasing annealing temperature, the insulating characteristics of the Ga 2 O 3 thin films were significantly improved. Spectroscopic ellipsometry was used to derive the refractive indices and the thicknesses of the thin films. The refractive indices of the thin films showed normal dispersion behavior. The refractive indices of the thin films annealed at low temperatures were smaller than those annealed at high temperatures. © 2005 American Institute of Physics. ͓DOI: 10.1063/1.1980535͔</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Gallium oxide ͑Ga 2 O 3 ͒ is a wide-band-gap ͑ϳ5 eV͒ material with good chemical and thermal stabilities. Ga 2 O 3 thin films have been used as luminescent phosphors, hightemperature oxygen sensors, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> and deep-ultraviolet ͑UV͒ transparent oxides. ␤-phase Ga 2 O 3 can be applied in textured dielectric coatings for solar cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The value of the refractive index close to ͱ n GaAs allows the preparation of efficient single-layer antireflection coatings for GaAs. The various device applications require systematic research into Ga 2 O 3 thin films. However, despite their potential optical and optoelectronic applications, the optical and electrical properties of Ga 2 O 3 have not been thoroughly investigated.</p><p>Since the thickness of thin films is scaled down to nanometer scale for industrial technologies, thin-film deposition methods for precisely controlled thickness, composition, conformal step coverage, good uniformity, and high throughput are highly desirable. Atomic layer deposition ͑ALD͒ has been confirmed to be a very successful method in meeting such requirements. Due to the inherent atomic-level control and self-saturation chemistry, films deposited by ALD are highly conformal and uniform. Moreover, a lower deposition temperature is also required because interlayer diffusion could destroy the properties of nano scale devices. The introduction of plasma during deposition in the ALD system makes the low-temperature deposition of high-quality thin films possible. The chemical composition of a thin film deposited by ALD has been proved to be uniform in a multicomponent system. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Furthermore, since plasma introduction into the ALD process, in comparison with conventional ALD film, can enlarge the process window of ALD in the lower temperature direction through the enhancement of the chemical reaction, plasma-enhanced atomic layer deposition ͑PEALD͒ has recently received much attention.</p><p>Several techniques have already been used to prepare Ga 2 O 3 thin films. These methods include sputtering, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> spray pyrolysis, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> pulsed laser deposition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> and electron-beam evaporation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> However, there has been no report of Ga 2 O 3 thin films deposited by PEALD. In this study, high-quality Ga 2 O 3 thin films were prepared using the PEALD process. Thin-film properties including stoichiometrical, microstructural, phase, homogeneity, and uniformity properties as well as electrical and optical properties were investigated systematically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. EXPERIMENT</head><p>Dielectric Ga 2 O 3 thin films were deposited on p-type Si ͑100͒ and sapphire ͑001͒ substrates by PEALD with an alternating supply of ͓͑CH 3 ͒ 2 GaNH 2 ͔ 3 source and O 2 plasma. The PEALD system used in this study consists of a warm-a͒ FAX: ϩ82-51-890-2113; electronic mail: fkshancn@yahoo.com b͒ Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; electronic mail: leewj@deu.ac.kr wall reactor, a gas-switching system, pumping systems, an rf-generating system, and an injector ͑manufactured by Genitech Co. Ltd, Korea͒. The plasma was generated to activate oxygen gas during the O 2 gas pulse, and the rf plasma power was 60 W. The deposition temperature was maintained at a substrate temperature of 200 °C and the pressure inside the chamber was maintained at 3.0 Torr.</p><p>During the thin-film deposition, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>, one deposition cycle consisted of four pulses in sequence: ͓͑CH 3 ͒ 2 GaNH 2 ͔ 3 vapor pulse with 100-standard cubic centimeter per minute ͑SCCM͒ Ar carrier gas for 0.1 s, an Ar purge gas pulse for 2 s, an O 2 plasma gas pulse for 1 s, and an Ar purge gas pulse for 0.4 s. These four pulses were defined as one deposition cycle. A schematic diagram of the deposition process is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. During deposition, this cycle was repeated until the desired thickness was obtained. In this experiment, a Ga 2 O 3 thin film was deposited in 1000 cycles on Si ͑100͒ and sapphire ͑001͒ substrates by PEALD. After deposition, the as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin films were annealed in a rapid thermal annealing ͑RTA͒ system in ambient oxygen gas for 1 min. The annealing temperatures were 500, 700, and 900 °C, respectively.</p><p>The coverage properties and surface morphologies of the films-were investigated by field-emission scanning electron microscopy ͑FE-SEM, HITACHI S-4200, Hitachi Co.͒ and atomic force microscopy ͑AFM, SPA-400, Seiko Instru-ments͒, respectively. The scanning area in AFM measurements was 500ϫ 500 nm 2 . The composition of the thin film was investigated by Auger electron spectroscopy ͑AES, MI-CROLAB 350, VG Scientific Co.͒. An x-ray diffractometer ͑D/MAX 2100H, Rigaku, Japan, 40 kV, 30 mA͒ was used to investigate the structural properties of the thin films.</p><p>To investigate the electrical properties of the metal-filmsubstrate ͑MFS͒ structures, the Pt top electrodes were prepared by dc magnetron sputtering and then patterned using lift-off lithography. The measured capacitor size was 100 ϫ 100 m 2 . The leakage current characteristics and dielectric constants were measured using an HP 4145B semiconductor parameter analyzer and an HP 4275A LCR meter at the frequency of 100 kHz, respectively.</p><p>To measure the transmittances, the Ga 2 O 3 thin films were deposited on a sapphire substrate. The optical transmittances at the normal incident angle were measured with a double-beam spectrophotometer ͑Cary-5, Varian, Australia͒ in the UV-visible range ͑200-700 nm͒. Spectroscopic ellipsometry ͑SE͒ measurements were carried out to obtain the refractive indices and the thicknesses of the thin films. The system used in this study was variable-angle phasemodulated SE ͑UNISEL, Jobin-Yvon͒. It consisted of a 300 -W Xe arc lamp as the light source, a dual-grating scanning monochromator ͑250-1700 nm͒ coupled to a dual photodetector ͓photomultiplier tube ͑PMT͒ and InGaAs͔, and a highprecision automated goniometer. The average bandwidth of the monochromator was 2 nm. An optically autocollimating device was used to confirm reproducible sample alignments. The measurements were carried out at an incident angle of 65°in the spectral range of 1.5-4.0 eV with a 0.2-eV step. The incident angles of 70°and 75°were also used for confirmation. A small beam spot ͑Ͻ1 mm͒ was used, and the azimuthal beam direction in the plane of each sample was carefully selected to minimize the depolarizing effect from the possible film thickness gradient. All of the measurements were performed at room temperature in ambient.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Structural properties</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Coverage property of PEALD</head><p>Good step coverage is of major importance in device fabrication. When the thickness of a thin film is decreased to nanometer scale, poor step coverage can lead to structures containing voids. Voids are generally unacceptable, since they can be opened during etching. The best way to avoid such problems is to use a deposition method that can produce a step coverage as high as possible. The step coverage property of PEALD was studied by depositing Ga 2 O 3 on a patterned SiO 2 / Si substrate.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows a cross-sectional FE-SEM image of the as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film on the patterned SiO 2 / Si substrate using PEALD. The film morphology is completely continuous and the film coverage is conformal around the sidewall and bottom of the patterned structure. The step coverage of Ga 2 O 3 films produced by PEALD is excellent above 90%. As can be seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the PEALD process has great potential for step coverage and conformal coating procedures, which are often required in ultralarge-scale-integrity ͑ULSI͒ device manufacturing due to the nature of the re- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Depth profile</head><p>The AES depth profiles presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> were obtained with a sputtering rate of ϳ0.2 Å / s for the asdeposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film. The profiles show the distribution of gallium, oxygen, silicon, and carbon with depth for the thin film. This result demonstrates that, within the limits of Auger spectroscopy, the Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited by PEALD is of stoichiometric and excellent depth homogeneity. No impurities, including carbon, which is thought to be the dominant impurity in Ga 2 O 3 thin film, could be detected by Auger analysis. According to the literature, Ga 2 O 3 has a band-gap energy of about 5 eV. Its semiconducting or insulating nature in this material is mainly due to the stoichiometry between gallium and oxygen. Ga 2 O 3 exhibits an n-type semiconductor property in the high-temperature range over 600 °C due to the deficiency of oxygen. Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited by PEALD is insulating due to its stoichiometric characteristics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Crystal structure</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the x-ray-diffraction ͑XRD͒ patterns of the as-deposited and annealed Ga 2 O 3 thin films ͑500, 700, and 900 °C, respectively͒ on Si substrates. It was found that the annealing temperature played an important role in determining the crystal structure of Ga 2 O 3 thin films. The asdeposited and the 500 °C-annealed films were amorphous. Except for the high Si peak, no Ga 2 O 3 peak was observed in either film. However, with increasing annealing temperature up to 700 °C, the structure of the film changed to ␤-phase Ga 2 O 3 with a preferred orientation of ͑400͒. The intensity of the ͑400͒ orientation increased with increasing annealing temperature. The thin film annealed at 900 °C showed more orientations of ͑002͒ and/or ͑2 ¯02͒. These orientations also belonged to monoclinic ␤-phase Ga 2 O 3 . There was no observable secondary phase in the XRD patterns of the thin films.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Surface morphology</head><p>The surface morphologies of the thin films were measured using a scanning probe microscope ͑SPA-400͒ in the AFM mode. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> shows the AFM images of the asdeposited thin film and of the annealed ones. It was found that the surfaces of the thin films deposited by PEALD were absolutely smooth. With increasing annealing temperature, the grain size became larger; the surface roughness showed only a small change. The surface roughness of the thin film annealed at 500 °C was smaller than that of the as-deposited one. The values of the root-mean-square ͑rms͒ of the asdeposited thin film and of the thin films annealed at 500, 700, and 900 °C were 4.6, 4.1, 5.1, and 4.6 Å, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Electrical properties</head><p>To investigate the electrical properties of the Ga 2 O 3 thin films, Pt top electrodes patterned with lift-off lithography processes were deposited. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows the leakage current-voltage ͑I-V͒ characteristics at various annealing temperatures for the Ga 2 O 3 thin films deposited on Si substrates. As can be seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, the leakage current of the Ga 2 O 3 thin films annealed at low temperatures were leaky, but a 1-min annealing in O 2 ambient gas at 700 or 900 °C resulted in a dramatic improvement. The leakage current densities for the thin film annealed at 700 °C were approximately 1 ϫ 10 -7 A/cm 2 and were maintained up to an applied field of about 1000 kV/ cm. They then increased slowly above 1 MV/ cm. For the thin film annealed at 900 °C, the leakage current densities of 1 ϫ 10 -7 A/cm 2 were maintained up to an applied field of about 1.5 MV/ cm. These good insulating properties might have resulted from an improved film quality after RTA annealing.</p><p>The dielectric response at a frequency of 100 kHz was measured by applying a small signal of 10-mV amplitude. After the thicknesses of the thin films were determined by SE measurements ͑listed in Table I͒, the dielectric constants of the Pt/film/Si structure at different annealing temperatures were calculated and are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. It was found that, with increasing annealing temperature, the dielectric constant of the thin film decreased from 13 to 9. FIG. 4. XRD patterns of as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film and of those annealed at various RTA temperatures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Optical properties</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Transmittance</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> shows the transmittances of the Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited at 200 °C and those of the ones annealed at different temperatures. All of the thin films show a nearly 100% optical transmission in the pertinent wavelength. This is very important for applications such as antireflection coatings and dielectric coatings for solar cells.</p><p>Ga 2 O 3 is a material with a direct band gap. The absorption coefficient of the direct band-gap material is 10</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">␣͑h͒ ϰ ͑h -E g ͒ 1/2 , ͑1͒</formula><p>according to I = AI 0 e -␣d , the absorption coefficient ␣ ϰ -ln T.</p><p>As an example, shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">9</ref>, of the as-deposited thin film, we made a plot of the relative absorption coefficient ͓␣͑h͔͒ 2 against the photon energy h. A sharp absorption edge is clearly observed. The sharp absorption edge can be accurately determined for a high-quality thin film by a linear fit. The optical band-gap energies determined from the obtained transmission spectra are shown in the inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. It was found that the band-gap energy increased from 5.00 to 5.24 eV with increasing annealing temperature in the temperature range studied. The band-gap energy of the Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited by PEALD was higher than that deposited by sputtering, pulsed laser deposition, or electronbeam evaporation methods. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> The reported values of the band gap of Ga 2 O 3 lie in the range from 4.23 to 4.99 eV for thin films, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and from 4.7 to 5.1 eV for single crystals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> The increase of band-gap energy with increasing annealing temperature is consistent with the improvement of the film quality ͑as can be seen from the XRD result͒.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Refractive indices</head><p>SE was performed to derive the refractive index and the thickness of the thin film. In the SE measurements, two parameters ⌿ and ⌬ were measured as functions of wavelength ͑or photon energy͒ for a given sample. These two parameters were related to the optical and structural properties of the sample through the following expression:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">= R p /R s = tan ⌿ exp i⌬, ͑2͒</formula><p>where R p and R s are the complex reflection coefficients for the light polarized parallel ͑p͒, respectively, and perpendicular ͑s͒ to the plane of incidence. Note that both R p and R s contain information on the optical and structural properties of the sample. The procedure of modeling and fitting to determine the optical constants of the samples is based on the procedure by FIG. 6. ͑Color online͒ Leakage current curves of the Pt/ Ga 2 O 3 / Si structured thin films.</p><p>TABLE I. Thicknesses of Ga 2 O 3 thin films on Si substrates deposited by PEALD. Sample ͑°C͒ 200 500 700 900 Thickness ͑Å͒ 709.3 679.9 647.2 666.0</p><p>Kim and Vedam. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> The dispersion behavior of the dielectric constant can be expressed by a Lorentz dispersion relation,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">⑀͑h͒ = ⑀ 1ϱ + ͚ k A k E k 2 -͑h͒ 2 -iB k h , ͑3͒</formula><p>for the kth oscillator, where A k is the amplitude, E k is the center energy, B k is the broadending of each oscillator, h is the photon energy in eV, and ⑀ 1ϱ is an additional offset term defined in the model.</p><p>To obtain the refractive index, the dielectric function ⑀ is related to the complex index of refraction n + ik by the relationship,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">⑀ = ⑀ 1 + i⑀ 2 = ͑n + ik͒ 2 , ͑4͒</formula><p>where ⑀ 1 and ⑀ 2 are the real and imaginary parts. Note that ⑀ 2 equals the power absorbed per unit volume. We can obtain the values for n and k according to the values of ⑀ 1 and ⑀ 2 .</p><p>The relationships are</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">n͑͒ = ͱ 1 2 ͓͑⑀ 1 2 + ⑀ 2 2 ͒ 1/2 + ⑀ 1 ͔, ͑5͒ k͑͒ = ͱ 1 2 ͓͑⑀ 1 2 + ⑀ 2 2 ͒ 1/2 -⑀ 1 ͔. ͑6͒</formula><p>In the Lorentz model, the thin films correspond to a collection of oscillators grouped together in the UV, visible, and IR ranges. The Lorentz oscillator is useful to illustrate the qualitative aspects of insulators, semiconductors, and con-ductors by observing where the absorption peak lies in the spectral range. The Lorentz dispersion relation is Kramers-Kronig consistent.</p><p>For clearance, the measured quantities of ⌿ and ⌬ at different incident angles ͑65°, 70°, and 75°͒ for the Ga FIG. 8. ͑Color online͒ Transmission spectra of as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film and of those annealed at various RTA temperatures. The inset is the bandgap energies of the thin films. FIG. 10. ͑Color online͒ The raw SE data ͑experimental͒ and the fit ͑simulated by Lorentz model͒ for ⌬ and ⌿ are shown as a function of photon energy for Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited by PEALD at 200 °C and annealed at the temperature of 500 °C.</p><p>nealed at temperatures higher than 700 °C were nearly the same and higher than those annealed at low temperatures. The refractive index n was 1.89 at = 6328 Å. The curves obtained using the ellipsometric data were between 1.5 and 4.0 eV. Ortiz et al. reported that the refractive index of Ga 2 O 3 thin film deposited by periodic lattice-distortion ͑PLD͒ is about 1.85 at = 6328 Å. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> Passalack et al. reported a refractive index of 1.84-1.88 at 9800-Å wavelength. This difference varies with the method of preparing thin films. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> The phase transition in the thin film might be one of the reasons why the refractive index increases with increasing annealing temperature. As can be seen from the XRD results, the as-deposited and 500 °C annealed Ga 2 O 3 thin films were amorphous; the thin films annealed at high temperatures were ␤-phase Ga 2 O 3 . With increasing annealing temperature, the thin film became ␤ phase and the refractive index increased.</p><p>During the fitting processes, the film thicknesses were also obtained as by-products and are listed in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. It can be seen that the thickness of the thin film depends on the annealing temperature. With increasing annealing temperature, the thickness of the thin film decreased, owing to the densification of the thin film after annealing. The densification of such film might be the other reason for the increase of the refractive index. The low-density thin film had lower refractive index. The air trapped in a film's pores ͑lower refractive index compared with that of the thin film͒ will effectively decrease the refractive index.</p><p>However, the thickness of the thin film annealed at 900 °C increased compared with that of the thin film annealed at 700 °C. This increasing of thickness at 900 °C was thought to arise from the oxidation of the interface between the thin film and the substrate. The thickness of the thin film was calculated to be approximately 67 nm. This result coincides with that estimated by SEM, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>High-quality Ga 2 O 3 thin films were deposited on silicon ͑100͒ and sapphire ͑001͒ substrates using PEALD technique with an alternating supply of reactant source, ͓͑CH 3 ͒ 2 GaNH 2 ͔ 3 , and oxygen plasma. Films deposited by PEALD showed excellent step coverage characteristics.</p><p>XRD measurements indicated that the as-deposited and lowtemperature-annealed Ga 2 O 3 thin films were amorphous. However, the thin film annealed at temperatures higher than 700 °C showed a ͑400͒ orientation of monoclinic structure ͑ ␤-phase Ga 2 O 3 ͒. The surface morphology investigated by AFM showed a very smooth surface. The roughness of the as-deposited thin film was about 4 Å. The electrical properties of the thin films of the Pt/ film/ Si structure were also investigated. It was found that, with increasing annealing temperature, the insulating characteristics of Ga 2 O 3 thin films were significantly improved; the dielectric constant decreased from 13 to 9.</p><p>The thin films deposited on sapphire substrates showed very high transmittances ͑nearly 100%͒. The band-gap energies of the thin films were determined by a linear fit of the transmittance spectra and were calculated to be approximately 5.00-5.24 eV. Through the fitting of ellipsometry angles ͑⌿ and ⌬͒, the optical constants and the thicknesses of the thin films were calculated. The refractive indices of the thin films showed normal dispersion behavior. The refractive indices of the thin films annealed at low temperatures were smaller than those annealed at higher temperatures.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>F</head><figDesc>. K. Shan, a͒ G. X. Liu, W. J. Lee, b͒ G. H. Lee, I. S. Kim, and B. C. Shin Electronic Ceramics Center, DongEui University, Busan 614-714, South Korea ͑Received 1 March 2005; accepted 27 May 2005; published online 20 July 2005͒</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG.1. ͑Color online͒ Schematic diagram of thin film deposition. One deposition cycle consisted of four pulses: ͓͑CH 3 ͒ 2 GaNH 2 ͔ 3 vapor pulse with 100-SCCM Ar carrier gas for 0.1 s, an Ar purge gas pulse for 2 s, an O 2 plasma gas pulse for 1 s, and an Ar purge gas pulse for 0.4 s. The period cycle was repeated until the desired thickness was obtained.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,88.80,49.76,168.00,112.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIG. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIG.3. ͑Color online͒ Auger depth profile of as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film. The analysis was done by using 4-keV Ar ions. The nominal etch rate was 0.2 Å / s. The film is homogeneous and stoichiometric.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,88.80,49.77,168.00,120.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIG. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>FIG.5. ͑Color online͒ AFM images of as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film ͑a͒ and of those annealed at 500 °C ͑b͒, 700 °C ͑c͒, and 900 °C ͑d͒ in RTA system for 1 min. The RMS values were 4.6, 4.1, 5.1, and 4.6 Å for as-deposited thin film and the thin films annealed at 500, 700, and 900 °C, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,107.40,49.76,130.80,463.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>FIG. 7. ͑Color online͒ Dielectric constants of the as-deposited Ga 2 O 3 thin film and of those annealed at various RTA temperatures.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,88.80,49.77,168.00,133.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIG. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>FIG. 9. ͑Color online͒ Calculation method of band-gap energy by the linear fit of the relative absorption edge.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,352.21,49.77,168.00,129.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This work was supported by a <rs type="funder">Korea Research Foundation</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">͑KRF-2004-042-D00095͒</rs>. The authors would like to thank <rs type="person">Dr. C. R. Cho ͑KBSI</rs>, <rs type="person">Busan Branch</rs>, <rs type="person">South Korea͒</rs> for profile measurements, <rs type="person">Professor S. G. Yoon</rs> ͑Department of <rs type="affiliation">Materials Science and Engineering, Chungnam National University, Daejeon, South Korea͒</rs> for the electrical property measurements, and <rs type="person">Professor S. Y. Kim</rs> ͑Department of <rs type="affiliation">Molecular Science and Technology, Ajou University, Suwon, South Korea͒</rs> for the ellipsometry measurements, respectively.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_GMAqP3S">
					<idno type="grant-number">͑KRF-2004-042-D00095͒</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hanrieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Meixner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1990</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hamberf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Granqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chopra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Major</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Pandya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1983</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. Appl. Phys.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Appl. Phys., Part</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2001</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Chae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Integr. Ferroelectr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rebien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Henrion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mannaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1987</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Urbiola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2001</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Orita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ohta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2000</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Al-Kuhaili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M A</forename><surname>Durrani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Khawaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Pankove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Optical Processes in Semiconductors ͑Dover</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Passalack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Moriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N G</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1995</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cocivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kershaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dwight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Res. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1990</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hosono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Waseda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kawazoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1997</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tippins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A316 ͑1965͒</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thin Solid Films 166, 325 ͑1988͒. FIG. 11. ͑Color online͒ Extracted refractive indices of Ga 2 O 3 thin films deposited by PEALD at 200 °C and annealed at various RTA temperatures by Lorentz simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vedam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
