<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Plasma-assisted and thermal atomic layer deposition of electrochemically active Li 2 CO 3 †</title>
				<funder ref="#_Q8nTd3T">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-08-24">24 August 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hornsveld</surname></persName>
							<email>n.hornsveld@tue.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Put</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vereecken</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Creatore</surname></persName>
							<email>m.creatore@tue.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kapeldreef 75</addrLine>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<settlement>Imec Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Microbial and Molecular Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Plasma-assisted and thermal atomic layer deposition of electrochemically active Li 2 CO 3 †</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-08-24">24 August 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8BB0BE6675BC132B79AF8DF891BD2FD5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1039/c7ra07722j</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 13th July 2017 Accepted 10th August 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Thin-film lithium carbonate (Li 2 CO 3 ) has applications in various electrochemical devices, like Li-ion batteries, gas sensors and fuel cells. ALD of Li 2 CO 3 is of interest for these applications as it allows for uniform and conformal coating of high-aspect ratio structures and particles with very precise thickness control. However, there are few studies that focus on its fabrication and characterization. In this work, plasma-assisted and thermal ALD were adopted to grow ultra-thin, conformal Li 2 CO 3 films between 50 and 300 C using lithium tert-butoxide as a precursor and O 2 plasma or H 2 O/CO 2 as co-reactants. More specifically, we focus on the plasma-assisted process by film growth, stability and conductivity studies and emphasize the differences from its more extensively adopted thermal counterpart. Plasma-assisted ALD allows for higher growth per cycle values (0.82 vs. 0.60 Å), lower substrate temperatures and shorter cycle times. The stoichiometry of the films, ranging from Li 2 CO 3 to Li 2 O, can be controlled by substrate temperature and O 2 plasma exposure time. The ionic conductivity for both plasma-assisted and thermal ALD is measured for the first time and is in the order of 10 À10 S cm À1 after normalizing to the different effective surface areas. The Li-ion conductivities found here are in line with literature values predicted by simulation studies.</p><p>In the present work we focus on the ALD characterization of Li 2 CO 3 . More specically, we focus on the plasma-assisted ALD process of Li 2 CO 3 by (in situ) growth studies and emphasize the differences from its more extensively adopted thermal</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Lithium carbonate is considered a potential electrode passivating lm in Li-ion batteries <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> and electrolyte material or sensing layer in electrochemical devices like fuel cells or chemical sensors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> This is attributed to its purely ionically conductive behavior and good electrochemical stability. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> In addition, it is widely used as building block for the fabrication of electrodes and electrolytes or as an additive to improve electrode performance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> Despite its widespread usage, there are only few studies in the literature focusing on its characterization.</p><p>With the trend of manufacturing devices that have smaller size, weight and lower power consumption, thin lm fabrication techniques are becoming preferable. This is especially applicable in the eld of Li-ion batteries, where thin-lm 3D battery architectures are currently being investigated. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> Nanostructured energy storage systems have demonstrated a substantial increase in power and energy density. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> Key to nanostructured energy storage systems is thin lms processing of battery active and passive materials compatible with complex battery design. Conventional deposition techniques, such as physical vapor deposition (PVD) and plasma-enhanced chemical vapor deposition (PE-CVD), do not generally lead to conformal thin layers on high aspect ratio structures. To enable fast charging thin-lm batteries, conformality and uniform material composition in extreme aspect ratios are required. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> Therefore, novel deposition techniques leading to enhanced control in thin lm properties and conformality are being presently introduced in the eld of Liion batteries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> Atomic layer deposition (ALD), which is based on sequential and self-limiting half-reactions between precursors (co-reactants) and surface, has emerged as a powerful tool since it shows potential towards exceptional conformality on high-aspect ratio structures, thickness control at sub-nanometer level, and tunable lm properties. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> Promising applications of ALD for Li-ion batteries include (surface modication of) particle-based electrodes, 3D-structured electrodes, and 3D all-solid-state microbatteries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> Due to the excellent conformality and thickness control of ALD, is suggested that ALD of lithium carbonate (Li 2 CO 3 ) is especially benecial when it is employed as electrode passivating lm or as additive to improve electrode performance.</p><p>counterpart. This is expected to be generally helpful to assess the opportunities of ALD for Li-ion materials. With plasmaassisted ALD a high reactivity is delivered to the deposition surface by the plasma species and therefore less thermal budget is required at the substrate to drive the ALD surface chemistry than for thermal ALD. The application of plasmas in combination with ALD generally leads to a wider range in substrate temperature and processing conditions and thus enables a larger variety of material properties. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> The process details of ALD Li 2 CO 3 as collected from literature are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Although the plasma-assisted ALD process for Li 2 CO 3 has been already reported in literature, the understanding of the ALD lm growth (primarily in terms of developed chemistry during and aer deposition) is so far insufficient. In addition, the effect of the process parameters on the layer properties was not reported. To the best of our knowledge we provide the rst proper conductivity measurement of thin lm Li 2 CO 3 .</p><p>Moreover, Li 2 CO 3 ALD represents an attractive model process for incorporating Li into multicomponent (ternary) ALD materials, since it is a highly stable compound with respect to process stability and ease of postdeposition analysis of the lms. Li 2 O and LiOH oen develop simultaneously during processing due to the reversible reaction with H 2 O and CO 2 and are being deposited by ALD as well. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> These materials are also widely used as building block for the fabrication of various other Li-ion battery active materials. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental</head><p>All depositions presented in this work were carried out using the thermal and remote plasma ALD reactor FlexAL (Oxford Instruments). The reactor consists of a rotary and turbo molecular pump such that it can reach a base pressure of &lt;10 À6 Torr by overnight pumping. The pump unit as well as the inductively coupled plasma (ICP) source are connected to the deposition chamber trough gate valves.</p><p>The ALD processes developed in this work are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. For thermal ALD (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>), the cycle consists of the exposure of the substrate to LiO t Bu (97%, Sigma Aldrich) lithium precursor, H 2 O gas and CO 2 gas respectively, alternated by argon purges. The plasma-assisted ALD process (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>) consists of a combination of the substrate exposure to the same lithium precursor and to an O 2 -fed plasma with a plasma power of 100 W, alternated by argon purging steps. To ensure the gas ow and pressure have stabilized, the reactor was lled with oxygen prior to switching on the plasma source. Air exposure of the fabricated layers was minimized by transporting the samples in an evacuated transport tube.</p><p>The LiO t Bu precursor was bubbled from the precursor pod with Ar at a reactor pressure of 20 mTorr and the precursor and precursor supply line were heated to 140 C and 150 C respectively to avoid precursor condensation. The reactor pressure during the O 2 plasma generation was 13 mTorr. The process table was heated to 50-300 C, since it is reported that precursor decomposition takes place from 350 C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> The wafers were placed on an aluminum substrate holder. The reactor wall is maintained at a temperature of 120 C (which is the maximum wall temperature), except for the deposition at 50 or 100 C, where the reactor wall is kept at 50 or 100 C, respectively.</p><p>As substrate, 60 nm titanium nitride (TiN) sputtered on silicon was used (Endura PVD). TiN is a barrier for Li-ion diffusion, and also functions as current collector for electrochemical testing of the layers. The lm thickness and dielectric function were monitored in situ by spectroscopic ellipsometry (SE) with a J.A. Woollam, Inc. M2000U (0.75-5.0 eV) tool. The dielectric function of Li 2 CO 3 was parameterized using a mathematical description in the form of B-splines, since this method requires no prior knowledge about the dielectric function of the deposited lms. Thickness values were conrmed by high resolution SEM (Zeiss Sigma) operated at 2 kV acceleration voltage.</p><p>The entire chemical composition of the samples has been characterized with ion beam analysis methods by Detect99. The hydrogen proles were determined by Elastic Recoil Detection (ERD) using a 1.9 MeV He + beam impinging on the sample under 15 glancing incidence, and 30 recoil angle. All other elements could be determined in a single run by Elastic Backscattering Spectrometry (EBS) with 2.8 MeV protons at perpendicular incidence. This technique is similar to Rutherford Backscattering Spectrometry (RBS) but has the advantage that the cross sections for light elements is enhanced by the use of high energy protons as projectiles instead of He. Spectra have been registered at 170 and 150 scattering angle. EBS was in this case necessary for the determination of the Li and C contents, for which the sensitivity of RBS is rather poor. Finally, the O, N and Ti contents have been conrmed by channeling RBS using 1900 keV He ions in the same conguration as for the EBS measurements.</p><p>X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) spectra were recorded by a Thermo Scientic K-alpha+ system using monochromatic Al Ka X-rays. The spot size of the beam was 400 mm and the base pressure of the system was 10 À8 mbar. The depth prole was obtained by an Ar ion gun of 500 eV during 5 s for each sputter step. The crystal structure of the Li 2 CO 3 layers was determined using a Philips X'Pert MPD diffractometer equipped with a Cu Ka source (1.54 Å radiation). The morphology of the deposited layers was investigated by the SEM which was described before.</p><p>For electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) testing an Autolab (Metrohm) potentiostat with a frequency-response analyzer module (frequency range from 0.01 Hz to 1 MHz) was used, operated by Nova soware (Metrohm Autolab). A </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ALD process characterization</head><p>A deposition temperature of 150 C was adopted to investigate the saturation behavior of the surface reactions during the subcycles of both thermal and plasma ALD Li 2 CO 3 . Film thickness was monitored every 10 cycles by in situ SE measurements while changing precursor or co-reactant dose times. Saturation curves for the thermal ALD process of Li 2 CO 3 are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>. A LiO t Bu dose of 6 s, a water dose of 50 ms and a CO 2 dose of 2 s were chosen as standard conditions for thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 . Without H 2 O dosing no lm growth occurred and without CO 2 , LiOH was formed. Due to a slower response speed of the CO 2 valve, dosing of 0.5 s or less did not deliver any CO 2 in the chamber (no pressure increase was observed). Purge steps aer LiO t Bu and CO 2 dose of 2 s are sufficient to remove the reaction products and unreacted species from the processing chamber, although 5 s purge was necessary for H 2 O. A growth per cycle of 0.60 Å was found for the thermal ALD process.</p><p>The saturation behavior of the surface reactions during the two half cycles of the plasma-assisted ALD process, i.e. the exposure to the lithium precursor and O 2 plasma, is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>: self-limiting growth was veried for both the precursor and the plasma step. For both half-cycles purge steps of 2 s are sufficient to remove the reaction products and unreacted species. A growth per cycle of 0.82 Å was obtained for a deposition temperature of 150 C.</p><p>The previously reported growth per cycle of 0.8 Å for thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 , <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> differs from our values. The reason for this difference is unclear, yet it is noted that the main difference with our process is a higher reactor pressure. Plasma-assisted ALD using LiO t Bu on the other hand was reported to have a growth per cycle of 0.4 Å, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> but the obtained stoichiometry was a mixture of Li 2 CO 3 and Li 2 O. Our lms grown at 150 C are found to be pure Li 2 CO 3 , as shown in the next section. Moreover, no saturation curves were shown in literature to support the data for this particular case. In general, plasma processes  oen have a higher growth per cycle when compared to thermal processes which is in agreement with our results. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> Next, the process window of ALD lms was extended to deposition temperatures between 50 and 300 C. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref> shows the thickness evolution as a function of the number of ALD cycles for various deposition temperatures. For plasma-assisted ALD and T sub # 200 C, the thickness of the lms develops linearly with the number of cycles. For temperatures higher than 250 C, the lm thickness develops according to two slopes, which correlates with a transition in lm chemical composition, as discussed in the next section. Due to high temperature sensitivity of the reactions and minor temperature uctuations of the process table, the trends of the thickness as a function of the number of cycles at 250 C varied from occasion to occasion: in some cases they tend to be similar to the growth behavior for T # 200 C and in other instances to T &gt; 250 C. Moreover, lms deposited at 250 C showed large height differences (see SEM images in the next section), which complicated the extraction of the lm thickness. For the thermal process, no transition in lm chemical composition was observed. However, the growth per cycle increases slightly as function of the number of ALD cycles, which can be explained by crystallization of the lms (in the ESI † more growth curves are shown for thermal ALD Li 2 CO 3 ).</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>, both the temperature dependency of the growth per cycle for the plasma-assisted, as well as the thermal ALD process is shown. It can be noticed that the growth per cycle of the thermal ALD process strongly decreases at 50 C, indicating the lower limit of the temperature window. The ALD process window for the plasma-assisted process is extended towards lower temperatures, as it has a similar growth per cycle at 50 C as at higher temperatures. The overall growth per cycle is higher for the plasma-assisted process as compared to the thermal process. As mentioned before, this is more oen observed for plasma processes due to the relatively high reactivity of the plasma species which could create a higher density of reactive surface sites. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> The differences in growth per cycle between thermal and plasma ALD, but also between different deposition temperatures for plasma-assisted ALD are conrmed by EBS data (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>). A slight decrease in growth per cycle with increasing temperature was observed for the thermal ALD process. This decrease might be caused by desorption of part of the absorbed precursor monolayer from the surface, by higher purity lm growth or by an increase in lm crystallinity. The crystallinity of the lms will be further discussed in the next paragraph.</p><p>To summarize, it is shown that both plasma-assisted and thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 show typical ALD growth behavior within a wide temperature window. Plasma-assisted ALD allows for lower temperature depositions, which results in a wider choice of (substrate) materials that can be used. This is particularly useful when temperature-sensitive materials are adopted, such as polymers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> In addition, the plasma-assisted process allows for higher growth per cycle values and shorter cycle times compared to thermal ALD, without compromising on the quality of the layer. This will enable higher throughputs for ALD reactors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical composition</head><p>The stoichiometry of 50 nm thick lms was probed using a combination of ERD and EBS. The atomic percentage of all the elements in the lm is reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. For thermal and plasma-assisted ALD lms grown up to 250 C, the results point out a stoichiometry very similar to Li 2 CO 3 . The lms are slightly sub-stoichiometric, since the carbon content in the lms is relatively low (stoichiometric Li 2 CO 3 contains 33.3 at% Li, 16.7 at% C and 50.0 at% O). Furthermore, the calculated mass density for these samples is slightly lower than the bulk density of 2.11 g cm À3 . Only a few at% of H is found in the lms.</p><p>Plasma ALD at 300 C on the other hand shows a high hydrogen content, suggesting the co-presence of LiOH. As mentioned before, air exposure of the fabricated layers was minimized by transporting the samples in an evacuated transport tube, although some degradation of the layers cannot be excluded. The hydrogen content is not constant through the lm thickness, but is mainly present in the lm's depth indicating air reactivity aer deposition (a depth prole shown in the ESI †). The relatively high carbon content suggests that the lm reacted from LiOH towards Li 2 CO 3 upon air exposure. The reactivity of plasma ALD lms deposited at 300 C will be discussed in more detail later in this paragraph.</p><p>For all samples, the amount of deposited lithium atoms scales with the growth per cycle obtained by SE (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>). Assuming the mass density of stoichiometric Li 2 CO 3 to be equal to the bulk density of 2.11 g cm À3 , one monolayer of lithium carbonate contains roughly 10.58 Li atoms per nm 2 . ‡ Based on the EBS growth per cycle of 2.09 Li atom per nm 2 for the thermal ALD process, in each cycle approximately 1/5 th of a monolayer of Li 2 CO 3 is deposited. For the plasma-assisted process, about 1/4 th to 1/3 rd of a monolayer is deposited every cycle.</p><p>For plasma ALD at 300 C, the amount of deposited Li atoms deviates strongly from the lower temperature processes. At the same time the SE growth per cycle for this sample, but also for the one prepared at 275 C, deviates from the lower temperature depositions. The lms deposited at higher temperatures changed when they were removed from the reactor as could be observed visually. Furthermore, the ellipsometric data obtained ex situ could not be tted using the same model as during in situ measurements. The instability, deviating growth per cycle and increased hydrogen content of these layers suggests that the formed layers were not Li 2 CO 3 but rather a mixture of LiOH and Li 2 O. The increased growth per cycle can be explained by the fact that LiOH is hygroscopic and easily absorbs H 2 O and forms a hydrate. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> It is reported for thermal ALD of LiOH at 225 C that long purge times of 2 hours lead to a stable mass measured by QCM as a result of H 2 O desorption. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> To further investigate the lm instability for growth temperatures above 250 C, 50 nm thick lms were fabricated at different deposition temperatures. These were then subsequently exposed to CO 2 and H 2 O pulses inside the ALD reactor. The lms were measured by in situ SE and the phase change (D) was monitored at 589 nm aer every pulse as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. For plasma depositions at 250 C, D was unaffected by CO 2 and H 2 O exposure, pointing out the stability of the lm. However, the lm deposited at a slightly higher temperature of 275 C strongly reacted with CO 2 , whereas for the lm deposited at 300 C D only slightly changes during the rst pulse. Both LiOH and Li 2 O could react with CO 2 to form Li 2 CO 3 . However, it is reported in literature that the reaction between Li 2 O and CO 2 for temperatures from 200 to 400 C only occurs in the top few nanometers of the Li 2 O and then a self-limiting shell of Li 2 CO 3 develops. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> This in contrast to LiOH, which would be extremely reactive towards CO 2 . Hence, the lm at 300 C most likely consists of Li 2 O as aer the rst CO 2 pulse D only slightly changes suggesting that only a surface reaction is occurring. During subsequent exposure steps, the layer does not further react with CO 2 , implying the absence of LiOH. Aer the CO 2 pulses, the sample was subjected to H 2 O pulses. As observed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, the 300 C lm consisting of Li 2 O is reacting with the H 2 O forming LiOH. Next, CO 2 is pulsed again, and the layer is again reacting to form Li 2 CO 3 . Unlike the lm deposited at 300 C, the as-deposited 275 C lm was very reactive towards the rst CO 2 pulses and therefore (partly) consisted of LiOH. For all other lms, which include plasma ALD lms deposited at 50-250 C and thermal ALD lms deposited at 50-300 C, the change in D was negligibly small, indicating that almost no reaction with H 2 O or CO 2 occurred. These stable Li 2 CO 3 lms were used for ex situ XPS analysis which will be discussed later in this section.</p><p>The in situ SE measurements presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> show the formation of LiOH/Li 2 O for plasma-assisted ALD at processing temperatures &gt; 250 C. For these temperatures it was also  shown that the lm thickness versus number of ALD cycles develops differently. In the rst 100 cycles the lm growth was signicantly different from the rest of the deposition which is correlated with the transition in lm chemical composition. Since the use of plasma at processing temperatures &gt; 250 C has a signicant effect on the lm growth and composition, also the effect of the plasma duration was investigated. Up to this point, a plasma exposure of 3 s was adopted. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> shows the thickness evolution with number of ALD cycles for various plasma exposure times. As observed from the graph, the bulk growth per cycle for different plasma exposure times is similar. However, for longer plasma exposure times, the growth per cycle requires a lower number of ALD cycles to become linear, compared to shorter plasma exposure times. The formation of LiOH/Li 2 O can thus be further stimulated by prolonging the plasma exposure time.</p><p>The chemical composition of the deposited lms was further studied by ex situ XPS. No sputtering procedure was adopted, as it was found that the stoichiometry of the lms changed due to interaction with Ar ions. Upon chemical decomposition during sputtering, Li 2 CO 3 experiences a transition to Li 2 O (ESI †). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>, the XPS core level spectra of C 1s, Li 1s and O 1s are shown for thermal ALD at 150 C. The binding energy scale was calibrated by using the hydrocarbon contamination C 1s peak at 285.0 eV. As expected, the C 1s spectrum shows a main peak at $290.1 eV assigned to the carbonate environment in Li 2 CO 3 . The other peaks tted with a red line are associated with adventitious carbon on the sample surface. In the Li 1s spectrum a peak at $55. 4 eV is observed which is associated to Li 2 CO 3 . The O 1s spectrum consists of a peak with a maximum at $531.8 eV. The shape of the peak is slightly asymmetric. To visualize the asymmetry a second peak is tted to the data. The asymmetry can be explained by the crystallographic structure of Li 2 CO 3 in which two oxygen atoms have an identical environment, but the third oxygen has a different environment of surrounding atoms. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> The obtained stoichiometry for this lm was: 33.0 at% lithium, 17.7 at% carbon and 49.3 at% oxygen, corresponding to stoichiometric Li 2 CO 3 . Proportionate, there is slightly more carbon than obtained by EBS. To some extent, the difference can be explained by the low penetration depth of XPS ($10 nm) and the presence of carbon on the sample surface. All other lms (prepared by plasma as well as thermal ALD) are measured and subsequently tted using the same method and all showed the expected Li 2 CO 3 stoichiometry. The results are summarized in the ESI. † Li 2 CO 3 lms which are only slightly sub-stoichiometric can thus be deposited by thermal as well as by plasma-assisted ALD. In addition, it is possible to deposited Li 2 O at temperatures &gt; 250 C using the plasma-assisted process. It has already been shown in literature that this is also possible using thermal ALD for temperatures &gt; 250 C, when the CO 2 step was omitted from the process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> Deposition of Li 2 O can be benecial when presence of carbon in the lms is undesirable. On the other hand, with thermal ALD it is possible to deposit Li 2 CO 3 lms also at high temperatures of 300 C. If high temperature Li 2 CO 3 depositions are preferred, for example when the process is combined in super-cycles (to make more complex material structures) employing also precursors or co-reactants which require higher deposition temperatures, the thermal process could be preferred.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crystallinity and morphology</head><p>XRD was used to determine the crystallinity of the lms deposited at different temperatures. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref> shows the X-ray diffractograms for $50 nm thick lms. Both plasma and thermal  ALD lms show a typical diffraction peak originating from crystalline Li 2 CO 3 . The gonio measurements, which detect periodicity of planes parallel to the surface, show only the peak at 31.7 , meaning the process yields a preferential crystal growth orientation in the &lt;002&gt; direction. For thermal ALD lms, the crystallinity increases slightly with increasing deposition temperature. A similar trend was observed in literature for thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 on Si (100) substrates using a LiN(SiMe 3 ) 2 precursor, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> although the crystalline growth started only at $180 C according to their XRD spectra. The onset for crystalline growth could thus be inuenced by the precursor, the substrate or a combination of both.</p><p>When considering the plasma ALD Li 2 CO 3 lms, the layer deposited at 50 C is highly crystalline and oriented in the &lt;002&gt; direction, similar to the thermal process. At higher deposition temperatures, the spectra change signicantly and the crystallinity seems to be suppressed. Since the samples are measured by gonio XRD, we cannot exclude that there is a crystalline component present in the lms because this technique is less sensitive to 50 nm thick lms. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>, SEM images of the surfaces and cross-sections are shown corresponding to the samples measured by XRD. The lm growth, and resulting topography, change drastically when increasing temperature. Although for lower deposition temperatures highly uniform lms are formed, at 250 C, the lms show large thickness variations. We expect that this is related to the combustion of organic ligands and the formation of LiOH/Li 2 O during deposition induced by the O 2 plasma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conformality</head><p>The conformality of the deposition was studied using SEM at different positions on high aspect ratio Si pillars. The pillars, which are 50 mm high and have a diameter of 2 mm, are coated with a $30 nm TiN current collector using ALD. On top of the TiN a $50 nm Li 2 CO 3 layer was deposited using a table temperature of 150 C. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref> shows 3 SEM pictures taken at different heights along the pillar for plasma-assisted as well as thermal ALD. Image (a) is taken at the top of the pillars and shows a Li 2 CO 3 layer of $55 nm for the plasma-assisted deposition. Image (b) is taken half way the pillar and depicts a $45 nm Li 2 CO 3 layer (82% of thickness at top). At the bottom (c), the plasma-assisted Li 2 CO 3 is $40 nm thick (73%). For thermal ALD on the other hand thicknesses of $60, 52 (87%) and 48 nm (80%) are measured along the pillars. We can conclude that the conformality on high aspect ratio pillars is rather good. Note that only the lithium exposure time was varied. Elongation of the lithium dosing time drastically improves the conformality of thermal ALD. For example, when thermal ALD was adopted using 6 s lithium dosing instead of 10 s, the Li 2 CO 3 layer at the bottom is 20 nm instead of 48 nm.  For plasma ALD the conformality remains similar when varying the lithium dosing time. It is expected that the conformality can still be improved by further optimization of the precursor and plasma exposure steps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electrochemical analysis</head><p>The Li-ion conductivity of plasma and thermal ALD Li 2 CO 3 layers was investigated using impedance spectroscopy. The measurements were performed at open circuit potential (OCP) on 50 nm Li 2 CO 3 lms deposited at 150 C on a TiN current collector. The results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref> on a complex plane plot. Both the measured layers show a behavior characteristic of a solid electrolyte: an intercept with the x-axis at high frequency, a semi-circle at medium frequency and a 45 inclined response at low frequency. Such behavior is typically associated with the ionic conductivity through a solid material. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> The high frequency intercept with the x-axis is generally attributed to the resistance of the cables, contacts and liquid electrolyte, the semi-circle originates from the ionic conductivity through the solid material and its capacitive response. The 45 slope is typically associated with a Warburg-like response, here the Liion diffusion through the liquid electrolyte. Note that in the measurements performed here electronic leakage through the Li 2 CO 3 lms is not probed.</p><p>Further analysis was performed by tting an equivalent circuit to the measured impedance response (shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref>). The response of the Li 2 CO 3 layer deposited by thermal ALD could be adequately tted using model I shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10b</ref> which is conrmed by the low c 2 value of 5 Â 10 À4 . When equivalent circuit model II was tried to t the response of the plasma deposited Li 2 CO 3 layer, no adequate t could be obtained. For this reason, model II was used, resulting in the t shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref>. The quality of the t was again conrmed by the low c 2 value of 2 Â 10 À4 .</p><p>From the complex non-linear square tting of the models to the impedance data, different component values are extracted. The R s was found to be around 150 U for both thermal and plasma samples. This value corresponds to the resistance of the cables and the electrochemical cell. The other relevant parameters are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. For the thermal sample a resistance (R 1 ) value of 25 kU is extracted, corresponding to a Li-ion conductivity of 4 Â 10 À10 S cm À1 , well in accordance values predicted by simulation studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> From the constant phase element (CPE 1 ), a capacitance value can be extracted according to the following formula: <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref>    </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(kU) C 1 (F) R 2 (kU) C 2 (F) c 2 Thermal 25 2 Â 10 À7 - - 5 Â 10 À4 Plasma 2.5 4 Â 10 À7 3 8Â 10 À7 2 Â 10 À4 C ¼ Q 1/n R 1 (1Àn)/n</formula><p>Usage of this formula assumes a normal distribution of the time constants associated with the constant phase element. It allows an accurate determination of the capacitance value associated with the CPE even with an n value around 0.8. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> By using the above formalism, a capacitance value of 200 nF is extracted for CPE 1 , corresponding to a dielectric constant of $25. This value is higher than what is expected for typical oxide lms. However, the large surface roughness of the thermal lms must be considered (see ESI Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4 †</ref>). Such roughness increases the effective contact area of the capacitor which is not included when using the geometrical surface area. For this reason also the extracted ionic conductivity value will be slightly overestimated and can be adjusted for surface roughness down to a value of 10 À10 S cm À1 .</p><p>The impedance response of the plasma-assisted Li 2 CO 3 sample was also probed. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10a</ref> shows that the plasma sample has a lower ionic resistance (as indicated from the intercept with the x-axis). This semi-circle consists of two overlapping semi-circles with slightly different time constants which is re-ected in the model choice (model II). The capacitance values were again extracted by using the previously shown formula. The values found were 400 and 800 nF for respectively CPE 1 and CPE 2 . These values correspond to dielectric constants of 40 and 80, so signicantly higher than the one of the thermal sample and too high for typical oxide lms.</p><p>Such capacity values can be attributed to a change in dielectric constant or different geometrical dimensions. However, no difference in mass density could be detected between the thermal and plasma Li 2 CO 3 layers (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). Therefore, it is unlikely that a signicant difference in dielectric constant exists between the two layers. When considering the morphology of the layers (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>), a columnar structure can be seen. Therefore, the liquid electrolyte may contact the individual grains. Clearly this would lead to a signicant increase in contact area and thus an increased capacitance value. The distribution in grain size can in such case lead to a distribution in time constants. The two resistance values extracted from the tting, each correspond to a Li-ion conductivity value in the order of 1 Â 10 À9 S cm À1 . However, the underestimation of the contact area introduces a signicant uncertainty on this value which, based on the increased surface area, will be overestimated. When normalizing the conductivity value found here to the ratio of the different effective surface areas of the thermal and plasma samples, a conductivity value of 10 À10 S cm À1 is obtained, a value again in line with other literature reports. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>A comparison has been made between the remote plasma ALD process and its more extensively adopted thermal counterpart. Self-limiting growth was obtained for both processes within a wide temperature window. This wide temperature window could especially useful when Li 2 CO 3 is combined in super-cycles to obtain more complex material stoichiometries, since many other precursors or co-reactants have a limited temperature window. Especially the use of plasma allows for the possibility to deposit at lower process temperatures, which would be benecial for temperature-sensitive substrates. Moreover, plasma-assisted ALD allows for shorter deposition times and higher growth per cycle values leading to an increase in reactor throughput.</p><p>Stoichiometric Li 2 CO 3 lms can be deposited with both ALD processes. In addition, it is possible to deposited Li 2 O at temperatures &gt;250 C through combustion of the organic ligands. This could be benecial when presence of carbon in the lms is undesirable. For thermal ALD it is necessary to also omit the CO 2 step from the process to obtain Li 2 O. For plasmaassisted ALD, introduction of Li 2 O in the lms is accompanied with suppression of lm crystallinity and increases lm non-uniformity. The formation of Li 2 O can be further promoted by prolonging the plasma exposure time.</p><p>Both plasma-assisted and thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 allow for conformal coating of high aspect ratio substrates as can be important for future Li-ion batteries. To the best of our knowledge this paper provides the rst proper conductivity measurement of Li 2 CO 3 ALD lms. An ion conductivity in the order of 10 À10 S cm À1 was obtained for both plasma and thermal ALD aer normalizing the tted conductivity values to the ratio of the different effective surface areas. Studies are ongoing to characterize the electrochemical properties of the Li 2 CO 3 lms in more depth.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Schematic of the pulsing sequence of the ALD cycle for depositions of Li 2 CO 3 by (a) thermal and (b) plasma-assisted ALD. The H 2 O dose during the thermal ALD process was only 50 ms, after which all valves were closed for 4 s to allow for the molecules to react. Therefore, this is referred to as "H 2 O reaction".</figDesc><graphic coords="3,64.29,50.57,466.70,109.93" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Saturation curves for (a) thermal and (b) plasma-assisted ALD of Li 2 CO 3 obtained at 150 C showing the self-limiting growth behavior of the ALD process. The solid line serves as a guide to the eye. Dotted lines indicate the chosen standard values and the corresponding growth per cycle. Note that the reaction time of H 2 O after dosing was kept at 4 s.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,67.64,546.86,460.02,143.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 (a) In situ thickness measurements by SE for plasma-assisted ALD of Li 2 CO 3 at 50, 200, 275 and 300 C and thermal ALD of Li 2 CO 3 at 150 C. The film growth between 50 and 200 C with plasma ALD was very similar (see ESI †). (b) Growth per cycle as a function of process table temperature for both plasma-assisted (squares) and thermal (circles) ALD processes.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,59.70,334.77,215.21,326.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4 Phase shift of the incident light (D) from in situ SE measurements of the reaction of CO 2 and H 2 O with $50 nm plasma ALD films grown at 250, 275 and 300 C. First, CO 2 was dosed into the reaction chamber 20 times with pulses of 2 s, next H 2 O was pulsed 20 times for 50 ms and afterwards CO 2 was again pulsed 20 times. SE data was recorded after every pulse and D is plotted at 589 nm.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,329.50,472.37,197.22,188.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 In situ SE thickness measurement for plasma-assisted ALD of Li 2 CO 3 at 300 C using different O 2 plasma exposure times.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,65.42,50.57,203.73,161.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6 XPS (a) C 1s, (b) Li 1s and (c) O 1s spectra for Li 2 CO 3 grown by thermal ALD at 150 C. The measured spectra (black line) and fitted peaks (blue and red) are plotted together. The obtained Li 2 CO 3 stoichiometry is 33.0 at% Li, 17.7 at% C and 49.3 at% O.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,67.64,584.11,460.02,116.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7 XRD gonio scans of $50 nm thick Li 2 CO 3 films grown on TiN using thermal (blue) and plasma (red) ALD at different processing temperatures. The bars in the lower panel indicate the expected diffraction from a Li 2 CO 3 powder sample. The reflections at $42.5 originate from the TiN (200) textured substrate.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,56.24,50.57,222.18,188.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8 (a) High resolution SEM pictures showing the surface topography and (b) cross-section of Li 2 CO 3 deposited with plasma ALD at 50, 150, and 250 C. The scale bar applies to all of the pictures.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,108.00,513.92,379.36,186.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9 Examination of the conformality of the Li 2 CO 3 processes at 150 C. Micropillars of 50 mm high and a diameter of 2 mm are used for this purpose. The pillars are coated with a 30 nm TiN layer on top of which a $50 nm layer of Li 2 CO 3 was deposited. Images (a), (b) and (c) show the Li 2 CO 3 /TiN layer at respectively the top, middle and bottom of the pillars. Thickness variations from 40-55 nm (plasma) and 48-60 nm (thermal) were observed. For the thermal process a lithium dosing time of 10 s was used, whereas for the plasma process the standard dose time of 6 s was sufficient. The scale bar applies to all of the pictures.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,49.44,50.57,235.65,203.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 (</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10 (a) Impedance spectroscopy of 50 nm Li 2 CO 3 films prepared by thermal (blue) and plasma-assisted (red) ALD at 150 C and (b) equivalent circuit models used to fit the data.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,341.86,50.57,172.54,330.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Li 2 CO 3 ALD process details collected from earlier publications Teon cell was clamped on top of the sample using a Kalrez O-ring. A Luggin capillary was used to connect the cell with the reference-electrode compartment. One molar LiClO 4 (battery-grade, Sigma-Aldrich) in propylene carbonate was used as the electrolyte. The experiments were carried out in an Ar glovebox (O 2 , H 2 O &lt; 1 ppm). Impedance spectroscopy results were analyzed by tting an equivalent circuit to the data, using MEISP soware (Kumho Chemical Laboratories). The obtained ts had a c 2 value in the range from 10 À3 to 10 À5 . The relative standard deviation for all tted values remained below 5%.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Precursor</cell><cell>Co-reactant(s)</cell><cell>T sub ( C)</cell><cell>GPC ( Å)</cell><cell>Ref.</cell></row><row><cell>LiO t Bu</cell><cell>H 2 O, CO 2</cell><cell>225</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell>16</cell></row><row><cell>LiHMDS</cell><cell>H 2 O, CO 2</cell><cell>89-332</cell><cell>0.41-0.14</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>LiTMSO</cell><cell>H 2 O, CO 2</cell><cell>200-300</cell><cell>0.5-0.3</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>LiO t Bu</cell><cell>O 2 plasma</cell><cell>225, 300</cell><cell>0.4</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell>Li(thd)</cell><cell>O 3</cell><cell>185-225</cell><cell>0.3-0.07</cell><cell>20</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Properties of $50 nm films fabricated using the standard thermal ALD process at 150 C and plasma ALD process at 150, 250 and 300 C. The growth per cycle in terms of atoms per nm 2 and the atomic percentages where determined by EBS and ERD. The mass density was obtained by combining EBS and SE results. In the first row the typical error is given for a certain parameter</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sample</cell><cell>GPC (at. per nm 2 )</cell><cell>[Li] (at%)</cell><cell>[C] (at%)</cell><cell>[O] (at%)</cell><cell>[H] (at%)</cell><cell>Mass density (g cm À3 )</cell></row><row><cell>Thermal 150 C</cell><cell>2.09 AE 0.1</cell><cell>33.4 AE 1.7</cell><cell>14.6 AE 0.8</cell><cell>50.7 AE 2.0</cell><cell>1.3 AE 0.2</cell><cell>1.95 AE 0.20</cell></row><row><cell>Plasma 150 C</cell><cell>3.08</cell><cell>32.7</cell><cell>15.1</cell><cell>49.6</cell><cell>2.6</cell><cell>2.06</cell></row><row><cell>Plasma 250 C</cell><cell>2.76</cell><cell>30.5</cell><cell>15.8</cell><cell>50.9</cell><cell>2.8</cell><cell>1.97</cell></row><row><cell>Plasma 300 C</cell><cell>6.83</cell><cell>30.9</cell><cell>13.3</cell><cell>44.7</cell><cell>11.1</cell><cell>n.a.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Summary of the most relevant circuit model parameters</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sample</cell><cell>R 1</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This journal is © The Royal Society of Chemistry 2017</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>View Article Online</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p>This journal is © The Royal Society of Chemistry 2017 RSC Adv., 2017, 7, 41359-41368 | 41367</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge <rs type="person">Dr Marcel Verheijen</rs> for fruitful discussion and <rs type="person">Cristian van Helvoirt</rs> and <rs type="person">Jeroen van Gerwen</rs> for technical assistance. This project is nancially supported by the <rs type="programName">Dutch program</rs> "<rs type="projectName">A green Deal in Energy Materials" ADEM Innovation Lab</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_Q8nTd3T">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">A green Deal in Energy Materials&quot; ADEM Innovation Lab</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Dutch program</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head><p>There are no conicts to declare.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E.-J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Microchem</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Asakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mizusakib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Narita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Solid State Ionics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shimamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Okamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Itagaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Aono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sadaoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sens. Actuators, B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mizusaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Solid State Ionics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bhattacharya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riahi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Alpas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carbon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rolison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4463" to="4492" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F M</forename><surname>Oudenhoven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Baggetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Energy Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rubloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kozen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">58503</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vereecken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Huyghebaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Donders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012, 30, 10801</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-Q</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3589" to="3615" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Miikkulainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gandrud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Østreng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ruud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvåg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Status Solidi A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nanotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECS Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Østreng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vajeeston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvåg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Adv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6315" to="6322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ruud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Miikkulainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mizohata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvåg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="01B" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kozen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pearse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Noked</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rublo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27749" to="27753" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Putkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sajavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8767" to="8771" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Projt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol., A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50801</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Magrasó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvåg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4669" to="4675" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Comstock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Elam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1677" to="1683" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Donders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arnoldbik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3066" to="A3071" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Costelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fjellvåg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2877" to="2881" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Banis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Adv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7285" to="7288" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hämäläinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holopainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Munnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hatanpää</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heikkilä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="A263" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ind. Eng. Chem. Fundam</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="454" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mosqueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vazquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfeiffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2307" to="2310" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dedryvere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gireaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grugeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Laruelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Tarascon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gonbeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15868" to="15875" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Put</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vereecken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meersschaut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sepúlveda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stesmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7060" to="7069" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hector</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8579" to="8593" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Orazem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Frateur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tribollet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marcelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pébère</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bunge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Riemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Musiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="C225" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hirschorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Orazem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tribollet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Frateur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Musiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6218" to="6227" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
