<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Remote Plasma ALD of Platinum and Platinum Oxide Films</title>
				<funder ref="#_4zHJBhv">
					<orgName type="full">Netherlands Technology Foundation STW</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2009-04-27">April 27, 2009.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
							<email>h.c.m.knoops@tue.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials Innovation Institute M2i</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2600 GA</postCode>
									<settlement>Delft</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Mackus</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Donders</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials Innovation Institute M2i</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2600 GA</postCode>
									<settlement>Delft</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Philips Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5656 AE</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
							<email>w.m.m.kessels@tue.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5600 MB</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Remote Plasma ALD of Platinum and Platinum Oxide Films</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2009-04-27">April 27, 2009.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F21D1AE74C2228EF35E1B1C5FCDAC9B6</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.3125876</idno>
					<note type="submission">Manuscript submitted February 20, 2009; revised manuscript received April 7, 2009.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Platinum and platinum oxide films were deposited by remote plasma atomic layer deposition ͑ALD͒ from the combination of ͑methylcyclopentadienyl͒trimethylplatinum ͑MeCpPtMe 3 ͒ precursor and O 2 plasma. A short O 2 plasma exposure ͑0.5 s͒ resulted in low resistivity ͑15 ⍀ cm͒, high density ͑21 g/cm 3 ͒, cubic Pt films, whereas a longer O 2 plasma exposure ͑5 s͒ resulted in semiconductive PtO 2 films. In situ spectroscopic ellipsometry studies revealed no significant nucleation delay, different from the thermal ALD process with O 2 gas which was used as a benchmark. A broad temperature window ͑100-300°C͒ for remote plasma ALD of Pt and PtO 2 was demonstrated.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>When deposited with the precise thickness control and high conformality of atomic layer deposition ͑ALD͒, platinum films have a large variety of potential applications in microelectronics and energy technologies due to their chemical stability, catalytic activity, and excellent electronic properties. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> While being less investigated, platinum oxide is of interest because of its optical properties and because PtO x can be ͑locally͒ reduced to Pt. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> In the research efforts toward the applications of these films deposited by ALD, nucleation properties, material quality, and process temperature window are of key importance.</p><p>Few Pt ALD processes have been reported, of which the thermal ALD process using ͑methylcyclopentadienyl͒trimethylplatinum ͑MeCpPtMe 3 ͒ and O 2 gas described by Aaltonen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> has become the most adopted. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> This process relies on the dissociative chemisorption of O 2 on the Pt surface for oxidative decomposition of the precursor ligands. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> For PtO x only one ALD process has been reported, to the best of our knowledge. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> PtO x films were obtained from the combination of Pt͑acac͒ 2 ͑acac = acetylacetonate͒ and O 3 in the small temperature window of 120-130°C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> In this article, ALD processes are reported for Pt and PtO 2 from the combination of MeCpPtMe 3 precursor and O 2 plasma exposure. In the O 2 plasma, O radicals are created, providing atomic O to the surface directly from the gas phase, enhancing oxygen chemisorption and oxidation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> The growth and nucleation properties, material properties, and substrate-temperature dependence of the Pt and PtO 2 process are investigated for remote plasma ALD and benchmarked against the thermal ALD of Pt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental</head><p>The Pt and PtO 2 films were deposited in the open-load ALD-I setup described extensively in Ref. 15. In short, a deposition chamber was connected to an inductively coupled plasma source and a pump unit through gate valves. The pump unit consisted of a turbo molecular pump and a rotary pump reaching a base pressure of Ͻ10 -5 mbar by overnight pumping. MeCpPtMe 3 precursor ͑98%, Sigma-Aldrich͒, heated to 70°C, was vapor drawn into the chamber. The substrates were heated to 100-300°C ͑precursor decomposition starts above 310°C͒, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> while the reactor walls were kept at a temperature of 75°C.</p><p>For the processes investigated the first half-cycle consisted of MeCpPtMe 3 precursor dosing with the bottom valve closed ͑no pumping͒ to maximize precursor usage. After the precursor exposure the reaction products were pumped out by opening the bottom valve to the turbo pump. For thermal ALD the second half-cycle consisted of a 5 s O 2 exposure at 0.03 mbar. For the remote plasma process the O 2 gas flowed through the plasma source ͑0.01 mbar pressure͒ while a 100 W plasma power was applied. A 0.5 s O 2 plasma exposure was used for Pt deposition, while a 5 s plasma exposure resulted in the deposition of PtO 2 films. Si͑100͒ with native oxide or with 400 nm thermally grown SiO 2 was used as the substrate.</p><p>In situ spectroscopic ellipsometry ͑SE͒ with a J. A. Woollam, Inc. M2000U ͑0.75-5.0 eV͒ ellipsometer was employed to determine the thickness and the dielectric function of the films during the ALD process. After deposition the optical range was extended to 6.5 eV using ex situ variable-angle measurements with a J. A. Woollam, Inc. M2000D. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> Electrical resistivity was measured by a four-point probe ͑FPP͒, whereas the atomic composition and mass density of the films were determined from Rutherford backscattering spectrometry ͑RBS͒ using 2 MeV 4 He + ions. The microstructure of the films was studied using X-ray diffraction ͑XRD͒ with a Philips X'Pert MPD diffractometer equipped with a Cu K␣ source ͑1.54 Å radia-tion͒. Additionally, the thickness and mass density were determined by X-ray reflectometry ͑XRR͒ measurements on a Bruker D8 Advance X-ray diffractometer. The surface roughness of the films was determined by atomic force microscopy ͑AFM͒ using an NT-MDT Solver P47 SPM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head><p>ALD growth and nucleation delay.-Pt films were deposited by remote plasma and thermal ALD, and PtO 2 was deposited by remote plasma ALD at a substrate temperature of 300°C. A summary of the conditions and material properties is given in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. For the thermal process a MeCpPtMe 3 dosing time of 1 s is necessary to reach saturation of the growth per cycle, while the remote plasma process requires 3 s. The length of the plasma exposure time determines whether Pt or PtO 2 is deposited. A short O 2 plasma exposure of 0.5 s results in Pt, while a long O 2 plasma exposure of 5 s results in PtO 2 . When using O 2 gas, Pt is obtained up to long O 2 exposure times in line with the results reported by Aaltonen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> When measuring the thickness as a function of the number of cycles by in situ SE for the three processes ͑Fig. 1͒, no growth was observed for thermal ALD on c-Si substrates with 400 nm SiO 2 or native oxide for the conditions employed. Pt growth on these substrates could only be achieved by using a higher O 2 pressure ͑Ͼ0.8 mbar͒ as also typically used in the literature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> On the contrary, remote plasma ALD of Pt ͑0.5 s O 2 plasma͒ leads to immediate growth without a substantial nucleation delay. From the ellipsometry measurements, which have a reduced accuracy in the first 1-2 nm, it is concluded that growth per cycle is constant after the first 50 cycles. On the Pt film deposited by remote plasma ALD, the thermal ALD process continues without nucleation delay, demonstrating the possibility to deposit a Pt seed layer by remote plasma ALD. The remote plasma process of Pt shows a similar growth rate as the thermal process, which in turn is close to that reported by Aaltonen et al. ͑ϳ0.045 nm/cycle͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The PtO 2 process ͑5 s O 2 plasma͒ also shows immediate growth with potentially a brief nucleation delay. After ϳ50 cycles the growth per cycle is constant at 0.047 nm/cycle compared to ϳ0.055 nm/cycle found by Hämäläinen et al. using Pt͑acac͒ 2 and O 3 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> From the difference in Pt atomic density, it is concluded that for PtO 2 , fewer Pt atoms are deposited per cycle than for the Pt process ͑1.1 ϫ 10 14 Pt cm -2 cycle -1 for PtO 2 compared to 3.0 ϫ 10 14 Pt cm -2 cycle -1 for Pt͒. This is different from the thermal Ru and RuO 2 ALD process where the growth rate increases with the partial O 2 pressure going from Ru to RuO 2 material. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> The dielectric functions determined by SE for Pt and for PtO 2 are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The two materials result in very distinct dielectric functions, whereas the dielectric functions for Pt obtained by thermal ALD and remote plasma ALD are indistinguishable. The Pt was modeled using a Drude-Lorentz parametrization, where the Drude term, dominant at low photon energies, accounts for the intraband absorption by conduction electrons. Several Lorentz oscillators ͑at 0.9, 1.5 eV, and higher energies͒ were used for the interband absorption. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> In agreement with its semiconductive nature, the dielectric function of PtO 2 could be parametrized by a single Tauc-Lorentz oscillator ͑0.9 eV bandgap and 4.8 eV peak energy͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> The optical Tauc bandgap was ϳ1.5 eV, which is close to the bandgap reported for sputtered amorphous PtO 2 ͑1.2-1.3 eV͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Material properties.-As shown in Table <ref type="table">I</ref> both the remote plasma and thermal ALD process result in very similar material properties for the Pt films. In both cases high density ͑ϳ21 g/cm 3 ͒, low resistivity ͑ϳ15 ⍀ cm͒, and high purity Pt films were deposited. The density and resistivity for these ϳ30 nm thick films are close to the bulk values of 21.4 g/cm 3 and 10.8 ⍀ cm, and they are similar to the values reported for thermal ALD of Pt. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> The O and C contents remain below the RBS detection limit ͑Ͻ5%͒ and grazing incidence XRD spectra ͑Fig. 3͒ revealed a cubic phase composition for both the thermal and remote plasma ALD Pt films. The relatively high intensity of the ͑220͒ peak indicates that the Pt crystallites have a preferred orientation with their ͑111͒ lattice planes parallel to the sample surface as also reported for the thermal ALD process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The remote plasma ALD Pt film, which is only slightly thicker than the thermal ALD film, shows much stronger diffraction peaks, indicating a higher crystallinity. Both processes resulted in smooth films and had generally lower root-mean-square roughness values ͑0.4-0.7 nm͒ than reported ͑0.75-4 nm͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> Because island growth is known to promote surface roughening, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> the fast nucleation and, consequently, more pronounced layer-by-layer growth can be related to the lower surface roughness obtained for the remote plasma ALD process.</p><p>The platinum oxide has a lower density and is slightly overstoichiometric ͑PtO 2.2 ͒. The resistivity is very high as it is above the detection limit of the FPP ͑Ͼ100 ⍀ cm͒. For the process employing Pt͑acac͒ 2 and O 3 , a lower resistivity ͑1.5-5 ⍀ cm͒ was reported most probably due to a lower O content ͑PtO 1.6 ͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> The</p><p>Table I. The material properties of Pt and PtO 2 films deposited at 300°C by thermal and remote plasma ALD from MeCpPtMe 3 and O 2 gas or O 2 plasma. In situ SE, XRR, AFM, RBS, and FPP measurements were used for analysis. The typical experimental errors are given in the first row. Material ALD process Thickness ͑nm͒ Roughness ͑nm͒ Growth per cycle ͑Å/cycle͒ Mass density ͑g cm -3 ͒ Atomic composition ͑atom %͒ Electrical resistivity ͑⍀ cm͒ SE XRR XRR RBS Pt O C Pt 5 s O 2 gas a 27.3 Ϯ 0.5 26.6 Ϯ 0.3 0.7 Ϯ 0.3 0.45 Ϯ 0.04 22 Ϯ 1 20.8 Ϯ 0.5 100 Ͻ5 Ͻ5 1 3Ϯ 1 Pt 0.5 s remote plasma ϳ30 b 29.2 0.4 0.47 22 20.0 100 Ͻ5 Ͻ5 1 5 PtO 2 5 s remote plasma 26.7 26.5 0.4 0.47 10 8.9 31 69 Ͻ5 Ͼ1 ϫ 10 8 a Includes a 7 nm Pt seed layer deposited by the remote plasma ALD process. b Thickness determination less accurate due to opacity of the film at SE wavelengths.  <ref type="table">I</ref>. The starting substrate at 0 cycles was Si͑100͒ with 400 nm SiO 2 . After 150 cycles of remote plasma ALD, the Pt film growth is continued by thermal ALD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">͑Color online͒</head><p>The imaginary part of the dielectric function ͑ 2 ͒ for Pt and PtO 2 as determined by in situ SE measurements evaluated using Drude-Lorentz and Tauc-Lorentz parametrizations, respectively. PtO 2 film is amorphous or nanocrystalline, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> and no diffraction peaks from the ␣ and ␤ PtO 2 phases can be identified in the XRD spectra. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Temperature dependence.-Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref> shows the growth per cycle for the three processes over a wide temperature range. The thermal ALD Pt process has a temperature window starting at ϳ200°C. The fact that the growth per cycle is reduced at lower substrate temperatures is not yet understood. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> From surface science studies, it can be inferred that the dissociative chemisorption of O 2 ͓on Pt͑111͔͒ should not be the limiting factor. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> On the other hand, the remote plasma ALD process which uses atomic oxygen from the gas phase has a higher growth rate than the thermal process at 200°C. The higher resistivity ͑ϳ500 ⍀ cm͒ found for this temperature, however, suggests incomplete removal of O and C impurities from the material. The poorer material properties could be overcome by an H 2 plasma treatment. Exposure of the film to 300 s H 2 plasma at 100°C reduced the resistivity to 61 ⍀ cm. Moreover, tests with an ALD cycle containing a H 2 gas exposure step ͑no plasma power applied͒ of 2 s after the O 2 plasma step resulted in excellent materials properties for Pt at 100°C ͑mass density of 19.8 g cm <ref type="bibr">-3</ref> , no C and O impurities detected, and a resistivity of 19 ⍀ cm at 22 nm film thickness͒. These results demonstrate that the temperature window for remote plasma ALD of Pt can effectively be extended down to 100°C. For PtO 2 the growth per cycle decreases slightly with increasing substrate temperature between 100 and 300°C, demonstrating that this process also has a large temperature window. At the substrate temperature of 300°C, decomposition of PtO 2 is reported to start for sputtered films, while in air decomposition starts at 550°C due to the higher partial pressure of oxygen. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> For the process employing Pt͑acac͒ 2 and O 3 , only a small temperature window was observed ͑120-130°C͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> Therefore, the large temperature window of our PtO 2 process suggests a higher stability of the material, which can most likely be related to the higher oxygen content ͑PtO 2.2 compared to PtO 1.6 ͒.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>Remote plasma ALD processes of Pt and PtO 2 were developed from the combination of MeCpPtMe 3 precursor and O 2 plasma, and compared to the thermal ALD process of Pt using the same precursor and O 2 gas. High purity Pt can be obtained by a short O 2 plasma exposure, whereas PtO 2 can be obtained by a long O 2 plasma exposure. In situ SE revealed that the remote plasma processes lead to immediate growth without substantial nucleation delay, whereas the thermal ALD process leads to no growth at all unless a Pt starting surface or a high O 2 pressure is employed. A broad temperature window of 100-300°C was achieved for both materials when deposited by remote plasma ALD. For Pt a H 2 gas exposure step was included in the ALD cycle to obtain high purity films at 100°C.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. ͑Color online͒ Thickness measured by in situ SE function of the number of cycles for the Pt and PtO 2 ALD processes. The process conditions are listed in TableI. The starting substrate at 0 cycles was Si͑100͒ with 400 nm SiO 2 . After 150 cycles of remote plasma ALD, the Pt film growth is continued by thermal ALD.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>͑Color online͒ Grazing incidence XRD spectra for a remote plasma ALD Pt film ͑29 nm thickness͒, a thermal ALD Pt film ͑27 nm thickness͒, and a remote plasma ALD PtO 2 film ͑27 nm thickness͒. The Miller indexes of cubic Pt are indicated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. ͑Color online͒ growth per cycle for remote plasma and thermal ALD of Pt and remote plasma ALD of PtO 2 as a function of the substrate temperature. At 100°C the growth rate of the remote plasma process including a H 2 gas exposure step in the ALD cycle is shown. For thermal ALD of Pt, deposition took place on 10 nm thick Pt starting surfaces prepared by remote plasma ALD at 300°C. The lines serve as guides to the eye.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,37.50,454.29,520.00,336.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was sponsored by the <rs type="projectName">Materials Innovation Institute M2i</rs> under project no. <rs type="grantNumber">MC3.06278</rs>, and by the <rs type="funder">Netherlands Technology Foundation STW</rs>.</p><p><rs type="funder">Eindhoven University of Technology</rs> assisted in meeting the publication costs of this article.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_4zHJBhv">
					<idno type="grant-number">MC3.06278</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Materials Innovation Institute M2i</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sajavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keinonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date>1924 ͑2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kaloyeros</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1292" to="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Niessen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Baggetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Mater. (Weinheim, Ger.)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Armand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tarascon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">451</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2008</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Baggetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Niessen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Notten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Funct. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<date>1057 ͑2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hoover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Tolmachev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A37 ͑2009͒</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Maya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Riester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Thundat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yust</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1998</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kurihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamakawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nakano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tominaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. A, Pure Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Machalett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Edinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Diegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9030" to="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochem. Solid-State Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kuipers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Segner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1981</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hämäläinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Munnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2008</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gerrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">592</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Mackus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83517" to="082007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S A</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<date>205117 ͑2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Jellison</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Modine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1996</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Vandervorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jpn. J. Appl. Phys., Part</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date>2092 ͑1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aaltonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arstila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Meinander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
