<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Reaction mechanisms during plasma-assisted atomic layer deposition of metal oxides: A case study for </title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences ͑KNAW͒</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Dutch Technology Foundation STW</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2008-05-19">19 May 2008͒</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Hemmen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
							<email>w.m.m.kessels@tue.nl.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Appl</forename><surname>Phys</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Lett</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Al</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eindhoven University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>103</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 513</postBox>
									<postCode>5600 MB 103302-1 103302-13</postCode>
									<settlement>Eindhoven</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Reaction mechanisms during plasma-assisted atomic layer deposition of metal oxides: A case study for </title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2008-05-19">19 May 2008͒</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2B6540864BE7E430727B81959CC8EA9A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2924406</idno>
					<note type="submission">͑Received 14 November 2007; accepted 17 March 2008;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Plasma-assisted atomic layer deposition of Ta 2 O 5 from alkylamide precursor and remote O 2 plasma</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The synthesis of very thin metal oxide films by atomic layer deposition ͑ALD͒ is currently a very active research field. Investigations into various metal oxide materials for applications in semiconductor devices such as gate oxide in complementary-metal-oxide-semiconductor gate stacks and as dielectric layer in dynamic-random-access-memory devices had led to a rapid increase in the number of ALD processes developed. In many of the metal oxide ALD processes metal organic precursors are employed and H 2 O is used as oxidant. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> However, since recently, ALD processes in which O 3 or an O 2 plasma is used as an alternative oxidant source are gaining increasingly more attention. In these latter processes the oxidant is more reactive than H 2 O and, therefore, the surface reactions rely less on thermal activation by the substrate temperature. For example, when an O 2 plasma is used, chemical activation of the oxidant has already occurred in the gas phase and, therefore, the use of a lower deposition temperature is in many cases facilitated. Furthermore, for some materials it has been reported that improved film properties are obtained when using O 3 or O 2 plasma instead of H 2 O. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> The potentially more favorable process settings ͑e.g., in terms of substrate temperature and purge times͒ as well as the potentially improved material properties obtained for the O 3 and O 2 plasma based ALD processes have also contributed to an increased interest into ALD by other fields of technology than semiconductor industry. Potential application of ALD films in areas such as microsystems, solar cells, flexible electronics, energy storage, and photonics have recently been reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> While the material properties and functionality of the films have already been investigated in relative detail, the reaction mechanisms leading to film growth in the O 3 and O 2 plasma based ALD processes have hardly been addressed. Very recently, however, theoretical and experimental investigations of the reaction mechanism of Al 2 O 3 ALD from Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͓trimethylaluminum ͑TMA͔͒ precursor and O 3 were reported by Elliott et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> and Goldstein and George. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> Our research group recently published a first study about the reaction mechanism of plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 using Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and O 2 plasma. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> The current article is a follow up on this earlier work and a more extended study of the plasma-assisted ALD process of Al 2 O 3 will be presented.</p><p>Due to its excellent dielectric properties, its good adhesion to many surfaces, and its high thermal and chemical stability, Al 2 O 3 is a very relevant material for a wide range of applications. Furthermore, the thermal ALD process of Al 2 O 3 using Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and H 2 O is considered to be a model system for ALD film growth of metal oxides. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The ALD reaction mechanisms during the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and the H 2 O step have been thoroughly investigated both experimentally and theoretically. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> From these investigations, it has been established that Al 2 O 3 growth by thermal ALD occurs via the following successive "half-reactions:" <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> AlOH ͑s͒ + Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3͑g͒ → AlOAl͑CH 3 ͒ 2͑s͒ + CH 4͑g͒ , ͑1͒</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Al -CH 3͑s͒ + H 2 O ͑g͒ → AlOH ͑s͒ + CH 4͑g͒ ,<label>͑2͒</label></formula><p>where ͑s͒ and ͑g͒ represent surface groups and gas species, respectively. The chemisorption of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and H 2 O on the surface is a Lewis acid-base reaction in which methyl ligands ͑CH 3 -͒ and hydroxyl protons ͑H + ͒ combine in a Brønsted acid-base reaction and are eliminated as CH 4 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> For Al 2 O 3 as well as for some other metal oxides, the amount of material deposited per cycle was found to directly relate with the substrate temperature dependent ϪOH density on the surface. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> For the plasma-assisted ALD process of Al 2 O 3 based on Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing and O 2 plasma exposure, we recently presented compelling evidence that the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 chemisorption step appears very similar as in the thermal ALD process with H 2 O. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> Nonetheless, the oxidation step by the O 2 plasma appeared to be very different from the H 2 O based process. It was demonstrated that combustionlike reactions by the plasma generated O radicals removed the -CH 3 ligands from the surface because combustion products such as CO 2 and H 2 O were detected by mass spectrometry. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> Furthermore, a small signal due to the presence of CH 4 during the plasma exposure step indicated that the formed H 2 O byproduct induces a secondary thermal ALD-like reaction pathway. Previously such secondary reaction pathway, in which the reaction products of the oxidation step play a role in the surface chemistry, was speculated upon. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> In this article we present corroborating evidence and additional details that support the previously proposed reaction mechanism. A more extensive and complementary data set is reported as obtained by a combination of several in situ diagnostics such as spectroscopic ellipsometry ͑SE͒, quartz crystal microbalance ͑QCM͒ measurements, quadrupole mass spectrometry ͑QMS͒, and optical emission spectroscopy ͑OES͒. More specifically, extensive data on the saturation of the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 chemisorption reaction are presented. The previous observations are also corroborated by an additional data set obtained on a commercial 200 mm ALD reactor ͑Oxford Instruments FlexAL͒. More insight into several aspects of the reaction mechanism of plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 has been obtained: QMS signals for mass-to-charge ratios of m / z = 24-30 suggest the presence of small amounts of C 2 H x during the plasma exposure, in addition to the earlier detected presence of H 2 O, CO 2 , CO, and CH 4 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> By OES with an extended wavelength range in the UV, the presence of OH * emission was also identified during the plasma step. Furthermore, it has been demonstrated that the saturation conditions for Al 2 O 3 film growth can be determined not only directly via the use of film growth monitoring techniques, such as spectroscopic ellipsometry and quartz crystal microbalance, but also indirectly by gas phase diagnostics, such as OES and QMS. On the basis of the results reported a more complete picture of the reaction mechanisms during plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 will be presented. Finally, from this case study of Al 2 O 3 , the implications for plasma-assisted ALD of other metal oxide films grown from metal organic precursors and O 2 plasma will be briefly discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. EXPERIMENTAL</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. ALD-I reactor</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Reactor setup</head><p>Most of the experiments were carried out on a homebuilt remote plasma ALD reactor referred to as "ALD-I," which is schematically represented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1͑a͒</ref>. The reactor has been described in detail in our previous work with respect to the deposition of TiN and TaN films using a N 2 -H 2 plasma. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> Briefly, it consists of a remotely placed inductively coupled plasma source which is powered at a radiofrequency of 13.56 MHz and at a power of 100 W. For Al 2 O 3 deposition the source is operated on O 2 gas ͑purity Ͼ99.999%͒. The plasma source is connected to a wall heated deposition chamber where substrates can be placed on a individually heated stainless steel substrate holder. Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͑Akzo No- bel, semiconductor grade, purity Ͼ99.9999%͒ contained in a stainless steel bubbler and kept at room temperature was mounted to the precursor delivery line in which a small trapped volume ͑ϳ0.25 cm 3 ͒ was present in between two pneumatic valves. It should be noted that Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 forms a dimeric molecule in the liquid phase and in the gas phase at low temperatures through a bridged structure via the methyl groups. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> At temperatures ജ70 °C and at low pressures the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 is predominantly in the monomer phase. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Pulsing of the reactants</head><p>A schematic of the ALD cycle used in these experiments is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1͑b͒</ref>. A continuous flow of O 2 through the plasma source served both as plasma gas and as a purge gas. Since Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and O 2 do not react in the gas phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> it can be introduced into the O 2 background. The amount of precursor dosed per cycle was set by the number of successive, small Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures introduced into the reactor through alternatively evacuating ͑1 s͒ and refilling ͑1 s͒ the small trapped volume in the precursor delivery line. After a purging period, an O 2 plasma exposure was applied for a number of seconds by turning on the rf power. In the current investigation the implemented purge times were set such to allow for a complementary study by all diagnostics. During the cycle the pressure in the reactor was approximately constant at 7.5 mTorr. The deposition temperature was set to 70 °C by wall heating of the reactor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">In situ diagnostics</head><p>For in situ film measurements, a rotating compensator SE ͑J.A. Woollam, Inc. M2000U͒ with a wavelength range of 245-1000 nm was mounted on the reactor. The angle of incidence on the substrates was 68°with the substrate normal. SE data were typically measured after every ten completed Al 2 O 3 ALD cycles. Crystalline silicon ͑c-Si͒ was used as substrate material, which was either plasma oxidized for 5 min prior to deposition or contained a 400 nm thick thermal SiO 2 layer on top. The thickness of the Al 2 O 3 was determined by fitting the SE data with a Cauchy model using the Woollam WVASE software. The value of the refractive index at a photon energy of 2 eV ranged typically between 1.60 and 1.65 for the Al 2 O 3 films investigated by SE.</p><p>Film growth was also monitored by a QCM. Gold covered AT-cut quartz crystals with an oscillation frequency of 6 MHz were mounted in a Maxtek 150BSH bakeable crystal holder positioned in close proximity to the substrate holder and with the crystal surface facing down ͑i.e., not facing the plasma source͒. The crystals were first coated with a "fresh" plasma-assisted ALD Al 2 O 3 film before taking any film growth data. The QCM signal was monitored using a Maxtek TM400 thickness monitor which was interfaced with a computer at a data acquisition rate of 10 Hz. The extremely high sensitivity of the QCM to surface temperature fluctuations on the crystal progresses with temperature and, consequently, a careful interpretation of the measured signal is required. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> This high sensitivity of the QCM is the reason for controlling the temperature at 70 °C by uniform wall heating in this particular experiment, as described above. In addition, pres-sure variations in the reactor were adequately minimized by continuously flowing the O 2 gas. The QCM results are expressed in terms of mass gain with the unit hertz. <ref type="bibr">46</ref> The gas composition was measured by a differentially pumped QMS ͑Pfeifer QME 200, mass-to-charge ratio m / z =0-100͒ fitted at the side of the reactor. The gas sampling took place through a 150 m diameter pinhole keeping the pressure in the mass spectrometer within the working range ͑Ͻ10 -5 Torr͒ for the secondary electron multiplier to operate. The electron impact ionization by ϳ70 eV electrons in the mass spectrometer leads to fragmentation or "cracking" of incoming gas species. The identification of the parent molecules was therefore performed on the basis of its so-called cracking pattern. The cracking pattern of some molecules ͑CO, CO 2 , and Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͒ was measured specifically for our QMS by introducing calibration gases yielding good agreement with data reported in the literature. To achieve sufficient time resolution, time-resolved measurements were carried out by monitoring only two mass-to-charge ratios ͑m / z͒ at a time with an integration time of 10 ms. One of the two masses selected served as a reference signal, while the other mass ͑in the range of m / z =10-75͒ was varied over several runs. In the current measurements m / z =32 ͑O 2 + ͒ was taken as reference as there is a continuous flow of O 2 into the reactor. Data are typically taken over ten ALD cycles, and on the basis of the m / z =32 ͑O 2 + ͒ signal the measurements were synchronized afterwards. This procedure allowed for constructing a time-resolved mass scan of several masses with an adequate time resolution.</p><p>OES measurements were carried out by measuring the plasma emission just above the substrate holder using an Ocean Optics USB2000 spectrometer having a wavelength detection range of 250-870 nm and a spectral resolution of approximately 1 nm. The emission by the plasma was coupled into the spectrometer by placing an optical fiber with a small aperture ͑ϳ100 m diameter͒ close to one of the quartz windows on the main chamber. Time dependent measurements were carried out by repetitively acquiring full spectra ͑250-870 nm͒ with an integration time of 100 ms. The option in the software for selecting emission peaks in the spectrum and measuring the signal height as a function of time was also used to monitor excited plasma species during the plasma exposure step.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. FlexAL reactor</head><p>A similar, but less extensive in situ study of the Al 2 O 3 process was carried out in the commercial 200 mm FlexAL reactor from Oxford Instruments. Both the FlexAL reactor itself and the characteristics of the deposition process of Al 2 O 3 by remote plasma ALD using this reactor have been described in our previous work. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">47</ref> One main difference with the experiments carried out on the homebuilt ALD-I reactor described above is the method of precursor dosing. In the FlexAL a single dose is injected into the deposition chamber using a fast open-close ͑20 ms͒ Swagelok ALD valve positioned in the precursor delivery line. In all experiments an open-close time of 20 ms was used for Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing leading to saturated ALD reactions for Al 2 O 3 . Furthermore, a continuous O 2 flow of 60 SCCM ͑SCCM denotes cubic centimeter per minute at STP͒ was applied through the plasma source and the pressure in the reactor was kept constant at 15 mTorr. The intermitting purge time between precursor and plasma was 3 s, the plasma exposure was set to 4 s, and the purge between plasma and precursor was 0.5 s. Both the reactor walls and the substrate holder were not heated and remained at a temperature of approximately 25 °C.</p><p>Similar to the ALD-I setup, the FlexAL was equipped with a spectroscopic ellipsometer, a mass spectrometer, and optical emission spectroscopy. The SE configuration was similar to the ALD-I. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> The mass spectrometer ͑QMS, Pfeifer QME 200, m / z =0-200͒ was differentially pumped and the only difference with the ALD-I setup is that this mass spectrometer has an extended mass-to-charge ͑m / z͒ range and consequently a higher signal-to-noise ratio, especially for m / z ratios Ͼ40. Optical emission spectroscopy was performed using the same equipment as for the ALD-I. The plasma emission was collected through a quartz window at the top of the plasma source probing the emission from both the plasma source region and the downstream reactor region by line-of-sight measurement. This configuration was chosen because probing the emission downstream from the side of the reactor lead to a poor signal-to-noise-ratio at the high time resolution ͑ഛ100 ms͒ desired. The data analysis of the in situ diagnostics on the FlexAL reactor was identical to the data analysis on the ALD-I reactor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. In situ thickness monitoring by SE</head><p>In our previous work, it was established that in situ spectroscopic ellipsometry is a valuable tool to monitor ALD film growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">48</ref> In the current work the plasma-assisted ALD process of Al 2 O 3 was characterized at substrate temperatures of 70 and 200 °C. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the results obtained for a plasma exposure time of 2 s. The substrates were plasma oxidized Si samples prepared in situ. A clear linear increase in thickness with the number of cycles can be observed at both deposition temperatures. A thickness increase per cycle of 1.66Ϯ 0.02 Å at 70 °C and 1.27Ϯ 0.02 Å at 200 °C was calculated from the slope of the data shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. No significant initial growth delay was observed in the first few cycles of Al 2 O 3 deposition both on the plasma oxidized Si samples and on the thermal oxide covered c-Si.</p><p>In situ SE was used to determine the saturated precursor dosing regime associated with ALD film growth. The amount of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 introduced per precursor exposure was varied using the trapped volume in the precursor line as described earlier. The amount of precursor is fixed by the size of the trapped volume ͑ϳ0.25 cm 3 ͒ and the total precursor dose can therefore be varied by varying the number of successive precursor exposures used per cycle. The thickness increase per cycle ͑i.e., growth rate, sometimes also referred to as growth per cycle͒ is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3</ref> as a function of the number of successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures per cycle at 70 and 200 °C. The figure reveals that saturated growth is obtained for a total precursor dose consisting of more than six Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures per cycle for both temperatures.</p><p>Under saturated Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing conditions ͑i.e., more than six exposures͒ and 4 s plasma exposure the growth rate is 1.80Ϯ 0.02 Å / cycle at 70 °C and 1.27Ϯ 0.02 Å / cycle at 200 °C. These values are higher than typically reported for thermal ALD process using H 2 O, i.e., 1.1 Å / cycle at 70 °C and 1.0 Å / cycle at 200 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> Also for the thermal ALD process with O 3 lower growth rates were observed ͑1.1 Å / cycle at 70 °C and 0.8 Å / cycle at 200 °C͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">49</ref> A higher growth rate has been reported earlier for both remote and direct plasmas compared to thermal ALD for identical deposition temperature settings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">51</ref> We would like to note that the H 2 O based process suffers from the so-called "soft saturation" behavior, especially at low temperatures. High doses of H 2 O have been found necessary to reach saturated film growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52</ref> Not fully saturated growth might therefore be a reason for the lower growth rate reported for the thermal process based on H 2 O at 70 °C. A related aspect is that also very long purge times are required for removal of H 2 O from FIG. 3. ͑Color online͒ Growth rate per cycle as measured by SE at deposition temperatures of 70 and 200 °C as a function of the number of successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures used per ALD cycle. Also the mass gain determined by QCM measurements at 70 °C is given. 103302-4</p><p>the reactor. These long purge times provide more time for dehydroxilation reactions, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> lowering the surface -OH density. One of the benefits of ALD using O 3 or O 2 plasma as oxidant sources is that the purge times do not have to be severely extended to maintain proper ALD film growth at low deposition temperatures ͑Ͻ100 °C͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Mass uptake measurements by QCM</head><p>Quartz crystal microbalance measurements were used to monitor the mass uptake during a cycle at a substrate temperature of 70 °C. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref> shows the mass gain recorded by QCM for ten ALD cycles using only one single Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposure ͑i.e., a nonsaturated dose͒ per cycle and a plasma exposure time of 2 s. The QCM reveals a stepwise increase in mass in each ALD cycle. Also a negative spike is observed during every O 2 plasma step but this behavior can be attributed to a plasma artifact as will be discussed below. The mass gain was also measured in an experiment in which the total precursor dose was varied in a similar experiment as for the SE measurements. These results, obtained at 70 °C, are also included in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3</ref>. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3</ref>, it is evident that also the QCM measurements reveal saturated growth for a dose consisting of more than six precursor exposures per cycle, in perfect agreement with the SE measurements.</p><p>A detailed view of the QCM signal for one ALD cycle is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>. The time at which precursor valve was opened and the period during which the plasma exposure was active are indicated. When Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 is introduced into the reactor the chemisorption of the precursor to the surface can be observed in the form of a large stepwise increase in mass ͑m 1 ͒ ͓Fig. 5͑a͔͒. At the moment when the plasma is switched on, a sharp downward spike in the signal can be observed. Different from thermal ALD, the occurrence of electrical charging by the presence of ions and electrons or possibly plasma induced heat transfer apparently interferes with a proper measurement during the plasma exposure. The spike is a true plasma artifact, corroborated by the fact that a similar spike is also observed when only the plasma is pulsed ͓i.e., no Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose has preceded the plasma exposure͔, as is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure">5͑b͒</ref>. In both cases the signal slowly recovers to its genuine level after the plasma is switched off ͑ϳ20 s͒. The main difference, however, is that in Fig. <ref type="figure">5͑a͒</ref> a small increase in mass ͑m 2m 1 ͒ can be observed after the plasma exposure. This increase in mass is not observed when the precursor has not been introduced ͓see Fig. <ref type="figure">5͑b͔͒</ref>. The mass increase can be related to the oxidation of bonded precursor and the replacement of the surface functional groups.</p><p>The behavior in Fig. <ref type="figure">5͑a͒</ref> shows resemblance to what has previously been observed during QCM studies of thermal ALD of Al 2 O 3 at 70 °C. In these experiments during both the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and the H 2 O dosing, an increase in mass was observed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> Although for plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 the exact reaction mechanism has still not been clearly established, when following the procedure introduced by Rahtu and Ritala, <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">53</ref> the origins for the mass gain after the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose ͑m 1 ͒ and the plasma exposure ͑m 2 ͒ can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">m 1 = M͓Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͔ -n • M͑CH 4 ͒, ͑3͒ m 2 = M͑AlO 3/2 ͒, ͑4͒</formula><p>where M͓Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͔, M͑AlO 3/2 ͒, and M͑CH 4 ͒ represent the masses of the species involved, 72, 51, and 16 amu, respectively. On the basis of the previous measurements we can assume that reaction ͑3͒ occurs during the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing in which n -CH 3 ligands leave to the gas phase as CH 4 molecules. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> Furthermore, for simplicity after the plasma step a complete Al 2 O 3 layer is considered to have been formed. The possible presence of H on the surface after the plasma step is discarded since its mass is small compared to the other masses involved. On the basis of these assumptions the number of -CH 3 ligands released from the surface into the gas phase can be calculated by rewriting the ratio of the mass uptake after the two half-reactions ͑m 1 / m 2 ͒ to FIG. 5. ͑Color online͒ Detailed view of the QCM measurement at 70 °C of ͑a͒ a complete ALD cycle with Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing and O 2 plasma exposure and ͑b͒ O 2 plasma exposure without preceding Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing. The introduction of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and the start and end of the O 2 plasma exposure are indicated.</p><p>n =</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">M͓Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 ͔ -͑m 1 /m 2 ͒ • M͑AlO 3/2 ͒ M͑CH 4 ͒ , ͑5͒</formula><p>For a saturated dose at 70 °C it was calculated using Eq. ͑5͒ that, on average, n ϳ 1.</p><p>8 ͑-CH 3 ͒ ligands per chemisorbed Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 molecule are released from the surface as CH 4 . This indicates that Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 predominantly binds bifunctionally to the surface, i.e., on two surface groups, expectedly creating predominantly ͑-O -͒ 2 Al͑CH 3 ͒ surface groups. For thermal ALD with H 2 O as oxidant source, values between n = 1 and n = 2 have been reported by QMS and QCM for the 150-350 °C range. The values are somewhat closer to n = 2 at the lower temperature side, whereas QCM yielded also somewhat higher values than QMS over the full temperature range. 24</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Investigation of reaction products by QMS</head><p>The gas species injected in the reactor as well as the stable gas species created by the surface reactions were measured using QMS. To achieve sufficient time resolution, the measurement procedure as outlined in the experimental section ͑Sec. II B͒ was employed. The QMS signals of the m / z ratios which showed the largest response to the ALD process are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>  During Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing peaks can be observed at m / z =15 ͑CH 3 + ͒ and, albeit less clear due to the O 2 background, also at m / z =16 ͑CH 4 + ͒. On the basis of cracking pattern information, it can be concluded that CH 4 is released from the surface during precursor dosing. Similar to thermal ALD, the detection of CH 4 indicates that the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 precursor chemisorbs to the surface through a reaction, in which H is removed from the surface by forming gaseous CH 4 with a -CH 3 ligand of the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 . During the plasma exposure peaks appear at m / z =18 ͑H 2 O + ͒, 44 ͑CO 2 + ͒, and 28 ͑CO + ͒, signaling the production of H 2 O, CO 2 , and possibly CO as discussed in our previous work. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> Furthermore the consumption of oxygen during the plasma exposure can be clearly observed by the decrease of signal at m / z = 16 and 32.</p><p>The CO + signal has a comparable intensity during the plasma exposure as the CO 2 + signal. On the basis of the CO 2 cracking pattern reported in literature ͑m / z = 44: 100% normalized peak height, m / z = 28: 10%͒ it is therefore conceivable that CO is present in the deposition chamber. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">54</ref> The deviation from the literature values for CO 2 can, however, also be attributed to a lower transmission of high masses in the mass spectrometer. A dedicated experiment has, therefore, been performed to investigate the ratio of CO and CO 2 in the plasma by calibrating our mass spectrometer signals. CO 2 and CO gas from lecture bottles was introduced separately into the deposition reactor and a cracking spectrum of both species was determined at a pressure of 7.5 mTorr. The cracking of CO 2 was found to lead to the detection of mainly CO 2 + ͑m / z = 44: 100%͒, CO + ͑m / z = 28: 18%͒, O + ͑m / z = 16: 25%͒, and C + ͑m / z = 12: 20%͒. The cracking of CO led to the detection of mainly CO + ͑100%͒ and some O + ͑4%͒ and C + ͑7%͒. To determine the gas composition at the start of the plasma exposure during processing, an experiment was carried out in which O 2 gas was mixed with CO and CO 2 in the reactor keeping the total pressure constant at 7.5 mTorr. From tuning the ratio of O 2 , CO, and CO 2 to the peak height of the signals measured during processing, an estimate of the gas composition could be determined. On the basis of these measurements it was found that the concentrations of CO and CO 2 in the plasma are comparable in magnitude and that they form a substantial part of the total gas composition at the start of the plasma exposure ͑ϳ7 and ϳ5 vol % for CO and CO 2 , respectively͒.</p><p>These results indicate that during the O 2 plasma exposure the surface bonded -CH 3 ligands are removed by combustionlike reactions, while the Al atoms at the surface are oxidized to form an Al 2 O 3 film. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> In the combustionlike reactions H 2 O and CO 2 are produced, whereas the origin of CO could either be through incomplete combustion of the surface ligands or through dissociation of CO 2 in the plasma. On the basis of the current mass spectrometry measurements these production mechanisms of CO cannot be uniquely distinguished from each other.</p><p>During the plasma exposure a signal rise can also be observed at m / z =15 ͑this is most clear during the second cycle shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>, where the m / z = 28 and m / z = 44 sig- nals have been omitted for clarity͒. The m / z = 15 peak is smaller in height and appears to be about twice as short in time when compared to the CO, CO 2 , and H 2 O peaks. The observation of a signal at m / z = 15 indicates the formation of CH 4 during the plasma step. A direct observation of CH 4 through the detection of CH 4</p><p>+ at m / z = 16 is obscured by a decrease in O + signal ͑also at m / z =16͒ due to the consumption of O 2 . It is conceivable that CH 4 is produced in a concurrent thermal ALD-like reaction pathway in which H 2 O, available from the combustionlike reactions, is consumed in reactions with neighboring -CH 3 groups to form -OH groups at the surface. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> The fact that this peak is observed for shorter time than the other peaks could be related to the limited availability of -CH 3 at the surface due to the competition with the combustionlike reactions.</p><p>The gas phase species were also monitored by QMS for ALD cycles which included the use of 15 successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref> the QMS signals for the massto-charge ratios of m / z =15 ͑CH 3 + ͒ and m / z =27 ͑Al + ͒ are shown. The ratio m / z = 27 can be attributed to the cracking of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 in the mass spectrometer, whereas m / z = 15 can be attributed to cracking of both Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and CH 4 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">55</ref> Simultaneously, QCM measurements were carried out to monitor film growth as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑c͒</ref>. In this part of the figure the precursor dosing and plasma exposure have also been indicated. Unfortunately, already during the recovery of the QCM signal from the plasma induced artifact, the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing was started, which partly obscured the mass uptake. Still the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposure can be observed as a sharp increase in mass uptake in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑c͒</ref>. The recovery of the signal from the plasma interference continues during the subsequent exposures of the precursor. It is evident that the mass uptake by QCM is accompanied by a sharp peak in the CH 3 + signal which is considerably higher for the first few Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures ͓see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑a͔͒</ref>. Since no signal for Al + is observed during these first few exposures, we can attribute the first few peaks in CH 3 + signal to the cracking of CH 4 generated by the chemisorption of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 on the surface, as reported above. The peak intensities of the CH 3 + signal gradually decreases with the number of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures since less and less precursor chemisorps with each succeeding Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposure. After five to six Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures the CH 3 + peaks reach approximately a constant intensity at each additional exposure, whereas also a signal for Al + is now observed in the QMS data ͓see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑b͔͒</ref>. For the remainder of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures, the Al + and CH 3 + signal intensities have roughly the same peak height and both signals correlate to the dissociation of unreacted Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 in the QMS. Also after five to six Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures no more mass uptake is observed with the QCM ͓see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑c͔͒</ref>, indicating that the surface reactions have reached saturation. These observations agree well with the growth rate saturation curves obtained by SE and QCM shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3</ref>. Since QMS is a volume based technique, the aforementioned observations indicate that all surfaces, i.e., not only the surface of the QCM crystal or the substrate, but also the reactor walls, are saturatively covered with Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 precursor after five to six successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures. The measurements in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref> also indicate that the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 introduced into the reactor is fully consumed by the surface reactions for the first five to six Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures. Only when the surface reactions have saturated a significant density of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 can build up in the gas phase leading to a QMS signal.</p><p>Another detail about the reaction mechanism is revealed by the QMS signal at m / z = 27 during the plasma exposure in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7͑a͒</ref>. A relatively high peak can be observed at m / z = 27 during the plasma step and the signal intensity is more than a factor of 5 larger than that during Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing. From a careful investigation of the other signals in the m / z = 24-28 range we came to the conclusion that larger hydrocarbons ͑C 2 H x ͒ are also present in the gas phase during the plasma exposure. This was not evident from our previous experiments, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> as the signal at m / z = 28 consists of contributions of CO + as well as C 2 H 4 + . The absolute signals ͑ion current ϳ3 ϫ 10 -11 A͒ at m / z = 26 and 27 are, however, a factor of 10 smaller compared to the CO + and CH 4</p><p>+ signals. On the basis of cracking pattern and cross-section data <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">57</ref> it can be inferred that the production of these higher hydrocarbons is only a minor effect. It indicates, however, an alternative, third pathway in plasma-assisted ALD next to the already discussed combustionlike and thermal ALD-like reactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Monitoring excited plasma species and reaction products by OES</head><p>Specific to plasma-assisted ALD is the emission of light by plasma species during the plasma exposure step. This light emission provides an additional tool in the study of the gas composition and chemistry as the emission lines observed originate from radiative de-excitation of the gas species present in the plasma. These gas species can be both reactant or reaction products, and consequently these species can be identified by the use of optical emission spectroscopy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8͑a͒</ref> the emission spectrum of a pure O 2 plasma is shown as collected in the proximity of the position of the substrate holder. The use of a quartz window provided better sensitivity in the UV region Ͻ350 nm compared to our earlier results in which a glass window was applied. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> The identification of the various emission lines is given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8͑a͒</ref>. In the spectra mainly emission lines of excited O radicals ͑denoted as O * ͒ and of O 2 + ions from the first ͑b 4 ⌺ g -a 4 ⌸ u ͒ and second ͑A 2 ⌸ u -X 2 ⌸ u ͒ negative systems are visible. This emission gives rise to the greenish color of the plasma which can also be observed around the substrate holder as shown in the photograph in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8͑c͒</ref>. The photograph is taken from a window fitted at the side of the deposition chamber.</p><p>When an Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose has preceded the plasma exposure, the emission in the first hundreds of milliseconds of the plasma exposure is remarkably different from that of the pure O 2 plasma. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> In the spectrum, taken at 200 ms after the start of the plasma exposure, an intense broadband emission in the blue region can be observed ͓Fig. 8͑b͔͒. The plasma appears bluish to the naked eye, as is also apparent from the photograph in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8͑d͒</ref>. From identification of the spectral lines, the broadband emission was found to be predominantly originating from excited CO * molecules. The bands from the Angström ͑B 1 ⌺ + -A 1 ⌸ i ͒, Herzberg ͑C 1 ⌺ + -A 1 ⌸ i ͒, and third positive ͑b 3 ⌺ +a 3 ⌸ r ͒ systems of CO * as well as the Comet tail ͑A 2 ⌸ i -X 2 ⌺ + ͒ and Baldet-Johnson ͑B 2 ⌺ + -A 2 ⌸ i ͒ systems of the CO + * ion were identified as indicated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8͑b͒</ref>. Also the emission by atomic hydrogen ͑H ␣ and H ␤ ͒ and atomic oxygen ͑777 and 845 nm͒ can be observed. In the UV region, OH * emission ͑A 2 ⌺ + -X 2 ⌸͒ can be clearly distinguished from its typical band head structure around 309 nm as well as CO 2 + * from the double band structure ͑⌫ 2 ⌺ + -X 2 ⌸͒ present at 288.4 and 289.5 nm. Other lines in this UV region can most probably be assigned to CO * , in particular, to its third positive ͑b 3 ⌺ +a 3 ⌸ r ͒ system, however, also the observation of lines from Al * and Al + * ͓e.g., Al at 309.3 nm ͑3s 2 3d -3s 2 3p͒ and Al + at 281.6 nm ͑3s4s -3s3p͒, 286.8 nm ͑3s9p -3s3d͒, and 308.9 nm ͑3s6d -3s4p͔͒ cannot be excluded. Furthermore, the O 2 + * ion emission and O * radical emission are reduced in intensity at this early time after the start of the plasma exposure in the ALD cycle when compared to the emission during the continuous plasma operation ͓Fig. 8͑a͔͒. The CO * , OH * , and H * emission most probably originates from excitation reactions of the molecules by electron impact. The excitation can either result from dissociative ex- citation or ionization of H 2 O and CO 2 reaction products or from direct excitation and ionization of CO and H: 58 H 2 O + e -→ OH * + H + e - → OH + H * + e -, ͑6͒ H + e -→ H * + e -, CO 2 + e -→ CO * + O + e - → CO + * + O + 2e -, ͑7͒ CO + e -→ CO * + e → CO + * + 2e -. ͑8͒</p><p>The threshold for these reactions is in the range of 10-25 eV, which are energies not uncommon in the inductively coupled plasma for electrons within the high energy tail of the electron energy distribution. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">58</ref> The possible presence of Al emission lines could potentially be related to a small fraction of ͑physisorbed͒ Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 residing in the reactor after precursor dosing ͑see Sec. IV A͒. When the surface reactions are completed and the reaction products are being pumped away, the reaction product related emission decreases. When approaching the end of the plasma exposure the emission is again identical to that of a pure O 2 plasma. Observed by the naked eye, it appears that a kind of blue "flash," i.e. blue to green transition, occurs during the plasma exposure of each ALD cycle. <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">59</ref> In Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> the time-resolved emission at 519 nm ͑CO * , Angström system v-vЈ =0-2͒, at 656 nm ͑H * ,H ␣ ͒, and 777 nm ͑O * , 3p 5 P -3s 5 S͒ is shown for both a pure O 2 plasma strike and one which was preceded by an Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose ͑i.e., during an ALD cycle͒. During a pure O 2 plasma exposure ͓Fig. 9͑a͔͒ it can be observed that a stable O * emission is present at 777 nm instantly when the plasma was ignited. No significant emission signal is observed at 519 and 656 nm. When the plasma was ignited during the ALD cycle, a clear increase in emission at 519 and 656 nm can be observed at the beginning of the plasma exposure due to the build up of reaction products CO, ͑CO 2 , and H 2 O͒ in the gas phase ͓see Fig. <ref type="figure">9͑b͔͒</ref>. This increase is followed by a decrease in emission of the reactants due to the removal of the species by pumping when the surface reactions reach saturation. In the beginning of the plasma pulse the consumption of O radicals is also apparent from the initially lower emission intensity at 777 nm. This O * emission is lower as oxygen is used to generate CO, CO 2 and H 2 O reaction products as well as to oxidize the Al on the surface. Subsequently, the O * intensity increases and at the end of the plasma exposure it levels off at the same height as in a pure O 2 plasma.</p><p>Besides giving insight into the reaction mechanisms, the time dependent OES signals in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> also yield insight into the plasma exposure time necessary for reaching saturation. From the time-resolved signal of the CO * and H * emission, for which a 1 / e decay time of ϳ300 ms can be determined, it can be concluded that the surface reactions and removal of reactants during the plasma step occur in a time span well within 1 s. This was corroborated by in situ spectroscopic ellipsometry measurements of films deposited under different plasma conditions. These measurements revealed a saturation of the growth rate for plasma exposure times Ͼ0. FIG. 10. ͑Color online͒ Integrated intensity of the time-resolved OES measurements of CO*, H*, and O* during the plasma step of the ALD cycle as a function of the number of successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures used in the cycle.</p><p>of oxygen consumed can also be observed to increase in the nonsaturated region by a decrease in the integrated O * emission with increasing Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. QMS and OES results on the FlexAL reactor</head><p>To test the general validity of the results obtained on the ALD-I reactor, QMS and OES studies were also performed during the deposition of Al 2 O 3 in the FlexAL reactor. The experiments were carried out without heating the reactor walls and substrate holder, i.e., at 25 °C. At this temperature a considerable fraction of the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 might be in the dimer phase. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> However, to the best of our knowledge, there have been no reports that this dimer phase has a substantial influence on the surface chemistry during ALD at low temperatures.</p><p>Measurements by QMS, which had a better signal-tonoise ratio at higher m / z ratios for the FlexAL than for the ALD-I reactor, revealed signals at m / z =57 ͓Al͑CH 3 ͒ 2 + ͔, m / z =42 ͓Al͑CH 3 ͒ + ͔, m / z =27 ͑Al + ͒, and m / z =15 ͑CH 3 + ͒ for the unreacted precursor. The peak heights were found to correspond well to the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 cracking pattern reported under room temperature conditions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">55</ref> In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">11</ref> the time dependent signals of selected masses are given for a number of ALD cycles covering the same span as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>. The moment of precursor dosing ͑20 ms duration͒ and period of plasma exposure ͑4 s duration͒ have been indicated. The chemisorption of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 can be observed through the detection of CH 4 , both on m / z =15 ͑CH 3 + ͒ and m / z =16 ͑CH 4 + ͒ as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">11</ref>. During precursor injection the signal rises also slightly for m / z = 32. This increase is smaller than for m / z = 16 and we attribute the increase at m / z = 32 to the pressure increase in the QMS induced by the precursor injection. Albeit less clear, during the plasma exposure a decrease in the signals at m / z = 16 and 32 can also be observed similar to the case in the ALD-I reactor as discussed above. This decrease can be explained by the consumption of oxygen by the oxidation of the surface and the production of combustionlike reaction products.</p><p>These reaction products created during the plasma step are observed at m / z =28 ͑CO + ͒ and m / z =44 ͑CO 2 + ͒. From the relative intensity of the CO + and CO 2 + signals, it can be concluded that both CO 2 and CO are present in the plasma similar to the case in the ALD-I reactor. The production of H 2 O during the plasma exposure cannot be distinguished at m / z = 18. The absence of a clear signal rise at m / z = 18 can be attributed to the relatively high pressure and therefore high background signal in the QMS on the FlexAL reactor in comparison with the QMS on the ALD-I reactor. The background signal at m / z = 18 is approximately a factor of 10 higher in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">11</ref> than in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>, while the signal at m / z = 32 due to the O 2 injected is quite comparable for the FlexAL and ALD-I. The signal at m / z = 32 is only slightly higher in the FlexAL due to the higher operating pressure in the reactor ͑15 mTorr instead of 7.5 mTorr͒. The higher background pressure due to residual gases in the QMS and the corresponding higher baseline signal for m / z =18 ͑H 2 O + due to residual H 2 O͒ prevent therefore the detection of the relatively small H 2 O levels generated during the plasma exposure step. A factor contributing to the higher H 2 O pressure and background H 2 O signal could be the lower wall temperature used in the experiments on the FlexAL reactor compared to the ALD-I reactor. This lower wall temperature will complicate efficient pumping of H 2 O produced in the combustionlike reactions given the short cycle time of 7.5 s. This will lead to a built up to a relatively high H 2 O background pressure in the reactor and mass spectrometer. Although a clear H 2 O signal rise is absent during the plasma exposure, an increase at m / z = 15 is still clearly observed providing evidence that the concurrent thermal ALD-like reactions are taking place in addition to the combustionlike reactions. This is an indirect indication of H 2 O production during the plasma exposure step. Furthermore, similar as in the experiments on the ALD-I reactor a mass scan of m / z = 20-30 in the FlexAL revealed the presence of small amounts of larger hydrocarbons ͑C 2 H x ͒ during the plasma exposure as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>. Compared to the CH 4 + and CO + signals during the plasma exposure step, the signals due to the higher hydrocarbons were approximately ten times lower in magnitude ͑ion current of ϳ3 ϫ 10 -12 A͒. Similar to the case of the ALD-I setup ͑see Sec. III C͒, it can be inferred from this data that the production of these higher hydrocarbons is a minor effect.</p><p>In comparison to the QMS results obtained on the ALD-I setup, the signals at the various m / z ratios decay with longer time constants for the FlexAL reactor. For a part, these longer time constants can be attributed to a longer residence time in the FlexAL reactor. When the decay of the m / z =16 signal during Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposure is fitted with a single exponential value, = ϳ 0.17 s and = ϳ 0.45 s are found for the ALD-I and FlexAL reactor, respectively. Both values are close to the mean residence time t R in the ALD-I ͑t R = ϳ 0.2 s͒ and FlexAL ͑t R = ϳ 0.4 s͒. However, during the plasma exposure there appears to be another effect. The characteristic decay times of CO and CO 2 appear to be much longer ͑ ϳ 6 s͒ in the FlexAL reactor than what would generally be expected on the basis of the residence time of t R = ϳ 0.4 s. For the ALD-I reactor this is not observed and the characteristic decay times of CO and CO 2 are similar to the residence time ͑t R = ϳ 0.2 s͒. This discrepancy is not yet understood.</p><p>As described in Sec. II B, the OES measurements on the FlexAL were performed through a quartz window at the top of the plasma source. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">13͑a͒</ref>  FIG. 13. ͑Color online͒ ͑a͒ OES from a pure O 2 plasma and ͑b͒ from the O 2 plasma after a preceding Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose recorded in the first 200 ms after the plasma strike. The spectra were taken through the top viewport on the plasma source of the Oxford Instruments FlexAL reactor. The different peaks have been identified in the spectra and the saturation level of the spectrometer is indicated.</p><p>the production of CO, CO 2 , and H 2 O reaction products. The presence of CO in the plasma can indicate incomplete combustion reactions but can also be cause by the dissociation of CO 2 in the plasma. ͑vi͒ CH 4 is also a reaction product during the O 2 plasma exposure step. From the height of the CH 4 signal and its time response, it is concluded that the CH 4 is created in a concurrent thermal ALD-like reaction pathway initiated by the H 2 O produced in the combustionlike reactions of the -CH 3 groups. This secondary reaction competes with the combustionlike reactions. It is, however, a minor effect as it requires first the production of H 2 O, while it can only be significant during the time when there are still -CH 3 groups present at the surface. ͑vii͒ The presence of higher hydrocarbons ͑C 2 H x ͒ is also observed during the O 2 plasma exposure step indicating a possible third reaction pathway. ͑vii͒ At the beginning of the plasma exposure step, large quantities of reaction products are released into the plasma because Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 has been chemisorbed at all internal surfaces of the reactor. This leads to significant disturbance of the O 2 plasma properties as the reaction products undergo ionization and dissociation reactions in the plasma.</p><p>On the basis of these observations the following qualitative picture of the reaction mechanism during plasmaassisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 can be deduced. The surface reactions during Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing in plasma-assisted ALD appear to be very similar to those in thermal ALD. In both cases CH 4 is released as a reaction product during the chemisorption of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 on the surface. For both plasma-assisted ALD and thermal ALD it appears that Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 chemisorbs mostly bifunctionally on the surface, at least at the low substrate temperatures investigated. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> Information on the surface groups involved during Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 chemisorption cannot be directly deduced from the data. However, from the fact that CH 4 is released from the surface, it can be concluded that H atoms are available on the surface for the reaction with the -CH 3 ligands of the chemisorbing Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 .</p><p>The oxidation step during plasma-assisted ALD is very different from the oxidation step during thermal ALD with H 2 O. Oxygen radicals are the dominant species in an ͑inductively coupled͒ O 2 plasma <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">60</ref> and therefore rule the surface reactions during the oxidation step. These O radicals are consumed in the oxidation of the Al atoms on the surface and the combustion of the -CH 3 surface groups. This consumption of O radicals leads to a change in the mass balance in the plasma, decreasing the O and O 2 density levels during the time interval that the surface reactions take place. The reaction of the O radicals with the -CH 3 surface groups leads to several reaction products. Most important is the combustion of the -CH 3 surface groups leading to CO, CO 2 , and H 2 O reaction products in the gas phase. The fact that CO is observed in the plasma can indicate incomplete combustion reaction, however, from the data reported CO production from incomplete combustion cannot be distinguished unambiguously from the production of CO in the gas phase by dissociation of CO 2 molecules in the plasma. This latter reaction will certainly also take place. A second reaction pathway during the O 2 plasma step is initiated by the H 2 O produced by the combustionlike reactions. Once H 2 O is produced from a -CH 3 surface group it can react with a neighboring -CH 3 surface group by a thermal ALD-like reaction. This secondary reaction competes therefore with the combustionlike reactions but it can only take place during the time when there are still -CH 3 groups present at the surface. This reaction pathway becomes insignificant at the moment when almost all -CH 3 surface groups are reacted away by the combustionlike reactions. A third reaction pathway is indicated by the observation of higher hydrocarbon species ͑C 2 H x ͒ in the plasma. The observation of such higher hydrocarbons suggests that the oxygen radicals are not effective in combusting all -CH 3 surface groups. Consequently, it makes it more plausible that the combustionlike surface reactions are incomplete and that CO is also directly produced at the surface. The production of higher hydrocarbon species appears to be a minor effect, however, some of the higher hydrocarbon species can also be oxidized by combustionlike reactions with oxygen species in the gas phase. <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">61</ref> The higher hydrocarbon species can be generated at the surface by reaction mechanisms as proposed by Elliott et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> When O radicals attack the bonds within the -Al-CH 3 surface groups, intermediate surface groups can be formed such as -Al-O-CH 3 ͑methoxy groups͒ or -Al-CH 2 OH. Subsequently, volatile higher hydrocarbon species ͑C 2 H x ͒ can be formed. For example, by association reactions between neighboring -CH 2 surface groups, ethene ͑C 2 H 4 ͒ can be formed. On the basis of first principles density functional theory calculations it has been found that such reaction pathways might be energetically favored over combustionlike reactions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> It should, however, be noted that the preference for certain surface reaction pathways is also determined by the flux of the incoming O radicals. During the O 2 plasma exposure there is a relatively high flux of O radicals to the surface, <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">60</ref> which can cause the combustionlike reactions to be favored.</p><p>Although the reaction mechanism presented can explain most observations and is expected to describe the main surface reactions, other and additional reaction mechanisms can not be excluded. For example, an alternative explanation for the formation of higher hydrocarbons can be sought in the presence of physisorbed Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 at the surface during the precursor exposure. While it should be noted that Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 will predominantly chemisorb, a small fraction of physisorbed Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 can possibly be present, in particular, at high precursor doses and low substrate temperatures as under these conditions, adsorbed Al 2 ͑CH 3 ͒ 6 multilayers have been reported ͑albeit at much higher gas pressures͒. <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">62</ref> During the plasma exposure the physisorbed molecules will be released into the gas phase and subsequently be dissociated by the plasma. The fragmented hydrocarbon species can associate to form higher hydrocarbons and can explain the observation of C 2 H x species by mass spectrometry ͓see Figs. 7͑b͒ and 12͔. In addition, this effect can explain the possible presence of Al * and Al + * emission lines in the plasma although these lines cannot be unambiguously distinguished from the spec- The large quantities of reaction products that are released into the plasma at the beginning of the plasma step have a substantial effect on the plasma properties. The reaction products become dissociated and ionized in the plasma, thus changing the composition of the plasma significantly. As a consequence the impedance of the plasma can also be altered, which might affect plasma power coupling and drift in the optimum power matching conditions. In addition the change in plasma composition can also lead to secondary effects at the surface, for example, redeposition reactions can occur. These effects, caused by the surface reaction products, increase in importance with increasing inner surface area of the reactor because under saturated conditions Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 has been chemisorbed at all internal surfaces of the reactor.</p><p>As mentioned earlier, information on the surface groups created after O 2 plasma exposure of the -CH 3 terminated surface cannot directly be deduced from the reaction product data. The fact that CH 4 is released from the surface during Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing indicates, however, that H atoms are present at the surface after O 2 plasma exposure. This aspect, as well as the observation that the temperature dependence of the growth rate per cycle of plasma-assisted and thermal ALD show remarkable similarities 3 ͑most notably at higher substrate temperatures͒ might suggest the presence of hydroxyl ͑-OH͒ surface groups after the O 2 plasma step. Such -OH surface groups can possibly be created directly in the combustionlike reactions, but they can also be created indirectly by the H 2 O molecules generated at the surface in the combustionlike reactions. The presence of -OH surface groups after the oxidation step has also been predicted for ALD of Al 2 O 3 using O 3 as oxidant source <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> although experimental investigations showed some variance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> Possible differences between results obtained with O 3 as oxidant source and between the O 3 and O 2 plasma case can possibly be attributed to differences in the flux of reactive species to the surface during the oxidation step. A difference in flux and related surface chemistry can also possibly explain differences in growth rates per cycle observed for the different oxidant sources. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> More insight into the surface reactions and the surface groups present after the O 2 plasma step will be provided by in situ infrared spectroscopy measurements of the surface groups. These infrared spectroscopy measurements are currently carried out and will be reported in a future publication. <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">63</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Consequences for other plasma-assisted ALD processes</head><p>The qualitative picture of the reaction mechanism for plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 described above can most probably be generalized to other plasma-assisted ALD processes of metal oxide films employing O 2 plasma as oxidant source. It is expected that the reaction mechanism is similar when using other metal alkyl compounds as precursor, whereas it is also anticipated that roughly the same reaction mechanism holds for oxide films deposited by ALD from metal organic precursors and O 2 plasmas in general. During the precursor dosing, the chemisorption reactions are expected to specifically depend on the precursor, most notably on the nature of its organic ligands. The O 2 plasma step is, however, expected to be ruled by combustionlike reactions due to the large O flux in an O 2 plasma. Also secondary reactions such as initiated by H 2 O by-products are expected to play a role for other plasma-assisted ALD processes employing metal organic precursors. In addition, for other metal organic compounds ͑metal alkoxide, alkylamide, betadiketonate, etc.͒ also other types of reaction products than CO 2 , CO, H 2 O, and hydrocarbon species might be formed during the O 2 plasma step depending on the atomic composition of the organic ligands. For example, for metal alkylamide precursors and O 2 plasma, the formation of CN and NO-related species can be anticipated. The level of influence of these and other reaction products on the plasma properties depends on the ALD process characteristics. For example, when the precursor does not chemisorb on the reactor walls for a cold-wall reactor, the influence of the reaction products released from the heated substrate holder during the O 2 plasma step will be relatively minor. Insight in these and other aspects of plasma-assisted ALD of metal oxides from metal organic precursors and O 2 plasma can be obtained relatively easy by mass spectrometry and optical emission spectroscopy studies as shown in this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The reaction mechanism of the plasma-assisted ALD process of Al 2 O 3 from Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing and O 2 plasma exposure was investigated. Results were combined from four complementary in situ diagnostics. With spectroscopic ellipsometry and quartz crystal microbalance measurements, the thickness increase and mass gain per cycle was monitored, whereas with quadrupole mass spectrometry and optical emission spectroscopy, the reaction products created during the ALD surface reactions were investigated. Aspects such as Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 chemisorption and its saturation behavior, combustionlike reactions and additional reaction pathways during O 2 plasma exposure leading to hydrocarbon species, and the influence of the reaction products on the O 2 plasma properties were discussed. From a comparison with thermal ALD of Al 2 O 3 and the main observations made, a qualitative picture of the reaction mechanism of plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 was presented. To achieve a higher level of understanding of the reaction mechanism, experimental data on the surface functional groups created by the ALD half-reactions will be required. Such information can be obtained by infrared spectroscopy measurements that are currently carried out for plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 .</p><p>It has also been discussed that the results on the reaction mechanism obtained for Al 2 O 3 can most probably be generalized for plasma-assisted processes of metal oxides employing metal alkyl compounds and even for metal organic precursors in general. From the results presented in this work, it has become clear that considerable insight into the reaction mechanisms of plasma-assisted ALD processes of other metal oxides can be obtained by common diagnostics such as quadrupole mass spectrometry and optical emission spectros-copy. Especially optical emission spectroscopy has turned out to be a relatively simple and inexpensive diagnostic which can easily be applied to ͑commercial͒ plasma-assisted ALD reactors while providing much more information than only the oxygen species present in the steady-state O 2 plasma employed. The in situ diagnostics will therefore also be employed in future studies of the plasma-assisted ALD processes of other metal oxide films deposited from different kinds of metal organic precursors.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. ͑Color online͒ ͑a͒ Schematic of the homebuilt remote plasma ALD reactor "ALD-I" with the in situ diagnostics indicated. ͑b͒ Schematic layout of the plasma-assisted ALD cycle for Al 2 O 3 deposition. The precursor dosing by several successive, small Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures per cycle is indicated.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,316.21,49.77,240.00,343.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIG. 2. ͑Color online͒ Thickness of Al 2 O 3 as a function of the number of cycles as measured by SE for deposition temperatures of 70 and 200 °C. The data shown are for films deposited on plasma oxidized c-Si substrates.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,52.80,49.77,240.00,192.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIG. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>FIG. 4. ͑Color online͒ QCM measurements during plasma-assisted ALD of Al 2 O 3 at a deposition temperature of 70 °C. The mass gain is shown for ten reaction cycles with the length of one ALD cycle being indicated. The precursor dose is smaller than necessary for saturation of the surface reactions.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,52.80,49.76,240.00,195.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>for two ALD cycles. The most likely parent molecules leading to the signals shown have been indicated in the figure. As mentioned earlier, the signals can either be due to direct ionization or dissociative ionization ͑cracking͒ of the corresponding molecule. Since a continuous O 2 flow was used a relatively high signal was measured at m / z =32 ͑O 2 + ͒ and m / z =16 ͑O + ͒ due to the ͑dissociative͒ ionization of O 2 in the mass spectrometer. Furthermore, a relatively high signal at m / z = 18 was measured ͑ion current of 4.5ϫ 10 -12 A͒ which can be attributed to H 2 O. It is generally difficult to remove H 2 O from the vacuum system, including both the ALD reactor and the differentially pumped QMS housing. The other masses which are shown in Fig. 6 are m / z =15 ͑CH 3 + ͒, 28 ͑CO + ͒, and 44 ͑CO 2 + ͒. These signals have their baseline close to the noise level of the mass spec-trometer ͑ion current of 10 -13 A͒. For clarity purposes, the m / z = 28 and m / z = 44 signals are omitted during the second cycle in Fig. 6.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>FIG. 6. ͑Color online͒ Time-resolved QMS for two plasma-assisted ALD cycles of Al 2 O 3 . The most likely parent molecules contributing to the signals at the selected mass-to-charge ratios ͑m / z͒ are indicated. For clarity purposes, the m / z =28 and m / z = 44 signals are omitted during the second cycle.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,52.80,49.76,240.00,158.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIG. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>FIG. 7. ͑Color online͒ ͑a͒ QMS signal at m / z =15 and ͑b͒ at m / z = 27 during an experiment in which 15 successive Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures per cycle were applied. During the Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures, the signal at m / z = 27 can be attributed to Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 and the signal at m / z =15 to both CH 4 and Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 . During plasma exposure the signal at m / z = 27 can most probably be attributed to C 2 H 3 + created by dissociative ionization from higher hydrocarbon species. ͑c͒ Corresponding mass gain as measured by QCM. The Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 exposures are indicated by vertical tic marks in ͑c͒.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,316.21,49.76,240.00,411.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIG. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>FIG.8. ͑Color online͒ ͑a͒ OES from a pure O 2 plasma and ͑b͒ from the plasma after a preceding Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dose recorded in the first 200 ms after the plasma strike. The different emission lines have been identified in the figure.͑c͒ and ͑d͒ show photographs of the plasma corresponding to ͑a͒ and ͑b͒, respectively. The photographs are taken through the viewport at the side of the reactor and show the downstream region where the substrate holder is located.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,50.07,49.77,360.00,288.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><figDesc>FIG. 9. ͑Color online͒ Time-resolved OES measurements at the wavelengths of 519, 656, and 777 nm corresponding to CO*, H*, and O*, respectively. ͑a͒ Emission for an O 2 plasma without preceding Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing and ͑b͒ the emission for a plasma exposure step during an ALD cycle.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,52.80,49.77,240.00,175.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>FIG. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>FIG. 11. ͑Color online͒ Time-resolved QMS during several plasma-assisted ALD cycles of Al 2 O 3 carried out in the Oxford Instruments FlexAL reactor. The most likely parent molecules contributing to the signals at the selected mass-to-charge ratios ͑m / z͒ are given. The Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 dosing and plasma exposures are indicated in the figure.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,52.80,49.76,240.00,166.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>O 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIG. 12. ͑Color online͒ Bar graph mass spectrum during the O 2 plasma step as composed from the time-resolved quadrupole mass spectrometry ͑QMS͒ measurements carried out in the Oxford Instruments FlexAL reactor. The spectrum has been corrected for ͑background͒ signals during regular O 2 plasma operation and shows therefore only species that are related to the ALD surface reactions taking place during the O 2 plasma step. The most likely ions contributing to the signals at the selected mass-to-charge ratios ͑m / z͒ are indicated.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,52.80,49.76,240.00,188.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>103302- 12 tra</head><label>12</label><figDesc>in Figs. 8͑b͒ and 13͑b͒ due to the interfering presence of OH * , CO 2 + * , and CO * lines in the UV region.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,0.00,-0.00,116.21,852.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,130.00,645.29,435.00,116.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors acknowledge <rs type="person">A.J.M. Mackus</rs> and <rs type="person">P. Kudlacek</rs> for their assistance with the measurements and <rs type="person">Dr. R. Engeln</rs> for the fruitful discussions. M.J.F. van de Sande, <rs type="person">W. Keuning</rs>, and <rs type="person">J.J.A. Zeebregts</rs> are thanked for their skilful technical assistance. The authors would like to thank the reviewer for pointing out the possible presence of Al emission lines and the related consequences. The <rs type="funder">Dutch Technology Foundation STW</rs> is acknowledged for their financial support. The research of W.K. was made possible by a fellowship from the <rs type="funder">Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences ͑KNAW͒</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1940727</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Roh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tsf.2004.09.035</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">476</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Hemmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Klootwijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.2737629</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.1756541</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochem. Solid-State Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Won</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.2177047</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1829773</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ramanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Longdergan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.1859631</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1515951</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Elam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kotula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1570926</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2883" to="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hoex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2240736</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42112" to="042006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Creatore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2338776</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81915" to="082006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1826238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1984082</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11907" to="012005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Groner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2221912</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31915" to="032006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gerenser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jarman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fornalik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1929867</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223503" to="222005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Groner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2168489</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51907" to="052006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Agostinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Delabie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vitanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Alexieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F W</forename><surname>Dekkers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Beaucarne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.solmat.2006.04.014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sol. Energy Mater. Sol. Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bernay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ringuede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Colomban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lincot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cassir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0022-3697(03)00105-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1761" to="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ginestra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sreenivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karthikeyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ramanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mcintyre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.2759606</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochem. Solid-State Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scarel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wiemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fanciulli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pavia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cm0608903</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th AVS Topical Conference on ALD</title>
		<meeting>the 6th AVS Topical Conference on ALD<address><addrLine>Seoul, Korea</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006 ͑unpublished͒</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kudlacek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Engeln</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2357886</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131505" to="132006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Juppo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/la991183+</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2000</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Alaranta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/la010103a</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2001</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Groner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Fabreguette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Elam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/cm0304546</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Greer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1039/b405776g</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Widjaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Musgrave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1473237</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Soto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Tysoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.577226</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date>2686 ͑1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Way</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0039-6028(94)00578-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1995</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mccarley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Klaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Way</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0169-4332(96)00503-X</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1996</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Klaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0040-6090(96)08934-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1997</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">For simplicity only the reaction is given in which Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 reacts with one surface -OH group ͑i.e., monofunctionally͒. As discussed in Ref</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>there is evidence that a considerable fraction of Al͑CH 3 ͒ 3 reacts with two surface -OH groups ͑i.e., bifunctionally͒</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advanced Inorganic Chemistry ͑Interscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cotton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bochmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.apsusc.2004.10.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">245</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1689732</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Puurunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cvde.200306266</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Vap. Deposition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.2344843</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2006</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Knoops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Mackus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2798598</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Laubengayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gilliam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/ja01847a031</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1941</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gutowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/ja01215a027</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<date>2204 ͑1946</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kvisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rytter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0584-8539(84)80153-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Spectrochim. Acta, Part A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1984</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Szymanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Seman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.2779039</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1493" to="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Szymanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Seman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.surfcoat.2007.04.076</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Coat. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2007</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Rocklein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/ac030141u</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absolute calibration of the mass gain proved to be inaccurate because the effective surface area of the QCM was ill defined</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.1433904</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2002" to="2046" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>This is due to the fact that also a part of the backside of the QCM crystal is covered with Al 2 O 3 by ALD</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Hemmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hodson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Klootwijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.2753846</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1357" to="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B S</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kemmeren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roozeboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1116/1.1938981</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">L5 ͑2005͒</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0254-0584(02)00375-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2003</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Niskanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arstila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.1931471</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2005</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1149/1.1628666</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electrochem. Solid-State Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2004</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Matero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sajavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0040-6090(00)00890-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2000</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1039/b109846b</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nist/Epa/Nih</forename><surname>Mass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Spectral</forename><surname>Library</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Data Version NIST05, Software Version 2.0d</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Jiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dejoseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Haaland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Garscadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S1387-3806(00)00258-X</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Mass. Spectrom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2000</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shirai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tabata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Itikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/adnd.2001.0878</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">At. Data Nucl. Data Tables</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2002</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Orient</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/0022-3700/20/15/036</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3923" to="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of Plasma Discharges and Materials Processing ͑Wiley</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">for a movie of the plasma emission during a plasma-assisted ALD cycle. This document can be reached through a direct link in the online article&apos;s HTML reference section or via the EPAPS homepage</title>
		<idno>EPAPS Document No. E-APPLAB-89-331639</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.aip.org/pubservs/epaps.html" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gudmundsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kouznetsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/0022-3727/34/7/312</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Serdyuchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Soltwisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1063/1.2219001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33302" to="032006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ehrlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Osgood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0009-2614(81)80226-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1981</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langereis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keijmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van De Sanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename><surname>Kessels ͑unpublished͒</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
