<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Tris(dialkylamino)aluminums: Syntheses, characterization, volatility comparison and atomic layer deposition of alumina thin films</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Research Corporation Innovation Award</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PCJXaFa #_6VAtsDp">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_YAcWYPv">
					<orgName type="full">IBM Faculty Award, Air Liquide</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2007-04-19">19 April 2007</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Casey</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wade</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Center for Materials Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska-Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>68588-0304</postCode>
									<settlement>Lincoln</settlement>
									<region>NE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carter</forename><surname>Silvernail</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Center for Materials Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska-Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>68588-0304</postCode>
									<settlement>Lincoln</settlement>
									<region>NE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chiranjib</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Center for Materials Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska-Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>68588-0304</postCode>
									<settlement>Lincoln</settlement>
									<region>NE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Axel</forename><surname>Soulet</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">American Air Liquide</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5230 S. East Ave.</addrLine>
									<postCode>60525</postCode>
									<settlement>Countryside</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Mcandrew</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">American Air Liquide</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5230 S. East Ave.</addrLine>
									<postCode>60525</postCode>
									<settlement>Countryside</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Belot</surname></persName>
							<email>jbelot2@unl.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry and Center for Materials Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska-Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>68588-0304</postCode>
									<settlement>Lincoln</settlement>
									<region>NE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Tris(dialkylamino)aluminums: Syntheses, characterization, volatility comparison and atomic layer deposition of alumina thin films</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2007-04-19">19 April 2007</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">87CFFF7C52F16DAAD757864C1134F581</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2007.04.009</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 16 November 2006; accepted 1 April 2007</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-13T11:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">0.8.2-11-gf6b522b3f</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Aluminum</term>
					<term>Precursors</term>
					<term>Alumina</term>
					<term>Vapor pressure</term>
					<term>Thin films</term>
					<term>Atomic layer deposition</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The syntheses and characterization of both tris(diethylamino)aluminum and tris(diisopropylamino)aluminum are presented in this letter. Characterization includes vapor pressure measurements and comparison of the two non-pyrophoric precursors showing them to be viable alternatives to trimethylaluminum. Ultimately, tris(diisopropyl)aluminum was successful in the atomic layer deposition of alumina thin films.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The search for SiO 2 high κ replacements (κ is the dielectric constant) continues to receive considerable attention as complementary metal-oxide semiconductor (CMOS) technology shrinks <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Advancements in this area, pertaining to materials chemistry, test the requirements of ultra-thin film processing of insulating binary or higher order oxides, devoid of impurity atoms (e.g. halides) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. The numerous attributes of these layers (thinness, conformal coverage, compatibility with terminated silicon surfaces, abrupt interfaces, thermal processing, etc.) necessitate both new material developments as well as novel deposition techniques. Concerning the former, various Group III oxides are currently being explored, from Al 2 O 3 to its heavier congeners Ln 2 O 3 (lanthanide 3+ ions). For the latter one promising growth method is atomic layer deposition (ALD) whose layer-by-layer, self-terminating mechanisms ideally offer exquisite control over thin film thickness, interfaces, stoichiometry, and surface roughness to mention only a few possible advantages <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. ALD (and chemical vapor deposition, CVD) may also benefit from new chemical precursor design. Although the desired properties of ALD precursors remain debatable <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, each source must be volatile and show appropriate reactivity at the growth surface. Furthermore, liquid or gaseous sources offer certain industrial and academic advantages. For example, liquids often exhibit weaker intermolecular forces than solids, suggesting higher volatility, and always provide constant surface areas minimizing changes in vapor flux over time and are easier to handle and transfer. Although numerous alumina source molecules have been evaluated, Al 2 (CH 3 ) 6 (and select hydrides) is the most common starting material <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. However, as a hypergolic gas it is not without drawbacksmost important industrially are its dangerous, explosive properties. Thus, novel aluminum sources of similar volatility, decreased ambient atmosphere reactivity, and applicability to ALD or CVD are desirable.</p><p>To assess potential alternatives to trimethylaluminum (TMA) we began investigating homoleptic Al 3+ aminos as ALD precursors <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Previously, this general class of molecules received only modest attention from the thin film community, mostly for the growth of nitrides (or oxides) from solid, crystalline sources <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>. This led us to the development of ultrapure tris(diethylamino)aluminum (Al(DEA) 3 , 1), a liquid, and solid tris(diisopropylamino)aluminum (Al(DIA) 3 , 2) and tris (bis(trimethylsilyl)amino)aluminum (Al(TMSA) 3 ) (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). These materials were hypothesized to show appropriate reactivity for ALD and oxide growth and 1.) their steric bulk should trigger the self-terminating paths and 2.) thermodynamics favor formation of an Al-O bond over the Al-N bond <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. In addition, 1 and 2 show appreciable volatility (vide infra)comparable to that of Al 2 (CH 3 ) 6and were successfully implemented in the growth of amorphous alumina using H 2 O as a coreactant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental</head><p>All manipulations were carried out using standard Schlenk techniques. Lithium aluminum hydride (95%, LiAlH 4 ), aluminum chloride (99.99%, AlCl 3 ), diethylamine (redistilled, 99.5%), and diisopropylamine (redistilled, 99.95%) were purchased from Aldrich and used as received. AlH 3 •N(CH 3 ) 3 was purchased from Gelest and used as received. Benzene and tetrahydrofuran (THF) were dried and distilled from sodium prior to use. Elemental analyses were performed by Midwest Microlabs (Indianapolis, IN, USA) and 1 H NMR was recorded at 400 MHz. The ALD chamber has been previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Synthesis of tris(diethylamino)aluminum (Al(DEA) 3 , 1)</head><p>A 250 mL, 2-neck, round bottom flask charged with a stir bar and LiAlH 4 (2.0 g, 0.053 mol) was sealed with a reflux condenser and a 100 mL addition funnel. Sequentially, the vessel was removed from the glove box, interfaced to a N 2containing Schlenk line and 60 mL of THF was introduced via syringe. Diethylamine (22 mL, 0.21 mol) was then added dropwise (1 drop/s) while stirring at ambient temperature. Fig. 2. Thermogravimetric analysis of Al(DEA) 3 and Al(DIA) 3 at atmospheric pressure and 50 cc/min He purge gas at a 10 °C/min heating rate.  Following complete evolution of H 2 (∼ 30 min), AlCl 3 (2.4 g, 0.018 mol) in 26 mL of THF was added dropwise (2 drops/s) and the mixture heated at reflux for 1 h. Upon cooling to room temperature, the THF was removed via azeotrope distillation with benzene (125 mL) and the mixture concentrated to ∼ 50 mL. The reaction was filtered through a fine porosity fritted funnel and dried in vacuo (25 °C, 0.15 Torr) resulting in an orange oil. Pure Al(DEA) 3 was isolated as a colorless oil via vacuum distillation (150 °C, 10 -4 Torr). Yield 60% (7.7 g); 1 H NMR (δ, C 6 D 6 ) 1.15 (m, 3H); 1.38 (m, 3H), 3.1 (m, 2H), 3.35 (m, 2H); Elem. Anal. Found: C 59.52, H 12.18; Calcd. C 59.22, H 12.42. 2.2. Synthesis of tris(diisopropylamino)aluminum (Al(DIA) 3 , 2)</p><p>63 mL (8.8 eq, 0.45 mol) of diisopropylamine was slowly added (2 drops/s) to a cooled (liquid N 2 ) 250 mL flask containing 4.5 g AlH 3 •N(CH 3 ) 3 (0.051 mol). H 2 evolution was immediately apparent. After amine addition the flask warmed to ambient temperature (2 h) and subsequently heated at reflux overnight. Excess amine was removed in vacuo and the crude product sublimed at 85 °C and 10 -4 Torr to yield colorless crystals (6.9 g, 42%). 1 H NMR (δ, C 6 D 6 ) 1.3 (d, 6H), 3.4 (sept., 1H); Elem. Anal. Found: C 65.84, H 12.82; Calcd. C 66.01, H 12.92.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>The synthetic methods utilized to arrive at these novel alumina precursors have one commonalityto minimize halide content and cost <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The preparation of Al(DEA) 3 uses inexpensive LiAlH 4 as the aluminum source whereas Al(DIA) 3 employs the alane, AlH 3 •NMe 3 . The purpose of these routes was to ultimately reduce contamination and charge carriers in the derived dielectric layer <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. From the atmospheric pressure thermogravimetric analysis (TGA, Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) both precursors evaporate with onset temperatures of 200 °C and 150 °C for 1 and 2, respectively. Although counterintuitive since 1 is a liquid, it is believed to exist as a dimer in this phase but evaporates as the monomer requiring more energy to break its dimeric structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. This is unlike 2 which exists as a monomer, in both the solid and vapor phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The TGA data also supports nearly complete evaporation with little residue at ambient pressure and a 50 cc N 2 flow. Al(DEA) 3 leaves less than 4% residue while under identical conditions Al(DIA) 3 has an initially higher residual of ∼ 10%. This suggests that 2 is more susceptible to atmospheric contamination rather than decomposition, since the percentage varied amongst runs and approaches zero at reduced pressures.</p><p>To evaluate the vapor pressure of these new precursors versus the industry standard trimethylaluminum (Al 2 (CH 3 ) 6 ) measurements were undertaken and fit to a modified Clausius-Clapeyron equation (supplemental information). From these data TMA is significantly more volatile than both Al(DEA) 3 and Al(DIA) 3 , however Al(DIA) 3 is one to two orders of magnitude more volatile than Al(DEA) 3 in the high (N 70 °C) and low temperature (b 70 °C) regimes, respectively. At higher temperatures these values become less disparate but do not cross; thus 2 is always more volatile than 1. Surprisingly both TMA and Al(DEA) 3 are liquids and dinuclear, making them structurally and chemically similar. From this observation we postulate that the greater vapor pressure of Al(DIA) 3 over Al(DEA) 3 is due to its mononuclear character. Although it is typical for liquids to exhibit weaker intermolecular forces, in this case it is a compromise between similar dispersive forces, molecular weight, and the energy required to break dimeric Al(DEA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> .</p><p>All films were deposited on cleaned Si(100) coupons in a previously described hot-walled ALD reactor <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Initially films were grown to optimize suitable delivery conditions for the ALD growth regime using 2 at a constant precursor source temperature of 70 °C (where the vapor pressures of Al(DEA) 3 and Al(DEA) 3 become least disparate). This resulted in a usable parameter of 3, 2 s "plugs" of compound 2. These "plugs" consist of the precursor vessel being slightly pressurized with carrier gas (N 2 , 240 mTorr from 100 mTorr) and then the metal-organic being evacuated into the growth chamber at 100 mTorr. To verify precursor purge time and self limiting growth film, thickness was monitored as a function of seconds, and after 20 s found to be stable and linear (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A</ref>).</p><p>Two additional contributing factors that were investigated were substrate temperature and oxidizer purge time. First it was found that growth became nonlinear beyond 325 °C at which point Al 2 O 3 thickness per cycles increased, presumably due to decomposition at the silicon substrate (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3B</ref>). The second factor was oxidizer delivery, for 2 a 50 ms pulse (carrier gas passed through a water bubbler cooled in an ice bath) followed by a 30 s purge yielded optimal conditions and growth. These H 2 O values are nearly identical to those found for 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Using these conditions the thickness versus number of cycles was linear from 100 Å to 220 Å with an incubation period of 13 Å before growth stabilized at 0.73 Å/cycle (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3C</ref>). Granted these data points do not include thicknesses below 100 Å because reliable values in this regime are hard to obtain in our system.</p><p>The amorphous films were characterized by PXRD and AFM. All attempts to find diffraction peaks failed, even on thicker films, yielding us to conclude they are amorphous despite the complications associated with thinner films and diffraction. The AFM images (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>) of two thin films having thicknesses of 211 Å and 157 Å both have RMS identical roughnesses of 5 Å, over a 1 μm 2 area, at an abrupt atmospheric interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary</head><p>This letter presents the synthesis and characterization of two, non-pyrophoric alternatives for the industry standard TMA -Al(DEA) 3 and Al(DIA) 3 . The compounds were designed to minimize halide content and were synthesized from aluminum hydrides instead of chlorides or heavier halides. The latter was used in the ALD growth of alumina on Si(100) whose conditions are explicitly given for a previously described hotwalled reactor. The derived films were amorphous by PXRD and have abrupt, uniform surfaces with RMS roughnesses of 5 Å.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Structures of tris(diethylamino)aluminum and tris(diisopropyl) aluminum.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,86.51,70.13,143.59,83.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. ALD growth parameters for Al(DIA) 3 . Precursor purge time (A), substrate temperature (B), and growth rate versus the number of cycles with linear fit (C).</figDesc><graphic coords="2,311.53,70.13,231.44,374.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Atomic force micrographs of two Al 2 O 3 films of 211 Å and 157 Å thicknesses both having RMS roughnesses of 5 Å.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,311.02,591.99,232.33,130.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>C.R. Wade et al. / Materials Letters 61 (2007) 5079-5082</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments This work was supported by a <rs type="funder">Research Corporation Innovation Award</rs>, an <rs type="funder">IBM Faculty Award, Air Liquide</rs>, in part by the <rs type="programName">MRSEC program</rs> of the <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> under Award Number <rs type="grantNumber">DMR 0213808</rs>, and <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">CHE-0415938</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_YAcWYPv">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">MRSEC program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PCJXaFa">
					<idno type="grant-number">DMR 0213808</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_6VAtsDp">
					<idno type="grant-number">CHE-0415938</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wilk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anthony</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5243</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Van Dover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3041</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Copel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cartier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gusev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bojarczuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Poppeller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2670</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Raisanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1415</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>De Rouffignac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Vap. Depos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">152</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. Engl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5548</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leskala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">409</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">626</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Matero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rahtu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ritala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lagmuir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3498</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2835</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kovar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ashby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inorg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">893</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brothers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wehmschulte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Olmstead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ruhlandt-Senge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Parkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Power</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organometallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2792</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rangarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Athavale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Economou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">306</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Endle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Silverman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ekerdt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fleurat-Lessard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Volatron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inorg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1849</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Katamreddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jursich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Soulet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Takoudis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Electrochem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">701</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inorg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1955</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
